<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Ubuntu blog</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/feed</link><description>Ubuntu blog feed</description><atom:link href="https://ubuntu.com//blog/feed" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>Python Feedgen</generator><lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 12:05:53 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Native integration available between Canonical LXD and HPE Alletra MP B10000</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/canonical_lxd_hpe_alletra</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Native integration available between Canonical LXD and HPE Alletra MP B10000. The integration combines efficient open source virtualization with high performance, enterprise-grade storage&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;The integration combines efficient open source virtualization with high performance, enterprise-grade storage&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are pleased to announce a new,  native integration between Canonical LXD and HPE Alletra. This integration brings together Canonical’s securely designed, open source virtualization platform with HPE’s enterprise-grade storage to deliver a simple, scalable, high-performance experience. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Enterprise-grade storage meets efficient open source virtualization&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HPE Alletra is designed to deliver mission-critical storage at mid range economics, with a consistent data experience across various cloud environments. With this integration, Canonical LXD and MicroCloud users can now provision and manage Alletra block storage directly through the LXD interface, without the need for any third-party plugins or additional abstraction layers. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The integration enables users to seamlessly create, attach, snapshot, and manage thin-provisioned block volumes as easily as working with local storage, while retaining the full performance, resilience, and enterprise data services of HPE Alletra. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="949" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1571px) 1571px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1571/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fb448%2Fimage.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fb448%2Fimage.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fb448%2Fimage.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fb448%2Fimage.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fb448%2Fimage.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fb448%2Fimage.png 1920w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1571/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fb448%2Fimage.png 1571w" width="1571"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Simplified operations and scalable performance&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HPE Alletra NVMe-based architecture ensures sub-millisecond latency for demanding workloads, with built-in services such as thin-provisioning and data deduplication minimizing storage costs while maintaining consistent performance. Paired with LXD’s lightweight control plane and streamlined UI, users can easily operate their environments, combining the best of open source with enterprise storage functionality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As demands grow, new volumes and storage capacity can be allocated on the fly. Alletra’s scale-out, modular architecture ensures the platform can expand without disrupting running workloads. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;A foundation for modern infrastructure deployments &lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LXD provides a unified open source virtualization platform to run system containers and virtual machines with a focus on efficiency, security, and ease of management. With native support for HPE Alletra, enterprises can now build, deploy, and manage their workloads with enterprise storage guarantees, whether in private clouds, on-premises data centers, or edge environments. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The combined solution empowers teams to deliver predictable performance for critical and data-intensive workloads while reducing complexity and ensuring agility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Availability&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The integration between LXD and HPE Alletra is available starting with the &lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/lxd/latest/reference/release-notes/release-notes-6.6/"&gt;LXD 6.6 feature release&lt;/a&gt;, and requires a HPE Alletra WSAPI version 1. LXD currently supports connecting to HPE Alletra storage through NVMe/TCP or iSCSI protocols. For detailed information, visit &lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/lxd/stable-5.21/reference/storage_alletra/"&gt;Canonical’s LXD documentation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Miona Aleksic (Miona Aleksic)</author><category>HPE</category><category>LXD</category><category>microcloud</category><pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 15:57:28 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Why you should retire your Microsoft Azure Consumption Commitment (MACC) with Ubuntu Pro</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/retire-azure-consumption-commitment-macc-ubuntu-pro</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Fulfilling your Microsoft Azure Consumption Commitment (MACC) requires efficient planning. Discover how allocating your MACC to Ubuntu Pro allows you to meet consumption goals while securing your open source supply chain and automating compliance.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;When your organization first signed its Microsoft Azure Consumption Commitment (MACC), it was a strategic step to unlock better pricing and enable cloud growth. However, fulfilling that commitment efficiently requires planning. Organizations often look for ways to retire their MACC that drive strategic value, rather than simply increasing consumption to meet a deadline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal is to meet your commitment while delivering long-term benefits to the business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Ubuntu Pro in the Azure Marketplace, you can retire your MACC at 100% of the pretax purchase amount. In practice, this allows you to meet consumption goals on your standard Azure invoice, while securing your open source supply chain and automating compliance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Turn a spend target into an open source security strategy&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of simply increasing consumption to hit a target, effective IT and FinOps teams align their MACC with broader strategic goals. Open source support and security maintenance is a priority for enterprises, as a &lt;a href="https://pages.ubuntu.com/rs/066-EOV-335/images/Final%20report%20-%20WorldofOS_EUSpotlight_2025_081525.pdf?version=0&amp;amp;_gl=1*tbk0ic*_gcl_au*MjAyODc1NDE5My4xNzU0OTk1ODU4"&gt;recent Linux Foundation report&lt;/a&gt; shows: 54% of enterprises want long-term guarantees, and 53% expect rapid security patching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu Pro offers both. By choosing software that strengthens your security and operations, you can retire your MACC while funding capabilities your organization prioritizes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Allocating MACC to Ubuntu Pro is a direct investment in your open source estate:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Expanded Security Maintenance (ESM)&lt;/strong&gt;: extend security coverage to the critical open source applications running above the operating system layer. ESM provides up to 15 years of security updates for the OS, plus tens of thousands of packages. You might already see alerts for these missing updates in your Azure portal – learn how to check your exposure in our blog: [&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/blog/ubuntu-lts-vm-azure-security-view"&gt;A complete security view for every Ubuntu LTS VM on Azure&lt;/a&gt;].&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kernel Livepatch&lt;/strong&gt;: reduce maintenance windows by applying critical kernel patches without requiring a reboot for most workloads.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Compliance tooling&lt;/strong&gt;: access options for CIS hardening and FIPS 140-3 validated cryptographic modules to support meeting compliance and regulatory needs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Optional enterprise support&lt;/strong&gt;: add enterprise SLAs, direct access to Canonical engineers for break-fix and bug-fix, and guidance on operating Ubuntu and ESM-covered packages on Azure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By choosing Ubuntu Pro, you convert your MACC spend into a maintained open source foundation across the development lifecycle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Maximize value and streamline procurement&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Retiring your commitment should be financially efficient and administratively simple. While standard Marketplace listings are MACC-eligible, many organizations use p&lt;a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/marketplace/private-offers-overview"&gt;rivate offers&lt;/a&gt; to secure tailored commercial terms, like custom pricing or volume discounts, without sacrificing eligibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;We support both standard private offers and multiparty private offers for rollouts involving resellers in the US/UK. In all cases, checking that your purchase counts toward your commitment is straightforward:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Confirm Eligibility&lt;/strong&gt;: verify the listing or private offer is marked as “Azure benefit-eligible.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Purchase Correctly&lt;/strong&gt;: execute the transaction in the Azure portal under the tenant and subscription tied to your MACC agreement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This approach guarantees that every dollar spent satisfies your financial goals while delivering the specific security coverage your organization needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ready to align Ubuntu Pro with your MACC? &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/azure/contact-us"&gt;Talk to our team&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Jehudi (Jehudi)</author><pubDate>Sat, 13 Dec 2025 00:07:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How to launch a Deep Learning VM on Google Cloud</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/how-to-launch-a-deep-learning-vm-on-google-cloud</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Setting up a local Deep Learning environment can be a headache. Between managing CUDA drivers, resolving Python library conflicts, and ensuring you have enough GPU power, you often spend more time configuring than coding. Google Cloud and Canonical work together to solve this with Deep Learning VM Images, which use Ubuntu Accelerator Optimized OS as [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;Setting up a local Deep Learning environment can be a headache. Between managing CUDA drivers, resolving Python library conflicts, and ensuring you have enough GPU power, you often spend more time configuring than coding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google Cloud and Canonical work together to solve this with &lt;a href="https://console.cloud.google.com/marketplace/details/click-to-deploy-images/deeplearning"&gt;Deep Learning VM Images&lt;/a&gt;, which use Ubuntu Accelerator Optimized OS as the base OS. These are pre-configured virtual machines optimized for data science and machine learning tasks. They come pre-installed with popular frameworks, such as PyTorch, and the necessary NVIDIA drivers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this guide, I’ll walk you through how to launch a Deep Learning VM on GCP using the Console, and how to verify your software stack so you can start training immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Why use a Deep Learning VM?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pre-installed frameworks:&lt;/strong&gt; No need to pip install generic libraries manually.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GPU-ready:&lt;/strong&gt; NVIDIA drivers are pre-installed and verified.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jupyter integration:&lt;/strong&gt; Seamless access to JupyterLab right out of the box.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;How to make a Deep Learning VM in GCP&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Step 1: Navigate to the GCP Marketplace&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, log in to your Google Cloud Console. Instead of creating a generic Compute Engine instance, we want to use a specialized image from the Marketplace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open the&lt;a href="https://console.cloud.google.com"&gt; Google Cloud Console&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the search bar at the top, type &lt;strong&gt;“Deep Learning VM”&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select the product named &lt;strong&gt;Deep Learning VM&lt;/strong&gt; published by Google.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="538" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1448px) 1448px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1448/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F8758%2Fimage.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F8758%2Fimage.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F8758%2Fimage.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F8758%2Fimage.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F8758%2Fimage.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F8758%2Fimage.png 1920w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1448/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F8758%2Fimage.png 1448w" width="1448"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Step 2: Configure your instance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you are on the Marketplace Deep Learning VM listing page, click &lt;strong&gt;Launch&lt;/strong&gt;. This will take you to the deployment configuration screen. This is where you define the power behind your model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the key settings you need to pay attention to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Zone:&lt;/strong&gt; Make sure to select a zone that supports the specific GPU you want to use (in my case, I selected the us-central1-f zone).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Machine Type:&lt;/strong&gt; Choose a CPU/RAM combination that meets your requirements if you don’t need a GPU.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GPU Type:&lt;/strong&gt; You can add your GPU type, such as the NVIDIA T4, A100, or H100. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="585" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1600px) 1600px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1600/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F7a77%2Fimage.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F7a77%2Fimage.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F7a77%2Fimage.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F7a77%2Fimage.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F7a77%2Fimage.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F7a77%2Fimage.png 1920w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1600/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F7a77%2Fimage.png 1600w" width="1600"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Configuring the VM instance in the Google Cloud Console.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you have made your selections, click &lt;strong&gt;Deploy&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Step 3: Connect and verify&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a minute or two, your VM will be deployed. You can find it listed in your &lt;strong&gt;Compute Engine &amp;gt; VM Instances&lt;/strong&gt; page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To access the machine, click the &lt;strong&gt;SSH&lt;/strong&gt; button next to your new instance. This opens a terminal window directly in your browser.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="497" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1600px) 1600px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1600/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2228%2Fimage.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2228%2Fimage.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2228%2Fimage.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2228%2Fimage.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2228%2Fimage.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2228%2Fimage.png 1920w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1600/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2228%2Fimage.png 1600w" width="1600"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Step 4: Check the software stack &amp;amp; drivers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, let’s make sure everything is working under the hood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;1. Verify NVIDIA drivers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have attached a GPU, the most important check is to ensure the drivers have loaded correctly. Run the following command in your SSH terminal:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;nvidia-smi&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should see a table listing your GPU (e.g., A100) and the CUDA version.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="691" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1600px) 1600px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1600/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F5332%2Fimage.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F5332%2Fimage.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F5332%2Fimage.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F5332%2Fimage.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F5332%2Fimage.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F5332%2Fimage.png 1920w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1600/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F5332%2Fimage.png 1600w" width="1600"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;2. Check pre-installed software&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google’s Deep Learning VMs usually come with PyTorch pre-configured. You can check the installed packages to ensure your favorite libraries are there:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;pip show torch&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="391" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1600px) 1600px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1600/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F737c%2Fimage-1.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F737c%2Fimage-1.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F737c%2Fimage-1.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F737c%2Fimage-1.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F737c%2Fimage-1.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F737c%2Fimage-1.png 1920w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1600/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F737c%2Fimage-1.png 1600w" width="1600"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that’s it! In just a few minutes, you have built a fully configured Deep Learning environment. You can now start running training scripts directly from the terminal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don’t forget:&lt;/strong&gt; Deep Learning VMs with GPUs can be expensive. Remember to &lt;strong&gt;stop&lt;/strong&gt; your instance when you aren’t using it to avoid unexpected charges!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/gcp/google-explanation/canonical-offerings/"&gt;Learn  more about Canonical’s offerings on GCP&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Read more&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://ubuntu.com/gcp"&gt;Ubuntu on Google Cloud&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://discourse.ubuntu.com/t/optimizing-ai-workloads-with-ubuntu-ai-images/67099"&gt;Optimizing AI workloads with Ubuntu AI images&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Hugo Huang (Hugo Huang)</author><category>accelerator</category><category>deep learning</category><category>Google Cloud</category><pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 14:31:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Harnessing the potential of 5G with Kubernetes: a cloud-native telco transformation perspective</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/harnessing-the-potential-of-5g-with-kubernetes-a-cloud-native-telco-transformation-perspective</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Telecommunications networks are undergoing a cloud-native revolution. 5G promises ultra-fast connectivity and real-time services, but achieving those benefits requires an infrastructure that is agile, low-latency, and highly reliable. Kubernetes has emerged as a cornerstone for telecom operators to meet 5G demands. In 2025, Canonical Kubernetes delivers a single, production-grade Kubernetes platform with long-term support (LTS) [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;Telecommunications networks are undergoing a cloud-native revolution. 5G promises ultra-fast connectivity and real-time services, but achieving those benefits requires an infrastructure that is agile, low-latency, and highly reliable. Kubernetes has emerged as a cornerstone for telecom operators to meet 5G demands. In 2025, Canonical Kubernetes delivers a single, production-grade Kubernetes platform with long-term support (LTS) and telco-specific optimizations, deployable across clouds, data centers, and the far edge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog explores how Canonical Kubernetes empowers 5G and cloud-native telco workloads with high performance, enhanced platform awareness (EPA), and robust security, while offering flexible deployment via snaps, Juju, or Cluster API. We’ll also highlight its integration into industry initiatives like Sylva, support for GPU/DPU acceleration, and synergy with MicroCloud for scalable edge infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;The rise of the cloud-native telco&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Telecom decision-makers face immense pressure to evolve their networks rapidly and cost-effectively. Traditional, hardware-centric architectures struggle to keep pace with 5G’s requirements for low latency, high throughput, and dynamic scaling. This is where Kubernetes – the de facto platform for cloud-native applications – comes in. Kubernetes brings powerful automation, scalability, and resiliency that allow telcos to manage network functions like software across data centers, public clouds, and far-edge deployments. The result is a more agile operational model: services can be rolled out faster, resources automatically optimized to demand, and updates applied continuously without disrupting critical services. In the 5G era, such agility is essential for delivering innovations like network slicing, multi-access edge computing (MEC), and AI-driven services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, Kubernetes opens the door for telcos to refactor their network functions into microservices. Instead of relying on monolithic appliances or heavy virtual machines, operators can deploy &lt;em&gt;cloud-native network functions (CNFs)&lt;/em&gt; – essentially containerized network services – that are lighter and faster to roll out than traditional virtual network functions (VNFs). By shifting to CNFs, new network features (whether a 5G core component or a firewall) can be introduced or updated in a fraction of the time, using automated CI/CD pipelines instead of lengthy manual upgrades. This approach helps telcos simplify the migration from legacy systems to a more agile, software-driven network model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, adopting Kubernetes for telecom workloads also means meeting rigorous performance and reliability standards. Carrier-grade services like voice, video, and core network functions can’t tolerate unpredictable delays or downtime. Telco leaders need a Kubernetes platform that combines cloud-native flexibility with &lt;em&gt;telco-grade&lt;/em&gt; performance, security, and support. Canonical Kubernetes answers that call, providing a Kubernetes distribution specifically tuned for telecommunications needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Canonical Kubernetes: optimized for cloud-native 5G networks and edge computing&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical’s Kubernetes distribution has been engineered from the ground up to address the unique challenges of 5G and cloud-native telco cloud deployments. It is a single, unified Kubernetes offering that blends the ease of use of lightweight deployments with the robustness of an enterprise-grade platform. Importantly, Canonical Kubernetes can be deployed and managed in whatever way best fits a telco’s environment – whether installed as a secure snap package or integrated with full automation tooling like Juju (model-driven operations) or Kubernetes Cluster API (CAPI). This flexibility means operators can start small at the network edge or scale up to carrier-core clusters, all using the same consistent platform. Notably, Canonical Kubernetes brings cloud-native telco-friendly capabilities in the areas of performance, networking, operations, and support:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;High performance &amp;amp; low latency&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/engage/an-introduction-to-real-time-linux-part-i"&gt;Real-time linux kernel&lt;/a&gt; support ensures that high-priority network workloads execute with predictable, ultra-low latency, a critical requirement for functions like the 5G user plane function (UPF). In parallel, built-in support for advanced networking (including SR-IOV and DPDK) enables fast packet processing by giving containerized network functions direct access to hardware, dramatically reducing network I/O latency for high bandwidth 5G applications. Together, these features allow cloud-native network functions to meet stringent performance and determinism once only achievable on specialized telecom hardware.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;GPU acceleration&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical Kubernetes integrates seamlessly with acceleration technologies to support emerging cloud-native telco workloads. It works with NVIDIA’s GPU and networking operators to leverage hardware accelerators (GPUs, SmartNICs, DPUs) for intensive tasks. It supports NVIDIA’s Multi-Instance GPU (MIG), which expands the performance and value of the NVIDIA’s data center GPUs, such as the latest GB200 and RTX PRO 6000 Blackwell Server Edition by partitioning the GPU into up to seven instances, each fully hardware isolated with its own high-bandwidth memory, cache, and streaming multiprocessors. The partitioned instances are transparent to workloads which greatly optimizes the use of resources and allows for serving workloads with guaranteed QoS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means telecom operators can run AI/ML analytics, media processing, or virtual RAN computations that take advantage of GPUs and DPU offloading within their Kubernetes clusters – all managed under the same platform. By tapping into hardware acceleration, telcos can deliver advanced services (like AI-driven network optimization or AR/VR streaming) with high performance, without needing separate siloed infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Operational efficiency and automation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Day-0 to Day-2 operations are streamlined through automation in Canonical’s stack. The distribution supports full lifecycle management – clusters can be deployed, scaled, and updated via one-step commands or integrated CI/CD pipelines, reducing manual effort and errors. Using Juju charms, Canonical’s model-driven operations further simplify complex orchestration, enabling teams to configure and update Kubernetes and related services in a repeatable, declarative way. Built-in self-healing and high availability features ensure that the platform can recover from failures automatically, keeping services running without intervention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This high degree of automation translates into faster rollout of new network functions and updates (with minimal downtime), allowing telco teams to focus on innovation rather than routine ops tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Edge flexibility&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical Kubernetes is designed to run from the core to the far edge with equal ease. Its lightweight, efficient design (delivered as a single snap package) results in a low resource footprint, making it viable even on a one- or two-node edge cluster in a remote site. At the same time, it scales up to multi-node deployments for central networks. The platform supports a variety of configurations – from a single node for an ultra-compact edge appliance, to a dual-node high-availability cluster, to large multi-node clusters for data centers – all with the same tooling and consistent experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This flexibility allows operators to extend cloud capabilities to edge locations (for ultra-low latency processing) while managing everything in a unified way. In practice, Canonical’s solution can power cloud-native telco IT workloads, 5G core functions, and edge applications under one umbrella, meeting the specific performance and latency needs of each environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Long-Term support and stability&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical backs its Kubernetes with long-term support options far exceeding the typical open-source release cycle. &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/blog/12-year-lts-for-kubernetes"&gt;Each Canonical Kubernetes LTS version can receive security patches and maintenance for up to 15 years&lt;/a&gt;, ensuring a stable foundation for cloud-native telco services over the entire 5G rollout and beyond. (For comparison, upstream Kubernetes offers roughly 1 year of support per release).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This extended support window means carriers can avoid frequent, disruptive upgrades and rest assured that their infrastructure remains compliant over the long term. Such a commitment to stability is a key reason telecom operators choose Canonical – long-term maintenance provides confidence that critical network workloads will run on a hardened, well-maintained platform for many years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Cost efficiency and vendor neutrality&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an open-source, upstream-aligned distribution, Canonical Kubernetes has no licensing costs and prevents vendor lock-in. Telcos are free to deploy it on their preferred hardware or cloud, and they benefit from a large ecosystem of Kubernetes-compatible tools and operators. The platform’s efficient resource usage and automation also help drive down operating costs – by improving hardware utilization and simplifying management, it enables operators to serve growing traffic loads without linear cost increases. In short, Canonical’s Kubernetes offers carrier-grade performance and features at a fraction of the cost of proprietary alternatives, all while keeping the operator in control of their technology roadmap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Enabling a new wave of cloud-native telco services&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using Canonical Kubernetes, cloud-native telcos can position themselves to innovate faster and operate more efficiently in the 5G era. They can readily stand up cloud-native 5G Core functions, scale out Open RAN deployments, and push applications to the network edge – all on a consistent Kubernetes foundation. In fact, Kubernetes makes it feasible for telcos to transition from traditional VNFs on virtual machines to containerized CNFs, reducing resource overhead and speeding up deployment of network features. This means legacy network applications can be modernized step-by-step and run alongside new microservices on the same platform, avoiding risky “big bang” overhauls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result is not only technical efficiency but business agility: operators can launch new services (from enhanced mobile broadband to IoT analytics) in weeks instead of months, respond quickly to customer demand spikes, and streamline the integration of new network functions or vendors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early adopters in the industry are already seeing the benefits. For example, &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/blog/bringing-canonical-kubernetes-to-sylva-a-new-chapter-for-european-telco-clouds"&gt;Canonical’s Kubernetes has been embraced in initiatives like the European Sylva open telco cloud project&lt;/a&gt;, in part due to its security, flexibility and long-term support advantages. This momentum underscores that a performant, open Kubernetes platform is becoming a strategic asset for telcos aiming to stay ahead in a competitive landscape. Perhaps most importantly, Canonical Kubernetes lets telcos focus on delivering value to subscribers – ultra-reliable connectivity, rich digital services, tailored enterprise solutions – rather than getting bogged down in infrastructure complexity. It abstracts away much of the heavy lifting of deploying and upgrading distributed systems, while providing the controls needed to meet strict cloud-native telco requirements. The combination of automation, performance tuning, and openness creates a powerful engine for telecom innovation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Cloud-native at any scale: Canonical Kubernetes meets MicroCloud&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the edge, complexity is the enemy. That’s why Canonical Kubernetes pairs naturally with MicroCloud, our lightweight production-grade cloud infrastructure for distributed environments. MicroCloud fits the edge use case extremely well: it is easy to deploy, fully automated, and optimized for bare-metal and low-power sites. Drop it into a telco cabinet, regional hub, or remote data center, and you get a resilient control plane for running Kubernetes, virtualization, and storage with zero overhead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In such deployments, MicroCloud and Canonical Kubernetes form a tightly integrated stack that brings cloud-native operations to the far edge. Need to orchestrate CNFs next to VMs? Spin up a single-node cluster with high availability? Scale to dozens of locations without rearchitecting? This combo makes it possible, with snaps for simple updates, Juju for full automation, and long-term support built in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Conclusion: building the future of cloud-native telco on open source Kubernetes&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5G and edge computing are reshaping telecom networks, and Kubernetes has proven to be an essential technology powering this evolution.&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/industrial"&gt; Industrial IoT&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/automotive"&gt; automotive applications&lt;/a&gt; ,&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/internet-of-things/smart-city"&gt; smart cities&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/robotics"&gt; robotics&lt;/a&gt;, remote health care, and the gaming industry rely on high data transfer, close to real time latency, very high availability and reliability. Canonical Kubernetes brings the best of cloud-native innovation to the telecom domain in a form that aligns with carriers’ operational realities and performance needs. It delivers a rare mix of benefits – agility and efficiency from automation, high performance for demanding workloads, freedom from lock-in, and assured long-term support – making it a compelling choice for any telco modernizing its infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Telecommunications leaders looking to become cloud-native telcos should consider how an open-source platform like Canonical Kubernetes can serve as a foundation for growth. Whether the goal is to reduce operating costs in the core network, roll out programmable 5G services at the edge, or simply break free from proprietary constraints, Canonical’s Kubernetes distribution provides a proven path forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Explore further&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To dive deeper into how Canonical Kubernetes meets telco performance and reliability requirements, we invite you to read our detailed white paper: &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/engage/kubernetes-for-telco-performance"&gt;Addressing telco performance requirements with Canonical Kubernetes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; It offers in-depth insights and benchmark results from real-world cloud-native telco scenarios. Additionally, visit our blogs on Ubuntu.com and Canonical.com for more success stories and technical guides – from 5G network modernization strategies to edge:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/blog/edge-networking-gets-smarter-ai-and-5g-in-action"&gt;Edge Networking gets smarter: AI and 5G in action&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/blog/canonical-releases-fips-enabled-kubernetes"&gt;Canonical releases FIPS-enabled Kubernetes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/blog/canonical-kubernetes-officially-included-in-sylva-1-5"&gt;Canonical Kubernetes officially included in Sylva 1.5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Visiting MWC 2026?&lt;a href="https://canonical.com/solutions/telco#get-in-touch"&gt; Book a meeting with Canonical&lt;/a&gt; to find out more.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Benjamin Ryzman (Benjamin Ryzman)</author><category>Cloud Native</category><category>kubernetes</category><category>Telco 5G</category><pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 15:47:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The rhythm of reliability: inside Canonical’s operational cadence</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/the-rhythm-of-reliability</link><description>&lt;p&gt;At Canonical, time is fixed. Ubuntu releases never slip because we run on a strict rhythm: six-month cycles, two-week pulses, and in-person sprints. Every change is deliberate, ensuring stability without losing agility. This discipline is what enables us to provide 15 years of Long-Term Support. Reliability is built into everything we do.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;In software engineering, we often talk about the “iron triangle” of constraints: time, resources, and features. You can rarely fix all three. At many companies, when scope creeps or resources get tight, the timeline is often the first element of the triangle to slip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At Canonical, we take a different approach. For us, &lt;strong&gt;time&lt;/strong&gt; is the fixed constraint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn’t just about strict project management. It is a mechanism of trust. Our users, customers, and the open source community need to know exactly when the next Ubuntu release is coming. To deliver that reliability externally, we need a rigorous operational rhythm internally, and for over 20 years, we have honored this commitment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is how we orchestrate the business of building software, from our six-month cycles to the daily pulse of engineering:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="554" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1184px) 1184px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1184/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F54bc%2Fimage.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F54bc%2Fimage.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F54bc%2Fimage.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F54bc%2Fimage.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F54bc%2Fimage.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F54bc%2Fimage.png 1920w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1184/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F54bc%2Fimage.png 1184w" width="1184"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p class="has-text-align-center"&gt;Fig. 1 Canonical’s Operating Cycle&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The six-month cycle&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our entire engineering organization operates on a six-month cycle that aligns with the Ubuntu release cadence. This cycle is our heartbeat. It drives accountability and ensures we ship features on time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make this work, we rely on three critical control points:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sprint Readiness Review (SRR): This is where prioritization happens. Before a cycle begins, we don’t just ask “what fits?”: we ask “what matters?” We go through feedback to find the most valuable engineering opportunities, ensuring we prioritize quality and impact over volume. We don’t start the work until we know the scope is worth the effort.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Product Roadmap Sprint: The SRR culminates in this one-week, face-to-face event. This is the formal moment of truth where we close out the previous cycle and leadership signs off on the plan for the next one. It ensures that every team leaves the room with a clear, approved mandate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Midcycle Review: Three months in, we hold a “Virtual Sprint” to check our progress. Crucially, we review any “bad news”, in which we immediately identify items that will not ship or are at risk. By addressing what won’t happen upfront, leadership can make informed decisions to course-correct immediately rather than letting a deadline slip.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This discipline ensures we stay agile, and that we can adjust our trajectory halfway through without derailing the entire delivery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The two-week pulse&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the six-month cycle sets the destination, the “pulse” gets us there. A pulse is our version of a two-week agile sprint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crucially, these pulses are synchronized across the entire company, on a cross-functional basis. Marketing, Sales, and Support all operate on this same frequency. When a team member says, “we will do it next pulse,” everyone, regardless of department, knows exactly what that means. This creates a shared expectation of delivery that keeps the whole organization moving in lockstep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sprints are for in-person connection&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We distinguish between a “pulse” (our virtual, two-week work iteration) and a “sprint.” For us, a sprint is a physical, one-week event where teams meet face-to-face.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are a remote-first company, which makes these moments invaluable. Sprints provide the high-bandwidth communication and human connection needed to sustain us through months of remote execution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also stagger these sprints to separate context. Our &lt;strong&gt;Engineering Sprints&lt;/strong&gt; happen in May and November (immediately after an Ubuntu release) so teams can focus purely on technical roadmapping. &lt;strong&gt;Commercial Sprints&lt;/strong&gt; happen in January and July, aligning with our fiscal half-years to focus on business value. This “dual-clock” system ensures that commercial goals and technical realities are synchronized without overwhelming the teams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Managing the exceptions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, market reality doesn’t always adhere to a six-month schedule. Customers have urgent needs, and high-value opportunities appear unexpectedly. To handle this without breaking our rhythm, we use the &lt;strong&gt;Commercial Review (CR)&lt;/strong&gt; process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The CR process protects our engineering teams from chaos while giving us the agility to say “yes” to the right opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Protection:&lt;/strong&gt; We don’t let unverified requests disrupt the roadmap. A Review Board assesses every non-standard request before we make a promise.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conscious trade-offs:&lt;/strong&gt; If a new request is critical, we ask: “What are we removing to make space for this?” It forces a conscious decision. We review the roadmap and agree on what gets deprioritized to satisfy the new request.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This ensures that when we do deviate from the plan, it is a strategic choice, not an accident.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quality as a natural habit&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Underpinning this entire rhythm is a commitment to quality standards. We follow the Plan, Do, Check, Act (PDCA) cycle, a concept rooted in ISO 9001. While we align with these formal frameworks, it has become a natural habit for us at Canonical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This operational discipline is what enables up to &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/blog/canonical-expands-total-coverage-for-ubuntu-lts-releases-to-15-years-with-legacy-add-on"&gt;15 years of LTS commitment&lt;/a&gt; on a vast portfolio of open source components, providing Long-Term Support for the entire, integrated collection of application software, libraries, and toolchains. Offering 15 years of security maintenance on our entire stack is only possible because we are operationally consistent. Long-term stability is the direct result of short-term discipline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By sticking to this rhythm, we ensure that Canonical remains not just a source of great technology, but a reliable partner for the long haul.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Maksim Beliaev (Maksim Beliaev)</author><category>Business</category><category>Canonical</category><category>lifecycle</category><category>operations</category><pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 12:22:33 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Canonical to distribute AMD ROCm AI/ML and HPC libraries in Ubuntu</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/canonical-amd-rocm-ai-ml-hpc-libraries</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Canonical is pleased to announce an expanded collaboration with AMD to package and maintain AMD ROCm™ software directly in Ubuntu. AMD ROCm is an open software ecosystem to enable hardware-accelerated AI/ML and HPC workloads on AMD Instinct™ and AMD Radeon™ GPUs, simplifying the deployment of AI infrastructure with long term support from Canonical. Canonical has [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;Canonical is pleased to announce an expanded collaboration with AMD to package and maintain AMD ROCm™ software directly in Ubuntu. AMD ROCm is an open software ecosystem to enable hardware-accelerated AI/ML and HPC workloads on AMD Instinct™ and AMD Radeon™ GPUs, simplifying the deployment of AI infrastructure with long term support from Canonical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical has formed a dedicated team of engineers to package the AMD ROCm software libraries to streamline installation, support, and long-term maintenance on Ubuntu. Canonical will also submit these packages for consideration in Debian.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This work will simplify the delivery of AMD AI solutions in data centers, workstations, laptops, Windows Subsystem for Linux, and edge environments. AMD ROCm software will be available as a dependency for any Debian package, snap, or Docker image (OCI) build.  Performance fixes and security patches will automatically be available to production systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This collaboration aims to make AMD ROCm software available in Ubuntu starting with Ubuntu 26.04 LTS, with updates available in every subsequent Ubuntu release.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;AMD ROCm software: a commitment to open source &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical works with silicon industry leaders to incorporate the software libraries and drivers that accelerate applications on their silicon directly into Ubuntu. Comprehensive support for the latest silicon dramatically accelerates developer adoption and production deployments. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For AMD, the software that enables hardware-accelerated AI processing is called ROCm. It is an open software platform that includes runtimes, compilers, libraries, kernel components, and drivers that together accelerate industry standard frameworks such as PyTorch, Tensorflow, Jax, and more on supported AMD GPUs and APUs. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“AMD ROCm software enables open, high-performance acceleration for AI and HPC on AMD hardware. Working with Canonical to package AMD ROCm for Ubuntu makes it easier for developers and enterprises to deploy AMD solutions on supported systems,” said Andrej Zdravkovic, Senior Vice President, GPU Technologies and Engineering Software and Chief Software Officer at AMD.     &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Packaging AMD ROCm in Ubuntu underscores the strong AMD commitment to developer experience and enterprise experience:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Simpler installation with ‘apt install rocm’ or as an automatic dependency for other projects, like ollama-amd.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Both stable LTS and fresh ROCm versions every six months will be available, to ensure immediate support for the latest hardware and software.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easy security fixes and performance improvements (just “apt upgrade”).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Up to 15 years of support for AMD ROCm in Ubuntu LTS versions under Ubuntu Pro. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Personal Ubuntu Pro subscriptions are free.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are delighted to work alongside AMD and the community to package AMD ROCm libraries directly into Ubuntu,” said Cindy Goldberg, SVP of Silicon and Cloud Alliances at Canonical. “This will simplify the use of AMD hardware and software for AI workloads, and enable organizations to meet security and maintenance requirements for production use at scale.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Improved hardware support&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical works closely with hardware manufactures to test, optimize, and certify Ubuntu for their devices, and to integrate the required software drivers and kernel patches to support that hardware. Thanks to this extensive hardware program, Ubuntu runs equally well on laptops, workstations, servers, and IoT/edge devices, and developers have a seamless path from development through to deployment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn more about &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/partners/silicon"&gt;Canonical’s silicon partnerships&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amd.com/en/products/software/rocm.html"&gt;Read about AMD ROCm software&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Canonical (Canonical)</author><category>AI/ML</category><category>Certified hardware</category><category>Ubuntu Pro</category><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 17:38:05 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How telco companies can reduce 5G infrastructure costs with modern open source cloud-native technologies</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/how-telco-companies-can-reduce-5g-infrastructure-costs-with-modern-open-source-cloud-native-technologies</link><description>&lt;p&gt;5G continues to transform the telecommunications landscape, enabling massive device density, edge computing, and new enterprise use cases. However, operators still face significant cost pressures: from accelerating RAN modernization and 5G SA rollouts to energy demands and the shift to cloud-native network functions (CNFs). As telcos redesign their infrastructure strategies, open source has become a [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;5G continues to transform the telecommunications landscape, enabling massive device density, edge computing, and new enterprise use cases. However, operators still face significant cost pressures: from accelerating RAN modernization and 5G SA rollouts to energy demands and the shift to cloud-native network functions (CNFs). As telcos redesign their infrastructure strategies, open source has become a key lever to reduce costs, increase flexibility, and accelerate innovation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog outlines today’s primary 5G infrastructure challenges and highlights how modern open source cloud technologies from Canonical help operators address them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;The telco dilemma: 5G infrastructure challenges&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the advancements of 5G and more complex deployments, telcos face several challenges in building and maintaining 5G infrastructure, including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;High investment costs:&lt;/strong&gt; 5G infrastructure requires significant investment in new hardware and software, especially for hosting the virtualization infrastructure necessary to run 5G software&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rising OPEX and energy costs:&lt;/strong&gt; Power consumption of distributed 5G sites is now one of the largest operational expenses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cloud-native complexity:&lt;/strong&gt; Moving from virtualized network functions (VNFs) to cloud-native network functions (CNFs) increases the need for Kubernetes-scale automation and observability.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disaggregated RAN and multi-vendor integrations:&lt;/strong&gt; Open RAN and virtualised RAN require consistent infrastructure, automation and lifecycle management.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Limited spectrum:&lt;/strong&gt; The available spectrum for 5G is limited and highly regulated, which can make it difficult for telcos to acquire and use.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Edge footprint explosion:&lt;/strong&gt; 5G MEC deployments increase the number of sites operators must manage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Talent and skills gaps:&lt;/strong&gt; Cloud-native and Kubernetes skills remain scarce in telecom operations teams.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Security:&lt;/strong&gt; 5G networks are vulnerable to cyber attacks, which can compromise the security and privacy of users’ data. The attack surface is larger with 5G compared to previous generations of mobile networks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vendor Lock-in:&lt;/strong&gt; a telecom operator is heavily dependent on one or a few vendors for all of its 5G network infrastructure and services, making it difficult for the operator to switch to another vendor without incurring significant costs and disruption to its network.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;How open source is changing the game&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open source plays a central role in enabling telcos to modernise their networks: from VNF virtualization to full cloud-native CNF deployments. By standardizing on open platforms like Ubuntu, Kubernetes and OpenStack, operators reduce infrastructure licensing costs, improve interoperability, and accelerate innovation. Today, most large operators run the majority of their 5G core workloads on open source infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Shared standards&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open source communities, including CNCF, O-RAN Alliance and Project Sylva, provide common frameworks that reduce integration effort. By adopting open standards, operators can more easily mix vendors and ensure long-term ecosystem interoperability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Avoid vendor lock-in&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In line with the development of shared standards, open source solutions can help avoid vendor lock-in by providing access to code that can be modified and adapted to meet specific needs. This means that telcos and ISVs can avoid being tied to a particular vendor or technology stack and choose the best solutions for their specific requirements instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Meet specific-telco requirements&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Telcos have demanding requirements when it comes to performance, reliability, and security. Long-term support (LTS) is important in the telco industry, as telcos often have long cycles of release deployment. Open source solutions that are supported over the long term, with no API breaks or major changes that could disrupt telco operations (i.e. 12-month release at least, and a few years on average) are the foremost choice for telcos. This is usually a vendor-driven decision, but choosing the right open source with the right vendor is the key here. The reason is, it is difficult to have a telco-grade system after dealing with all the interoperability and fixing into the puzzle challenges, so it is reasonable for an operator to expect the support cycle to be as long as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Performance, flexibility, and automation are key requirements in the telco industry, as they enable telcos to operate more efficiently and effectively. By leveraging the expertise of the wider community, telcos, and ISVs can build solutions that are optimised for telco environments and that can be easily customised to meet specific requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Cost optimization&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open source software offers cost savings compared to proprietary solutions, which can be especially beneficial for organizations with limited budgets. With open source software, organizations do not need to pay for licenses, and there are no vendor lock-ins. They can leverage the vast community of developers and users to troubleshoot issues and implement new features. In addition to removing licensing fees, open source automation frameworks significantly reduce operational costs by simplifying CNF lifecycle management, improving energy optimization, and enabling consistent operations across core, edge and RAN deployments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Security&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The telecom sector handles a vast amount of sensitive information, including personal and financial data, making it a prime target for cyber-attacks. There are several data privacy and security concerns that the telecom sector faces, including data breaches, malware attacks, insider threats, lack of compliance, etc. In this regard, open source software vulnerabilities are often patched more quickly than with proprietary software. In addition, open source software is transparent and customisable, making it easier to meet the operator’s unique needs and implement security features that align with their security requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the sections that follow we provide example applications for open source solutions across the telco stack, with a focus on tooling supported by Canonical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Open source solutions for telcos&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical’s telco portfolio spans the entire network – from RAN compute nodes to edge clouds, MEC platforms, private clouds and public-cloud deployments. Ubuntu and our cloud-native infrastructure stack (MAAS, MicroCloud, OpenStack, Kubernetes and Juju) provide a consistent operational model across all layers of the 5G architecture.. This enables telcos to meet any current or future use cases – from OpenRAN to next-generation Core (5G and beyond) and AI at the edge. &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/pro"&gt;Ubuntu Pro&lt;/a&gt; is Canonical’s comprehensive subscription for enterprise security, compliance and support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="has-text-align-center has-small-font-size"&gt;&lt;img decoding="async" height="404" loading="lazy" src="blob:https://admin.insights.ubuntu.com/7992c784-e5d4-4e93-9690-7104aa776539" width="588"/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Open source solutions for telcos&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Open source for RAN&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;vRAN and Open RAN deployments require high performance, low latency and hardware acceleration. Canonical works closely with &lt;a href="https://builders.intel.com/docs/networkbuilders/network-and-cloud-edge-reference-system-architecture-with-flexran-software-setup-on-a-single-server-quick-start-guide-1658491779.pdf"&gt;Intel FlexRAN&lt;/a&gt;, NVIDIA Aerial and ARM ecosystem partners to optimize Ubuntu for RAN workloads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another major Canonical contribution for RANs edge use cases is&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/engage/guide-to-micro-clouds"&gt; MicroCloud,&lt;/a&gt; which reproduces the APIs and primitives of the big clouds at the scale of the edge. MicroClouds are typically targeted to easily deploy and lifecycle manage distributed micro clouds – bare metal compute clusters of between 3-100 nodes. A Canonical MicroCloud stack consists of certain building blocks. The details for each component are covered in our Telco 5G infrastructure&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/engage/telco-dilemma-reduce-5g-infra-cost"&gt; whitepaper.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Open source for core networks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most operators deploy their 5G Core on private clouds to maintain strict performance and security control. Canonical’s reference architecture – &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/maas"&gt;MAAS&lt;/a&gt; for bare metal, &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/openstack"&gt;OpenStack&lt;/a&gt; for virtualised infrastructure, &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/kubernetes"&gt;Kubernetes&lt;/a&gt; for CNFs, and &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/juju"&gt;Juju&lt;/a&gt; for automation – provides a proven, carrier-grade cloud foundation adopted by major network equipment providers (NEPs) and operators globally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="has-text-align-center has-small-font-size"&gt;&lt;img decoding="async" height="416" loading="lazy" src="blob:https://admin.insights.ubuntu.com/6db34da1-e968-4e98-9b89-9477bd901677" width="624"/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Canonical stack for private clouds&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Open source for public and hybrid clouds&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu is known for its reliability, security, and versatility, making it a popular choice for telecom companies that require a stable and secure operating system to run Telco applications in the public cloud. A hybrid cloud architecture combines the usage of a private cloud and one or more public cloud services with a workload orchestration engine between the platforms. Using Juju, operators can orchestrate and lifecycle-manage the same CNF or VNF stack across private OpenStack, MicroCloud edge clusters, and hyperscalers. Juju automation provides a consistent approach that natively supports all major hyper scalers APIs and is a de-facto standard tool for MicroClouds in edge use cases. Additionally, Ubuntu Pro for Public Clouds provides telcos with capabilities based on their unique requirements. Details of these requirements and features from Ubuntu are given in this blog series:&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/blog/public-clouds-for-telco-amazon-web-services"&gt; Amazon Web services (AWS)&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/blog/public-cloud-for-telco-part-2-google-cloud-platform"&gt; Google Cloud Platform (GCP)&lt;/a&gt;, and&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/blog/public-cloud-for-telco-part-3-microsoft-azure"&gt; Microsoft Azure.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Wrapping up&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5G infrastructure modernization continues to introduce new operational and cost challenges. Open source cloud technologies, combined with Canonical’s automation and long-term support, help operators simplify their architectures, reduce OPEX, and accelerate the shift to cloud-native 5G.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To explore the latest best practices, &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/solutions/telco#get-in-touch"&gt;speak with our telco specialists&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Benjamin Ryzman (Benjamin Ryzman)</author><category>5g</category><category>Infrastructure</category><category>Telco</category><pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 12:38:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>From cloud to dashboard: experience the future of infotainment development at CES 2026</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/future-of-infotainment-canonical-at-ces-2026</link><description>&lt;p&gt;This year, we’re excited to show a demo that combines the strengths of both Anbox Cloud and Rightware’s Kanzi, the industry-leading software for creating rich, visually stunning infotainment interfaces.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;Every year at CES, we try to go beyond showing technology; we want to give you an experience. This time, it’s the story of how in-vehicle infotainment development is transforming, and how developers can now build, test, and deploy immersive experiences faster than ever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, we’re excited to show a demo that combines the strengths of both Anbox Cloud and Rightware’s Kanzi, the industry-leading software for creating rich, visually stunning infotainment interfaces. It demonstrates cloud-native development, automation, and how virtualization can open up completely new ways to design and test next-generation in-vehicle experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="720" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1280px) 1280px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1280/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fa0b2%2Fimage.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fa0b2%2Fimage.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fa0b2%2Fimage.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fa0b2%2Fimage.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fa0b2%2Fimage.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fa0b2%2Fimage.png 1920w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1280/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fa0b2%2Fimage.png 1280w" width="1280"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Bridging design, development, and validation&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Automotive software development has become incredibly complex. Teams are often focused on their own discipline, UI designers on immersive experiences, Android developers on building integrations, and validation engineers on reliability across hardware variants. These teams can’t always collaborate seamlessly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Testing an infotainment system means being able to access specific hardware or prototypes, which makes iteration slow and collaboration difficult. Small design updates can take days to validate, and testing across different screen configurations or performance conditions is often limited by the availability of physical setups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We wanted to change that by bringing agility and scalability to infotainment development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Infotainment comes to life in the cloud&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our demo, we’ll show how Anbox Cloud turns this traditionally hardware-bound process into a fully virtualized, cloud-native experience. By running Android in the cloud, developers can instantly deploy and test infotainment environments built using Kanzi, on demand, at any scale, from anywhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="900" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1600px) 1600px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1600/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Ff2cd%2Fimage-1.jpeg" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Ff2cd%2Fimage-1.jpeg 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Ff2cd%2Fimage-1.jpeg 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Ff2cd%2Fimage-1.jpeg 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Ff2cd%2Fimage-1.jpeg 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Ff2cd%2Fimage-1.jpeg 1920w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1600/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Ff2cd%2Fimage-1.jpeg 1600w" width="1600"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p class="has-text-align-center"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Widescreen 8K infotainment CES demo&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our setup fits perfectly with Rightware’s widescreen 8K infotainment and cluster bench, powered by Kanzi. Developers can stream the exact same 8K rendering using Anbox Cloud. The result is an impressive, interactive experience, generated and streamed entirely from the cloud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="302" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1600px) 1600px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1600/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F9fea%2Fimage-1.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F9fea%2Fimage-1.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F9fea%2Fimage-1.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F9fea%2Fimage-1.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F9fea%2Fimage-1.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F9fea%2Fimage-1.png 1920w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1600/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F9fea%2Fimage-1.png 1600w" width="1600"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p class="has-text-align-center"&gt;&lt;em&gt;8K virtual Android device running on Anbox Cloud&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Anbox Cloud, Android can be virtualized to any resolution, with pixel-perfect rendering and responsiveness. It can scale to dozens of Android instances running simultaneously, so teams can run automated testing, validate UI performance, and work on the system updates in parallel. Your development becomes faster, collaborative, and independent of physical limitations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Why choose cloud-native Android development?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When moving your development testing to the cloud, designers and developers can collaborate in real time and can see their changes without waiting for hardware to be available. Validation teams can run automated tests on multiple Android instances, across different configurations. For OEMs and Tier 1 suppliers, this means shorter development cycles, meaning more efficient resource use, and faster results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Kanzi has always been about empowering designers and developers to bring exceptional in-vehicle experiences to life,” says Tero Koivu, Co-CEO at Rightware. “Seeing a Kanzi made UI streamed at 8K through Anbox Cloud shows how cloud-native workflows can dramatically accelerate iteration and collaboration. It opens a powerful new path for teams building the next generation of connected, visually stunning automotive user interfaces.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;See it at CES 2026&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Join us at LVCC, North Hall, Booth #10562, and check out the workflow for yourself. You’ll see how Kanzi and Anbox Cloud come together to deliver high-fidelity, scalable, cloud-native infotainment experiences, and how this is redefining the way developers can use Android in the cloud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://calendar.app.google/ao4AHxoZWGkx4wsBA"&gt;Book a meeting with our team&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Come see the future of automotive software development, from cloud to dashboard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, learn more about &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/anbox-cloud"&gt;Anbox Cloud&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://rightware.com"&gt;Rightware&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Further reading&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/anbox-cloud/#"&gt;Official documentation&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/anbox-cloud/howto/install-appliance/install-on-github/"&gt;Anbox Cloud Appliance&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://canonical.com/anbox-cloud"&gt;Learn more about Anbox Cloud &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Android is a trademark of Google LLC. Anbox Cloud uses assets available through the Android Open Source Project.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Bertrand Boisseau (Bertrand Boisseau)</author><category>Anbox</category><category>anbox cloud</category><category>Anbox Cloud Appliance</category><category>Automotive</category><category>CES</category><category>Event</category><pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Canonical announces Ubuntu Pro for WSL </title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/canonical-announces-ubuntu-pro-for-wsl</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu Pro for WSL provides turnkey security maintenance and enterprise support for Ubuntu 24.04 LTS WSL instances in Windows. The subscription will also enable comprehensive management for system administrators.&amp;nbsp; Today, Canonical announced the general availability of Ubuntu Pro for WSL&amp;nbsp;which can be installed from the Microsoft Store. Source and beta releases are also on GitHub. [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;h4 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Ubuntu Pro for WSL provides turnkey security maintenance and enterprise support for Ubuntu 24.04 LTS WSL instances in Windows. The subscription will also enable comprehensive management for system administrators. &lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, Canonical announced the general availability of Ubuntu Pro for WSL which can be installed from the Microsoft Store. Source and beta releases are also on &lt;a href="https://github.com/canonical/ubuntu-pro-for-wsl/releases"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="p-pull-quote--small"&gt;
&lt;p class="p-pull-quote__quote"&gt;Canonical and Microsoft have a fantastic partnership, building out the WSL experience. This work will benefit enterprise developers who use WSL to build production Linux solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;span class="p-pull-quote__citation"&gt;Craig Loewen, Product Manager for WSL at Microsoft&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu Pro delivers enterprise-grade security maintenance and support across desktops, servers, and IoT devices. Now, that same proven value proposition comes to WSL, addressing the security and compliance needs of IT managers and paving the way for broader enterprise adoption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="540" loading="lazy" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/VKdAcrdjQKI?si=lzmcSzSo8xohAa3R" title="YouTube video player" width="960"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Power to developers, peace of mind for IT teams&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WSL provides developers, system administrators, and power users with a native Linux experience on Windows, without the overhead of a full virtual machine or dual boot. It allows users to run Linux command-line tools, utilities, and graphical Linux applications directly on Windows. In collaboration with NVIDIA, WSL 2 delivers near-native GPU-accelerated-performance, allowing applications in Ubuntu to access GPU drivers directly on the Windows host. With Ubuntu Pro, this developer-focused tool is transformed into a fully supported, enterprise-ready solution with up to 15 years of security maintenance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For many enterprises, strict security and compliance policies have been a barrier to adopting WSL given the risks of unmonitored and unsupported open source software. Ubuntu Pro for WSL ensures Expanded Security Maintenance (ESM) is enabled, providing CVE security updates that can be applied subject to administrative policy. Canonical provides up to 15 years of CVE security patching for software packaged and published through Ubuntu’s repositories. Ubuntu Pro subscriptions also cover security maintenance for popular toolchains on WSL, such as Python, Go, Rust, and more. This turnkey solution ensures security vulnerabilities are patched quickly and reliably, making WSL a viable, compliant option for enterprise environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu Pro for WSL will also enable system administrators to manage instances using &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/landscape"&gt;Landscape&lt;/a&gt;, Canonical’s system management tool for Ubuntu. The WSL management feature of Landscape is in beta today, and customers interested in sharing feedback about the feature, and shaping its future, can do so in a self-hosted Landscape server, or by &lt;a href="https://landscape.canonical.com/signup"&gt;signing up for Landscape SaaS&lt;/a&gt;. Landscape will monitor all WSL instances that are deployed once Ubuntu Pro for WSL is configured, and identify which Windows hosts are compliant and which are non-compliant with your WSL provisioning and configuration policies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Seamless installation with Microsoft ecosystem tools&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personal users benefit from a point-and-click installation of Ubuntu Pro for WSL from within the Microsoft Store. As a standard MSIX package, Ubuntu Pro for WSL integrates seamlessly into existing enterprise management workflows, allowing for easy installation and configuration using Microsoft’s enterprise tools. Ubuntu Pro for WSL can be installed and configured using cloud-based tools such as Microsoft Intune, or via Group Policies defined in Microsoft Active Directory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped wp-block-gallery-1 is-layout-flex wp-block-gallery-is-layout-flex"&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-large"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="1080" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1920px) 1920px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F0b7f%2FUbuntu-Pro-on-Windows-1080p.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F0b7f%2FUbuntu-Pro-on-Windows-1080p.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F0b7f%2FUbuntu-Pro-on-Windows-1080p.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F0b7f%2FUbuntu-Pro-on-Windows-1080p.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F0b7f%2FUbuntu-Pro-on-Windows-1080p.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F0b7f%2FUbuntu-Pro-on-Windows-1080p.png 1920w" width="1920"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to being available in the Microsoft Store, images of Ubuntu on WSL are available for download and distribution behind a firewall, giving enterprises the option to host images internally, with centralized control over which WSL images are available to employees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Comprehensive enterprise support&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond security and ease of deployment, Ubuntu Pro for WSL introduces a new support model for developers using WSL. Canonical provides an Ubuntu Pro subscription tier which includes comprehensive phone and ticket support (Ubuntu Pro + Support). This provides a clear and streamlined way for Windows-native developers to get expert help with their Linux environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu Pro for WSL brings Canonical’s security and support capabilities into the Windows ecosystem. Free subscriptions for personal users and paid subscriptions are available through Canonical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Next steps&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/engage/ubuntu-on-wsl-enterprise?utm_source=blog&amp;amp;utm_medium=takeover&amp;amp;utm_campaign=701N100000b75KIIAY"&gt;Watch the webinar: Ubuntu on WSL in the enterprise&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class="p-cta-block"&gt;
&lt;a class="p-button--positive" href="https://github.com/canonical/ubuntu-pro-for-wsl/releases/latest/download/UbuntuProForWSL.msixbundle"&gt;Download Ubuntu Pro for WSL&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/wsl/latest/tutorials/getting-started-with-up4w/"&gt;Read the Ubuntu Pro for WSL tutorial ›&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;About Canonical&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical, the publisher of Ubuntu, provides open source security, support and services. Our portfolio covers critical systems, from the smallest devices to the largest clouds, from the kernel to containers, from databases to AI. With customers that include top tech brands, emerging startups, governments and home users, Canonical delivers trusted open source for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn more at &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/"&gt;canonical.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Canonical (Canonical)</author><category>Ubuntu</category><category>Ubuntu Pro</category><category>Ubuntu WSL</category><category>WSL</category><pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 12:50:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Canonical announces general availability of Ubuntu on Qualcomm Dragonwing™ IQ-9075 platform</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/canonical-qualcomm-dragonwing-iq9075</link><description>&lt;p&gt;December 1, 2025 – Canonical, the publisher of Ubuntu, today announced the availability of certified images for the Qualcomm Dragonwing™ IQ-9075 platform. This high-performance industrial platform is now fully supported with optimized images for Ubuntu 24.04 LTS. The certified images are available for both Ubuntu Server and Desktop, equipping developers with a robust and securely [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;December 1, 2025 – Canonical, the publisher of Ubuntu, today announced the availability of certified images for the Qualcomm Dragonwing™ IQ-9075 platform. This high-performance industrial platform is now fully supported with optimized images for Ubuntu 24.04 LTS. The certified images are available for both Ubuntu Server and Desktop, equipping developers with a robust and securely designed software foundation necessary for next-generation industrial automation, robotics, and edge AI applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This launch builds on the &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/blog/ubuntu-ga-for-qualcomm-dragonwing"&gt;general availability of Ubuntu for the QCS6490 and QCS5430 processors&lt;/a&gt;, with today’s announcement being the latest instance of Canonical support for Qualcomm’s Dragonwing™  processors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Resilience and performance for edge AI &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Qualcomm Dragonwing™ IQ-9075 is designed for the next generation of industrial automation systems, handling everything from real-time analytics to on-device Generative AI. Designed for extreme edge AI, IQ-9075 combines high-performance with physical resilience. The platform can deliver up to 100 TOPS of on-device AI compute in thermal junction temperatures ranging from -40℃ to +115℃. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By certifying Ubuntu for the IQ-9075 platform, Canonical ensures that enterprises get a seamless out-of-the-box experience from development to production. Through Ubuntu Pro, Canonical’s subscription for open source security, developers benefit from up to 15 years of long term support. Combined with Qualcomm’s decade-long product lifecycle, developers on IQ-9075 benefit from stability on both the hardware and software level. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a more detailed rundown of the features you can expect on the Qualcomm Dragonwing™ IQ-9075: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8 Kryo Gold Prime high-performance cores &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Up to 16 concurrent cameras for multi-stream computer vision&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;High throughput data processing for robotics and factory automation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Access to the full ecosystem of Ubuntu packages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;A partnership that empowers developers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are delighted to deepen our collaboration with Canonical by bringing certified Ubuntu support to the Qualcomm Dragonwing™ IQ-9075 processor,” said Laxmi Rayapudi, VP of Product Management, Qualcomm Technologies, Inc. “The IQ-9075 is designed for the most compute-intensive industrial tasks. Providing certified Ubuntu images – optimized and supported by Canonical – gives our ODMs and customers an essential, trusted software layer to deliver security-focused, high-performance edge solutions to market faster.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Ubuntu on Qualcomm Dragonwing™ IQ-9075 will accelerate the launch of AI-ready industrial devices at scale. This partnership will ensure high performance and robust security at both the hardware and software level.”  said Olivier Philippe, VP of Devices Engineering at Canonical. “Manufacturers using Qualcomm’s Dragonwing™ IQ-9075 platform will not only be ready for long term support and maintenance, but also benefit from the full power of open source AI software innovations optimized for the Dragonwing™ IQ-9075″.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Getting started&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To access the latest certified Ubuntu images for the Qualcomm Dragonwing™ IQ-9075 platform, please visit our &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/download/qualcomm-iot#evaluation-kit"&gt;Qualcomm IoT download page&lt;/a&gt;. If you have any questions about the platform or would like information about our certification program, then &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/download/qualcomm-iot#get-in-touch"&gt;contact us by filling out our dedicated form.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Canonical (Canonical)</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 18:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>AMI and Canonical announce partnership</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/ubuntu-boot-in-uefi-announcement</link><description>&lt;p&gt; Today, Canonical, the publisher of Ubuntu, announced a partnership with AMI, a provider of Unified Extensible Firmware Interface (UEFI) solutions, allowing users of AMI’s Aptio® V UEFI Firmware to netboot directly into Ubuntu by simply selecting Ubuntu Cloud Installation in the boot menu.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The collaboration makes it easy to boot directly into Ubuntu from AMI’s UEFI firmware solutions&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nuremberg, Germany, November 24, 2025 &lt;/strong&gt;– Today, Canonical, the publisher of Ubuntu, announced a partnership with AMI, a provider of Unified Extensible Firmware Interface (UEFI) solutions. The partnership will enable users of AMI’s Aptio® V UEFI Firmware to netboot directly into Ubuntu by simply selecting Ubuntu Cloud Installation in the boot menu.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This new native boot functionality makes it easy and convenient to use Ubuntu, and eliminates the need for flashing images or using additional media or external devices. A simple Ethernet connection is enough to install and launch Ubuntu.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="2048" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536px) 1536px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1536/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F6efe%2FUntitled-design-1.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F6efe%2FUntitled-design-1.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F6efe%2FUntitled-design-1.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F6efe%2FUntitled-design-1.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F6efe%2FUntitled-design-1.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F6efe%2FUntitled-design-1.png 1920w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1536/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F6efe%2FUntitled-design-1.png 1536w" width="1536"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Alexander Lehmann (Sales Director – IoT, Canonical) and B. Parthiban (General Manager, Boot Firmware Group at AMI) are excited to provide users with the best out-of-the-box experience for Ubuntu.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“At AMI, we value partnerships that strengthen the ecosystem and deliver trusted solutions. Canonical’s widely adopted, community-supported platform is recognized for its stability and reliability, making this collaboration a natural fit,” commented B. Parthiban, General Manager, Boot Firmware Group at AMI. “Together, we’re enabling secure, high-performance experiences for customers everywhere.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Our collaboration with AMI furthers our commitment to deliver the best Ubuntu experience right out of the box. It’s now even easier to install Ubuntu,” said Alexander Lehmann, Sales Director – IoT, at Canonical. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The collaboration between Canonical and AMI kicks off at SPS – the Smart Production Solutions summit  – in Nuremberg from November 25 to 27, 2025. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To find out more about Ubuntu, visit &lt;a href="https://sps.mesago.com/nuernberg/en/exhibitor-search.detail.html/canonical-group-limited.html"&gt;Canonical’s booth in hall 6, number 112&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://sps.mesago.com/nuernberg/en/exhibitor-search.detail.html/american-megatrends-international-gmbh.html"&gt;AMI’s booth in hall 6, number 223&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;* * *&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;About Canonical &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical, the publisher of Ubuntu Pro, provides open source security, support and services. Our portfolio covers critical systems, from the smallest devices to the largest clouds, from the kernel to containers, from databases to AI. With customers that include top tech brands, emerging startups, governments and home users, Canonical delivers trusted open source for everyone. Learn more at &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/"&gt;https://canonical.com/&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;About AMI&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AMI is Firmware Reimagined for modern computing. As a global leader in Dynamic Firmware for security, orchestration, and manageability solutions, AMI enables the world’s compute platforms from on-premises to the cloud to the edge. AMI’s industry-leading foundational technology and unwavering customer support have generated lasting partnerships and spurred innovation for some of the most prominent brands in the high-tech industry. AMI is a registered trademark of AMI US Holdings, Inc. Aptio is a registered trademark of AMI in the US and/or elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Canonical (Canonical)</author><category>Partner</category><category>Ubuntu</category><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 09:41:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The $8.8 trillion advantage: how open source software reduces IT costs </title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/the-8-8-trillion-advantage-how-open-source-software-reduces-it-costs</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Open source software is known for its ability to lower IT costs. But in 2025, affordability is only part of the story. A new Linux Foundation report, The strategic evolution of open source, reveals that open source has evolved from a tactical cost-saving measure to a mission-critical infrastructure supporting enterprise-grade investments, and delivering stronger business [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;Open source software is known for its ability to lower IT costs. But in 2025, affordability is only part of the story. A new Linux Foundation report, &lt;em&gt;&lt;mark class="has-inline-color has-black-color" style="background-color:rgba(0, 0, 0, 0)"&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/engage/world-of-open-source-global-2025"&gt;The strategic evolution of open source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, reveals that open source has evolved from a tactical cost-saving measure to a mission-critical infrastructure supporting enterprise-grade investments, and delivering stronger business outcomes as a result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This transformation is supported by academic research estimating that, without open source, companies would pay roughly 3.5 times more  to build the software running their businesses – an $8.8 trillion increase.[1] &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Open source: from “free alternative” to core infrastructure&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 2025 World of Open Source Survey by the Linux Foundation reveals that open source is deeply embedded across enterprise technology stacks, making it a foundation for global IT operations.  In fact, over 55% of analyzed tech stacks used a Linux-based operating system; and similarly, around half of all analyzed cloud, container, and DevOps technologies have Linux at their core.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The survey illuminates the many great reasons businesses are choosing open source: improved productivity, reduced vendor lock-in, and, unsurprisingly, lower total cost of ownership (TCO). Nearly half of organizations (46%) report an increase in business value from open source compared to last year, with 83% considering it valuable for their future. According to the World of Open Source Survey, 58% of organizations reported lower software ownership costs, and 63% cited higher productivity as a direct benefit of adopting open source. In addition, 62% reported reduced vendor lock-in and 75% judged their software quality to be higher thanks to OSS. Overall, 56% said the benefits of OSS exceeded the costs.[3] A Gartner study echoes these findings, showing that cost control and application development flexibility remain the top drivers of open source adoption.[2] &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it’s not just about the costs: organizations that invest strategically in open source are 20% more likely to perceive competitive advantage, while 78% report workplace satisfaction and better talent attraction. Nearly 80% say open source makes their organization a better workplace, and 74% say it improves their ability to attract technical talent. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One respondent put it this way: “Open source is not supplementary tooling but an ecosystem of core infrastructure dependencies.” This captures the shift perfectly: cost savings may start the conversation, but reliability, flexibility, and long-term value now drive adoption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Why open source reduces IT costs and keeps cutting them&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same characteristics that make open source adaptable also make it economical:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No per-seat licensing: organizations avoid scaling costs tied to user counts or cores&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Modular adoption: businesses can deploy only what they need, minimizing waste&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shared innovation: security fixes, feature improvements, and bug patches benefit from collective community investment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interoperability and exit freedom: avoiding proprietary lock-in reduces switching costs and enables infrastructure that fits business strategy rather than the vendor’s roadmap&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Systems based on open source tend to have lower maintenance overhead and longer life cycles, advantages that compound fast. That’s why enterprises see real savings,not just from shifting license costs to labor, but through genuine efficiency gains across teams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s a real-world case study of that in action: Greek telecom leader Nova leveraged Canonical’s planning and open pricing to control its CAPEX and OPEX, benefiting from predictable costs and freedom from management software licensing fees. Support from Canonical paid for “real expertise that enriches our team, rather than paying for access.”[3]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open source is also the backbone of AI, making it easier to adopt this increasingly must-have technology into business operations. McKinsey research highlights how open source frameworks accelerate AI adoption, enable faster product development, and catalyze ecosystem innovation, amplifying the total value beyond mere cost savings.[4] In fact, the LF’s survey found that AI is the technology that benefits the most from being open source, according to 38% of respondents, and research from the Microsoft AI cloud Partners team showed that Linux environments such as Ubuntu deploy 63% faster with up to 306% ROl over three years.[5]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Mission-critical workloads demand enterprise-ready support&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data is clear: open source software lowers IT costs, but cost benefits only reach their full potential when paired with enterprise-ready support. For technical audiences, this isn’t about “just” having a backstop: it’s about operational excellence, security, and resilience. When issues do arise, they must be addressed quickly and precisely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The survey shows 71% of organizations expect response times under 12 hours for critical OSS production issues, marking a shift from traditional community support to commercial-grade service-level agreements. In financial services and manufacturing, over 90% consider paid OSS support essential. This need for enterprise-grade support peaks in mission-critical workloads (54%), systems handling sensitive data (43%), and regulated sectors (38%).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a perception that support is ‘too expensive’, but quite to the contrary, paid commercial support does not diminish open source’s cost benefits; instead, it enhances them. Just like OSS adoption saves on costs and licences, robust support services protect organizations against the potentially disastrous costs of downtime, compliance failures, or data breaches. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical’s own experience confirms that long-term OSS support is an increasingly strategic investment, especially in markets with high regulatory demands and cloud migration complexities.[6]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take, for example, The European Space Agency (ESA), which depends on Canonical’s distributions of Kubeflow and Spark running on Kubernetes for its mission operations. ESA highlights that Canonical’s support lets them “sleep soundly,” focusing on space missions while trusting infrastructure experts for uptime and reliability.[3]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;How Ubuntu Pro locks in the value of open source&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest IT cost benefits of open source software come when free software innovation is combined with investments in professional support. After all, these low-cost (or sometimes free) tools are highly accessible and often intuitive to build with, but they can take a lot of time, effort, and specialized skills to maintain and secure in the long term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical takes away that time-consuming effort from developers, and allows them to focus on building, through Ubuntu Pro + Support, our comprehensive security maintenance and support service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; Ubuntu Pro + Support gives users a wide range of benefits, including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Up to 15 years of security maintenance and support covering thousands of open source components from the kernel to the applications layer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compliance-ready patching for mission-critical, regulated, and sensitive workloads.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Predictable enterprise SLAs aligned with the sub–12-hour incident response expectations of 71% of organizations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Transparent, forecastable total cost of ownership, eliminating license uncertainties.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu Pro extends cost benefits beyond licensing into comprehensive lifecycle management, turning open source affordability into sustained business value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Open source is an economic strategy, not a shortcut&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, the business benefits of open source are clear to see, and widely reflected in the business landscape, where record numbers of organizations and tech stacks have open source as a core part of their mission-critical systems. The permissive licences, lack of vendor lock-in, and flexibility of open source make it a clear cost optimizer; but the most significant IT cost savings emerge when organizations combine free software innovation with enterprise-grade support, governance, and active engagement. Those who treat open source as core infrastructure aren’t just saving money: they’re building competitive, secure, and innovative foundations for growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$8.8 trillion – that’s what open source is worth to the global economy. If you’re not building on it, you’re paying for it somewhere else. The organizations leading in innovation, efficiency, and resilience already know: open source is the foundation of competitive advantage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Sources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.library.hbs.edu/working-knowledge/open-source-software-the-nine-trillion-resource-companies-take-for-granted"&gt;Open Source Software: The $9 Trillion Resource Companies Take for Granted, HBS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gartner.com/peer-community/poll/top-challenges-to-using-open-source-product-application-development-flexibility-cost-control-some-factors-have-favored-open"&gt;Top challenges to using Open-source for product and application development, Gartner&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/blog/state-of-open-source-adoption-in-europe"&gt;What’s the state of open source adoption in Europe?, Ubuntu blog&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.mckinsey.com/capabilities/quantumblack/our-insights/open-source-technology-in-the-age-of-ai"&gt;Open source technology in the age of AI, McKinsey&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://azure.microsoft.com/en-us/blog/idc-business-value-study-a-306-roi-within-3-years-using-ubuntu-linux-on-azure/?wt.mc_id=po2kq97x8c"&gt;IDC Business Value Study: A 306% ROI within 3 years using Ubuntu Linux on Azure, Microsoft Azure&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/blog/54-of-european-enterprises-want-long-term-open-source-support-how-ubuntu-pro-support-delivers"&gt;54% of European enterprises want long term open source support: how Ubuntu Pro + Support delivers, Ubuntu blog&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.linuxfoundation.org/blog/the-value-of-open-source-software-is-more-than-cost-savings"&gt;The value of open source software is more than cost savings, Linux Foundation&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Lidia Luna Puerta (Lidia Luna Puerta)</author><category>Linux Foundation</category><category>Open source</category><category>Support</category><category>Ubuntu Pro</category><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 09:40:58 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>