<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Ubuntu blog</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/feed</link><description>Ubuntu blog feed</description><atom:link href="https://ubuntu.com//blog/feed" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>Python Feedgen</generator><lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 06:27:36 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>From cloud to dashboard: experience the future of infotainment development at CES 2026</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/future-of-infotainment-canonical-at-ces-2026</link><description>&lt;p&gt;This year, we’re excited to show a demo that combines the strengths of both Anbox Cloud and Rightware’s Kanzi, the industry-leading software for creating rich, visually stunning infotainment interfaces.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;Every year at CES, we try to go beyond showing technology; we want to give you an experience. This time, it’s the story of how in-vehicle infotainment development is transforming, and how developers can now build, test, and deploy immersive experiences faster than ever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, we’re excited to show a demo that combines the strengths of both Anbox Cloud and Rightware’s Kanzi, the industry-leading software for creating rich, visually stunning infotainment interfaces. It demonstrates cloud-native development, automation, and how virtualization can open up completely new ways to design and test next-generation in-vehicle experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="720" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1280px) 1280px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1280/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fa0b2%2Fimage.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fa0b2%2Fimage.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fa0b2%2Fimage.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fa0b2%2Fimage.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fa0b2%2Fimage.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fa0b2%2Fimage.png 1920w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1280/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fa0b2%2Fimage.png 1280w" width="1280"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Bridging design, development, and validation&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Automotive software development has become incredibly complex. Teams are often focused on their own discipline, UI designers on immersive experiences, Android developers on building integrations, and validation engineers on reliability across hardware variants. These teams can’t always collaborate seamlessly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Testing an infotainment system means being able to access specific hardware or prototypes, which makes iteration slow and collaboration difficult. Small design updates can take days to validate, and testing across different screen configurations or performance conditions is often limited by the availability of physical setups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We wanted to change that by bringing agility and scalability to infotainment development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Infotainment comes to life in the cloud&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our demo, we’ll show how Anbox Cloud turns this traditionally hardware-bound process into a fully virtualized, cloud-native experience. By running Android in the cloud, developers can instantly deploy and test infotainment environments built using Kanzi, on demand, at any scale, from anywhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="900" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1600px) 1600px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1600/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Ff2cd%2Fimage-1.jpeg" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Ff2cd%2Fimage-1.jpeg 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Ff2cd%2Fimage-1.jpeg 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Ff2cd%2Fimage-1.jpeg 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Ff2cd%2Fimage-1.jpeg 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Ff2cd%2Fimage-1.jpeg 1920w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1600/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Ff2cd%2Fimage-1.jpeg 1600w" width="1600"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p class="has-text-align-center"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Widescreen 8K infotainment CES demo&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our setup fits perfectly with Rightware’s widescreen 8K infotainment and cluster bench, powered by Kanzi. Developers can stream the exact same 8K rendering using Anbox Cloud. The result is an impressive, interactive experience, generated and streamed entirely from the cloud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="302" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1600px) 1600px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1600/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F9fea%2Fimage-1.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F9fea%2Fimage-1.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F9fea%2Fimage-1.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F9fea%2Fimage-1.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F9fea%2Fimage-1.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F9fea%2Fimage-1.png 1920w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1600/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F9fea%2Fimage-1.png 1600w" width="1600"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p class="has-text-align-center"&gt;&lt;em&gt;8K virtual Android device running on Anbox Cloud&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Anbox Cloud, Android can be virtualized to any resolution, with pixel-perfect rendering and responsiveness. It can scale to dozens of Android instances running simultaneously, so teams can run automated testing, validate UI performance, and work on the system updates in parallel. Your development becomes faster, collaborative, and independent of physical limitations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Why choose cloud-native Android development?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When moving your development testing to the cloud, designers and developers can collaborate in real time and can see their changes without waiting for hardware to be available. Validation teams can run automated tests on multiple Android instances, across different configurations. For OEMs and Tier 1 suppliers, this means shorter development cycles, meaning more efficient resource use, and faster results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Kanzi has always been about empowering designers and developers to bring exceptional in-vehicle experiences to life,” says Tero Koivu, Co-CEO at Rightware. “Seeing a Kanzi made UI streamed at 8K through Anbox Cloud shows how cloud-native workflows can dramatically accelerate iteration and collaboration. It opens a powerful new path for teams building the next generation of connected, visually stunning automotive user interfaces.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;See it at CES 2026&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Join us at LVCC, North Hall, Booth #10562, and check out the workflow for yourself. You’ll see how Kanzi and Anbox Cloud come together to deliver high-fidelity, scalable, cloud-native infotainment experiences, and how this is redefining the way developers can use Android in the cloud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://calendar.app.google/ao4AHxoZWGkx4wsBA"&gt;Book a meeting with our team&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Come see the future of automotive software development, from cloud to dashboard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, learn more about &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/anbox-cloud"&gt;Anbox Cloud&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://rightware.com"&gt;Rightware&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Further reading&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/anbox-cloud/#"&gt;Official documentation&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/anbox-cloud/howto/install-appliance/install-on-github/"&gt;Anbox Cloud Appliance&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://canonical.com/anbox-cloud"&gt;Learn more about Anbox Cloud &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Android is a trademark of Google LLC. Anbox Cloud uses assets available through the Android Open Source Project.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Bertrand Boisseau (Bertrand Boisseau)</author><category>Anbox</category><category>anbox cloud</category><category>Anbox Cloud Appliance</category><category>Automotive</category><category>CES</category><category>Event</category><pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Canonical announces Ubuntu Pro for WSL </title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/canonical-announces-ubuntu-pro-for-wsl</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu Pro for WSL provides turnkey security maintenance and enterprise support for Ubuntu 24.04 LTS WSL instances in Windows. The subscription will also enable comprehensive management for system administrators.&amp;nbsp; Today, Canonical announced the general availability of Ubuntu Pro for WSL&amp;nbsp;which can be installed from the Microsoft Store. Source and beta releases are also on GitHub. [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;h4 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Ubuntu Pro for WSL provides turnkey security maintenance and enterprise support for Ubuntu 24.04 LTS WSL instances in Windows. The subscription will also enable comprehensive management for system administrators. &lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, Canonical announced the general availability of Ubuntu Pro for WSL which can be installed from the Microsoft Store. Source and beta releases are also on &lt;a href="https://github.com/canonical/ubuntu-pro-for-wsl/releases"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="p-pull-quote--small"&gt;
&lt;p class="p-pull-quote__quote"&gt;Canonical and Microsoft have a fantastic partnership, building out the WSL experience. This work will benefit enterprise developers who use WSL to build production Linux solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;span class="p-pull-quote__citation"&gt;Craig Loewen, Product Manager for WSL at Microsoft&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu Pro delivers enterprise-grade security maintenance and support across desktops, servers, and IoT devices. Now, that same proven value proposition comes to WSL, addressing the security and compliance needs of IT managers and paving the way for broader enterprise adoption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="540" loading="lazy" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/VKdAcrdjQKI?si=lzmcSzSo8xohAa3R" title="YouTube video player" width="960"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Power to developers, peace of mind for IT teams&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WSL provides developers, system administrators, and power users with a native Linux experience on Windows, without the overhead of a full virtual machine or dual boot. It allows users to run Linux command-line tools, utilities, and graphical Linux applications directly on Windows. In collaboration with NVIDIA, WSL 2 delivers near-native GPU-accelerated-performance, allowing applications in Ubuntu to access GPU drivers directly on the Windows host. With Ubuntu Pro, this developer-focused tool is transformed into a fully supported, enterprise-ready solution with up to 15 years of security maintenance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For many enterprises, strict security and compliance policies have been a barrier to adopting WSL given the risks of unmonitored and unsupported open source software. Ubuntu Pro for WSL ensures Expanded Security Maintenance (ESM) is enabled, providing CVE security updates that can be applied subject to administrative policy. Canonical provides up to 15 years of CVE security patching for software packaged and published through Ubuntu’s repositories. Ubuntu Pro subscriptions also cover security maintenance for popular toolchains on WSL, such as Python, Go, Rust, and more. This turnkey solution ensures security vulnerabilities are patched quickly and reliably, making WSL a viable, compliant option for enterprise environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu Pro for WSL will also enable system administrators to manage instances using &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/landscape"&gt;Landscape&lt;/a&gt;, Canonical’s system management tool for Ubuntu. The WSL management feature of Landscape is in beta today, and customers interested in sharing feedback about the feature, and shaping its future, can do so in a self-hosted Landscape server, or by &lt;a href="https://landscape.canonical.com/signup"&gt;signing up for Landscape SaaS&lt;/a&gt;. Landscape will monitor all WSL instances that are deployed once Ubuntu Pro for WSL is configured, and identify which Windows hosts are compliant and which are non-compliant with your WSL provisioning and configuration policies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Seamless installation with Microsoft ecosystem tools&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personal users benefit from a point-and-click installation of Ubuntu Pro for WSL from within the Microsoft Store. As a standard MSIX package, Ubuntu Pro for WSL integrates seamlessly into existing enterprise management workflows, allowing for easy installation and configuration using Microsoft’s enterprise tools. Ubuntu Pro for WSL can be installed and configured using cloud-based tools such as Microsoft Intune, or via Group Policies defined in Microsoft Active Directory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped wp-block-gallery-1 is-layout-flex wp-block-gallery-is-layout-flex"&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-large"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="1080" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1920px) 1920px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F0b7f%2FUbuntu-Pro-on-Windows-1080p.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F0b7f%2FUbuntu-Pro-on-Windows-1080p.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F0b7f%2FUbuntu-Pro-on-Windows-1080p.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F0b7f%2FUbuntu-Pro-on-Windows-1080p.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F0b7f%2FUbuntu-Pro-on-Windows-1080p.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F0b7f%2FUbuntu-Pro-on-Windows-1080p.png 1920w" width="1920"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to being available in the Microsoft Store, images of Ubuntu on WSL are available for download and distribution behind a firewall, giving enterprises the option to host images internally, with centralized control over which WSL images are available to employees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Comprehensive enterprise support&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond security and ease of deployment, Ubuntu Pro for WSL introduces a new support model for developers using WSL. Canonical provides an Ubuntu Pro subscription tier which includes comprehensive phone and ticket support (Ubuntu Pro + Support). This provides a clear and streamlined way for Windows-native developers to get expert help with their Linux environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu Pro for WSL brings Canonical’s security and support capabilities into the Windows ecosystem. Free subscriptions for personal users and paid subscriptions are available through Canonical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Next steps&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/engage/ubuntu-on-wsl-enterprise?utm_source=blog&amp;amp;utm_medium=takeover&amp;amp;utm_campaign=701N100000b75KIIAY"&gt;Register for the webinar: Ubuntu on WSL in the enterprise&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class="p-cta-block"&gt;
&lt;a class="p-button--positive" href="https://github.com/canonical/ubuntu-pro-for-wsl/releases/latest/download/UbuntuProForWSL.msixbundle"&gt;Download Ubuntu Pro for WSL&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/wsl/latest/tutorials/getting-started-with-up4w/"&gt;Read the Ubuntu Pro for WSL tutorial ›&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;About Canonical&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical, the publisher of Ubuntu, provides open source security, support and services. Our portfolio covers critical systems, from the smallest devices to the largest clouds, from the kernel to containers, from databases to AI. With customers that include top tech brands, emerging startups, governments and home users, Canonical delivers trusted open source for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn more at &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/"&gt;canonical.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Canonical (Canonical)</author><category>Ubuntu</category><category>Ubuntu Pro</category><category>Ubuntu WSL</category><category>WSL</category><pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 12:50:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Canonical announces general availability of Ubuntu on Qualcomm Dragonwing™ IQ-9075 platform</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/canonical-qualcomm-dragonwing-iq9075</link><description>&lt;p&gt;December 1, 2025 – Canonical, the publisher of Ubuntu, today announced the availability of certified images for the Qualcomm Dragonwing™ IQ-9075 platform. This high-performance industrial platform is now fully supported with optimized images for Ubuntu 24.04 LTS. The certified images are available for both Ubuntu Server and Desktop, equipping developers with a robust and securely [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;December 1, 2025 – Canonical, the publisher of Ubuntu, today announced the availability of certified images for the Qualcomm Dragonwing™ IQ-9075 platform. This high-performance industrial platform is now fully supported with optimized images for Ubuntu 24.04 LTS. The certified images are available for both Ubuntu Server and Desktop, equipping developers with a robust and securely designed software foundation necessary for next-generation industrial automation, robotics, and edge AI applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This launch builds on the &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/blog/ubuntu-ga-for-qualcomm-dragonwing"&gt;general availability of Ubuntu for the QCS6490 and QCS5430 processors&lt;/a&gt;, with today’s announcement being the latest instance of Canonical support for Qualcomm’s Dragonwing™  processors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Resilience and performance for edge AI &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Qualcomm Dragonwing™ IQ-9075 is designed for the next generation of industrial automation systems, handling everything from real-time analytics to on-device Generative AI. Designed for extreme edge AI, IQ-9075 combines high-performance with physical resilience. The platform can deliver up to 100 TOPS of on-device AI compute in thermal junction temperatures ranging from -40℃ to +115℃. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By certifying Ubuntu for the IQ-9075 platform, Canonical ensures that enterprises get a seamless out-of-the-box experience from development to production. Through Ubuntu Pro, Canonical’s subscription for open source security, developers benefit from up to 15 years of long term support. Combined with Qualcomm’s decade-long product lifecycle, developers on IQ-9075 benefit from stability on both the hardware and software level. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a more detailed rundown of the features you can expect on the Qualcomm Dragonwing™ IQ-9075: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8 Kryo Gold Prime high-performance cores &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Up to 16 concurrent cameras for multi-stream computer vision&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;High throughput data processing for robotics and factory automation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Access to the full ecosystem of Ubuntu packages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;A partnership that empowers developers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are delighted to deepen our collaboration with Canonical by bringing certified Ubuntu support to the Qualcomm Dragonwing™ IQ-9075 processor,” said Laxmi Rayapudi, VP of Product Management, Qualcomm Technologies, Inc. “The IQ-9075 is designed for the most compute-intensive industrial tasks. Providing certified Ubuntu images – optimized and supported by Canonical – gives our ODMs and customers an essential, trusted software layer to deliver security-focused, high-performance edge solutions to market faster.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Ubuntu on Qualcomm Dragonwing™ IQ-9075 will accelerate the launch of AI-ready industrial devices at scale. This partnership will ensure high performance and robust security at both the hardware and software level.”  said Olivier Philippe, VP of Devices Engineering at Canonical. “Manufacturers using Qualcomm’s Dragonwing™ IQ-9075 platform will not only be ready for long term support and maintenance, but also benefit from the full power of open source AI software innovations optimized for the Dragonwing™ IQ-9075″.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Getting started&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To access the latest certified Ubuntu images for the Qualcomm Dragonwing™ IQ-9075 platform, please visit our &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/download/qualcomm-iot#evaluation-kit"&gt;Qualcomm IoT download page&lt;/a&gt;. If you have any questions about the platform or would like information about our certification program, then &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/download/qualcomm-iot#get-in-touch"&gt;contact us by filling out our dedicated form.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Canonical (Canonical)</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 18:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>AMI and Canonical announce partnership</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/ubuntu-boot-in-uefi-announcement</link><description>&lt;p&gt; Today, Canonical, the publisher of Ubuntu, announced a partnership with AMI, a provider of Unified Extensible Firmware Interface (UEFI) solutions, allowing users of AMI’s Aptio® V UEFI Firmware to netboot directly into Ubuntu by simply selecting Ubuntu Cloud Installation in the boot menu.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The collaboration makes it easy to boot directly into Ubuntu from AMI’s UEFI firmware solutions&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nuremberg, Germany, November 24, 2025 &lt;/strong&gt;– Today, Canonical, the publisher of Ubuntu, announced a partnership with AMI, a provider of Unified Extensible Firmware Interface (UEFI) solutions. The partnership will enable users of AMI’s Aptio® V UEFI Firmware to netboot directly into Ubuntu by simply selecting Ubuntu Cloud Installation in the boot menu.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This new native boot functionality makes it easy and convenient to use Ubuntu, and eliminates the need for flashing images or using additional media or external devices. A simple Ethernet connection is enough to install and launch Ubuntu.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="2048" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536px) 1536px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1536/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F6efe%2FUntitled-design-1.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F6efe%2FUntitled-design-1.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F6efe%2FUntitled-design-1.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F6efe%2FUntitled-design-1.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F6efe%2FUntitled-design-1.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F6efe%2FUntitled-design-1.png 1920w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1536/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F6efe%2FUntitled-design-1.png 1536w" width="1536"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Alexander Lehmann (Sales Director – IoT, Canonical) and B. Parthiban (General Manager, Boot Firmware Group at AMI) are excited to provide users with the best out-of-the-box experience for Ubuntu.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“At AMI, we value partnerships that strengthen the ecosystem and deliver trusted solutions. Canonical’s widely adopted, community-supported platform is recognized for its stability and reliability, making this collaboration a natural fit,” commented B. Parthiban, General Manager, Boot Firmware Group at AMI. “Together, we’re enabling secure, high-performance experiences for customers everywhere.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Our collaboration with AMI furthers our commitment to deliver the best Ubuntu experience right out of the box. It’s now even easier to install Ubuntu,” said Alexander Lehmann, Sales Director – IoT, at Canonical. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The collaboration between Canonical and AMI kicks off at SPS – the Smart Production Solutions summit  – in Nuremberg from November 25 to 27, 2025. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To find out more about Ubuntu, visit &lt;a href="https://sps.mesago.com/nuernberg/en/exhibitor-search.detail.html/canonical-group-limited.html"&gt;Canonical’s booth in hall 6, number 112&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://sps.mesago.com/nuernberg/en/exhibitor-search.detail.html/american-megatrends-international-gmbh.html"&gt;AMI’s booth in hall 6, number 223&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;* * *&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;About Canonical &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical, the publisher of Ubuntu Pro, provides open source security, support and services. Our portfolio covers critical systems, from the smallest devices to the largest clouds, from the kernel to containers, from databases to AI. With customers that include top tech brands, emerging startups, governments and home users, Canonical delivers trusted open source for everyone. Learn more at &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/"&gt;https://canonical.com/&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;About AMI&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AMI is Firmware Reimagined for modern computing. As a global leader in Dynamic Firmware for security, orchestration, and manageability solutions, AMI enables the world’s compute platforms from on-premises to the cloud to the edge. AMI’s industry-leading foundational technology and unwavering customer support have generated lasting partnerships and spurred innovation for some of the most prominent brands in the high-tech industry. AMI is a registered trademark of AMI US Holdings, Inc. Aptio is a registered trademark of AMI in the US and/or elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Canonical (Canonical)</author><category>Partner</category><category>Ubuntu</category><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 09:41:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The $8.8 trillion advantage: how open source software reduces IT costs </title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/the-8-8-trillion-advantage-how-open-source-software-reduces-it-costs</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Open source software is known for its ability to lower IT costs. But in 2025, affordability is only part of the story. A new Linux Foundation report, The strategic evolution of open source, reveals that open source has evolved from a tactical cost-saving measure to a mission-critical infrastructure supporting enterprise-grade investments, and delivering stronger business [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;Open source software is known for its ability to lower IT costs. But in 2025, affordability is only part of the story. A new Linux Foundation report, &lt;em&gt;&lt;mark class="has-inline-color has-black-color" style="background-color:rgba(0, 0, 0, 0)"&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/engage/world-of-open-source-global-2025"&gt;The strategic evolution of open source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, reveals that open source has evolved from a tactical cost-saving measure to a mission-critical infrastructure supporting enterprise-grade investments, and delivering stronger business outcomes as a result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This transformation is supported by academic research estimating that, without open source, companies would pay roughly 3.5 times more  to build the software running their businesses – an $8.8 trillion increase.[1] &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Open source: from “free alternative” to core infrastructure&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 2025 World of Open Source Survey by the Linux Foundation reveals that open source is deeply embedded across enterprise technology stacks, making it a foundation for global IT operations.  In fact, over 55% of analyzed tech stacks used a Linux-based operating system; and similarly, around half of all analyzed cloud, container, and DevOps technologies have Linux at their core.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The survey illuminates the many great reasons businesses are choosing open source: improved productivity, reduced vendor lock-in, and, unsurprisingly, lower total cost of ownership (TCO). Nearly half of organizations (46%) report an increase in business value from open source compared to last year, with 83% considering it valuable for their future. According to the World of Open Source Survey, 58% of organizations reported lower software ownership costs, and 63% cited higher productivity as a direct benefit of adopting open source. In addition, 62% reported reduced vendor lock-in and 75% judged their software quality to be higher thanks to OSS. Overall, 56% said the benefits of OSS exceeded the costs.[3] A Gartner study echoes these findings, showing that cost control and application development flexibility remain the top drivers of open source adoption.[2] &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it’s not just about the costs: organizations that invest strategically in open source are 20% more likely to perceive competitive advantage, while 78% report workplace satisfaction and better talent attraction. Nearly 80% say open source makes their organization a better workplace, and 74% say it improves their ability to attract technical talent. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One respondent put it this way: “Open source is not supplementary tooling but an ecosystem of core infrastructure dependencies.” This captures the shift perfectly: cost savings may start the conversation, but reliability, flexibility, and long-term value now drive adoption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Why open source reduces IT costs and keeps cutting them&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same characteristics that make open source adaptable also make it economical:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No per-seat licensing: organizations avoid scaling costs tied to user counts or cores&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Modular adoption: businesses can deploy only what they need, minimizing waste&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shared innovation: security fixes, feature improvements, and bug patches benefit from collective community investment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interoperability and exit freedom: avoiding proprietary lock-in reduces switching costs and enables infrastructure that fits business strategy rather than the vendor’s roadmap&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Systems based on open source tend to have lower maintenance overhead and longer life cycles, advantages that compound fast. That’s why enterprises see real savings,not just from shifting license costs to labor, but through genuine efficiency gains across teams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s a real-world case study of that in action: Greek telecom leader Nova leveraged Canonical’s planning and open pricing to control its CAPEX and OPEX, benefiting from predictable costs and freedom from management software licensing fees. Support from Canonical paid for “real expertise that enriches our team, rather than paying for access.”[3]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open source is also the backbone of AI, making it easier to adopt this increasingly must-have technology into business operations. McKinsey research highlights how open source frameworks accelerate AI adoption, enable faster product development, and catalyze ecosystem innovation, amplifying the total value beyond mere cost savings.[4] In fact, the LF’s survey found that AI is the technology that benefits the most from being open source, according to 38% of respondents, and research from the Microsoft AI cloud Partners team showed that Linux environments such as Ubuntu deploy 63% faster with up to 306% ROl over three years.[5]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Mission-critical workloads demand enterprise-ready support&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data is clear: open source software lowers IT costs, but cost benefits only reach their full potential when paired with enterprise-ready support. For technical audiences, this isn’t about “just” having a backstop: it’s about operational excellence, security, and resilience. When issues do arise, they must be addressed quickly and precisely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The survey shows 71% of organizations expect response times under 12 hours for critical OSS production issues, marking a shift from traditional community support to commercial-grade service-level agreements. In financial services and manufacturing, over 90% consider paid OSS support essential. This need for enterprise-grade support peaks in mission-critical workloads (54%), systems handling sensitive data (43%), and regulated sectors (38%).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a perception that support is ‘too expensive’, but quite to the contrary, paid commercial support does not diminish open source’s cost benefits; instead, it enhances them. Just like OSS adoption saves on costs and licences, robust support services protect organizations against the potentially disastrous costs of downtime, compliance failures, or data breaches. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical’s own experience confirms that long-term OSS support is an increasingly strategic investment, especially in markets with high regulatory demands and cloud migration complexities.[6]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take, for example, The European Space Agency (ESA), which depends on Canonical’s distributions of Kubeflow and Spark running on Kubernetes for its mission operations. ESA highlights that Canonical’s support lets them “sleep soundly,” focusing on space missions while trusting infrastructure experts for uptime and reliability.[3]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;How Ubuntu Pro locks in the value of open source&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest IT cost benefits of open source software come when free software innovation is combined with investments in professional support. After all, these low-cost (or sometimes free) tools are highly accessible and often intuitive to build with, but they can take a lot of time, effort, and specialized skills to maintain and secure in the long term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical takes away that time-consuming effort from developers, and allows them to focus on building, through Ubuntu Pro + Support, our comprehensive security maintenance and support service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; Ubuntu Pro + Support gives users a wide range of benefits, including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Up to 15 years of security maintenance and support covering thousands of open source components from the kernel to the applications layer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compliance-ready patching for mission-critical, regulated, and sensitive workloads.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Predictable enterprise SLAs aligned with the sub–12-hour incident response expectations of 71% of organizations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Transparent, forecastable total cost of ownership, eliminating license uncertainties.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu Pro extends cost benefits beyond licensing into comprehensive lifecycle management, turning open source affordability into sustained business value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Open source is an economic strategy, not a shortcut&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, the business benefits of open source are clear to see, and widely reflected in the business landscape, where record numbers of organizations and tech stacks have open source as a core part of their mission-critical systems. The permissive licences, lack of vendor lock-in, and flexibility of open source make it a clear cost optimizer; but the most significant IT cost savings emerge when organizations combine free software innovation with enterprise-grade support, governance, and active engagement. Those who treat open source as core infrastructure aren’t just saving money: they’re building competitive, secure, and innovative foundations for growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$8.8 trillion – that’s what open source is worth to the global economy. If you’re not building on it, you’re paying for it somewhere else. The organizations leading in innovation, efficiency, and resilience already know: open source is the foundation of competitive advantage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Sources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.library.hbs.edu/working-knowledge/open-source-software-the-nine-trillion-resource-companies-take-for-granted"&gt;Open Source Software: The $9 Trillion Resource Companies Take for Granted, HBS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gartner.com/peer-community/poll/top-challenges-to-using-open-source-product-application-development-flexibility-cost-control-some-factors-have-favored-open"&gt;Top challenges to using Open-source for product and application development, Gartner&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/blog/state-of-open-source-adoption-in-europe"&gt;What’s the state of open source adoption in Europe?, Ubuntu blog&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.mckinsey.com/capabilities/quantumblack/our-insights/open-source-technology-in-the-age-of-ai"&gt;Open source technology in the age of AI, McKinsey&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://azure.microsoft.com/en-us/blog/idc-business-value-study-a-306-roi-within-3-years-using-ubuntu-linux-on-azure/?wt.mc_id=po2kq97x8c"&gt;IDC Business Value Study: A 306% ROI within 3 years using Ubuntu Linux on Azure, Microsoft Azure&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/blog/54-of-european-enterprises-want-long-term-open-source-support-how-ubuntu-pro-support-delivers"&gt;54% of European enterprises want long term open source support: how Ubuntu Pro + Support delivers, Ubuntu blog&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.linuxfoundation.org/blog/the-value-of-open-source-software-is-more-than-cost-savings"&gt;The value of open source software is more than cost savings, Linux Foundation&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Lidia Luna Puerta (Lidia Luna Puerta)</author><category>Linux Foundation</category><category>Open source</category><category>Support</category><category>Ubuntu Pro</category><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 09:40:58 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Open design: the opportunity design students didn’t know they were missing</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/open-design-the-opportunity-design-students-didnt-know-they-were-missing</link><description>&lt;p&gt;What if you could work on real-world projects, shape cutting-edge technology, collaborate with developers across the world, make a meaningful impact with your design skills, and grow your portfolio… all without applying for an internship or waiting for graduation? That’s what we aim to do with open design: an opportunity for universities and students of [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="372" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 660px) 660px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_660/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2e37%2Fimage.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2e37%2Fimage.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2e37%2Fimage.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2e37%2Fimage.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_660/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2e37%2Fimage.png 660w" width="660"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if you could work on real-world projects, shape cutting-edge technology, collaborate with developers across the world, make a meaningful impact with your design skills, and grow your portfolio… all without applying for an internship or waiting for graduation?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s what we aim to do with open design: an opportunity for universities and students of any design discipline. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;What is open design, and why does it matter?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we go further, let’s talk about what open design is. Many open source tools are built by developers, for developers, without design in mind. When open source software powers &lt;a href="https://static.carahsoft.com/concrete/files/1617/1597/8665/2024_Open_Source_Security_and_Risk_Analysis_Report_WRAPPED.pdf"&gt;90% of the digital world&lt;/a&gt; (PDF), it leaves everyday users feeling overwhelmed or left out. Open design wants to bridge that gap. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We aim to introduce human-centred thinking into open source development, enhancing these tools to be more intuitive, inclusive, and user-friendly. Most open source projects focus on code contributions, neglecting design contributions. That leaves a vast number of projects without a design system, accessibility audits, or onboarding documentation. That’s where designers come in, helping shape better user experiences and more welcoming communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open design is about more than just aesthetics. Open design helps to make technology work for people; that’s exactly what open source needs. Learn more about open design on our &lt;a href="https://canonical.design/open-design"&gt;webpage&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We want to raise awareness for the projects,  the problems that currently exist, and how we can fix them together,  and encourage universities and students to become advocates of open design. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We want universities to connect their students to real-world, meaningful design opportunities in a field that is currently lacking the creativity of designers. Our goal is to help and motivate students to bring their design skills into open source projects and become advocates, to make open design accessible, practical, and empowering! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;How Canonical helps universities access open design&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We want to help universities help students to access:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Real-world experiences:&lt;/strong&gt; Students apply their design skills to global projects to create valuable, demonstrable outcomes, beyond hypothetical briefs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Interdisciplinary growth:&lt;/strong&gt; Empower students to gain collaborative experience with developers, and navigate real tech workflows&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accessible opportunities:&lt;/strong&gt; No interviews, no barriers; just impact, experience, and learning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have provided universities with talks and project briefs, enabling them to prepare students to utilise their expertise and design a brighter future for open source. If you’re a department leader, instructor, or coordinator, &lt;a href="https://canonical.design/open-design/get-started-for-designers"&gt;exploring open source and open design&lt;/a&gt; will help you to give your students unique access to industry-aligned experiences, while embedding values of collaboration, open contribution, and inclusive design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Why should students care?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re a student in UX, UI, interaction, service, visual, HCI design, or &lt;strong&gt;any other field with design influence&lt;/strong&gt;, you’ve been told how important it is to build your portfolio, gain hands-on experience, and collaborate with cross-functional teams. Open design is your opportunity to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best part is, you don’t have to write a single line of code to make a difference! Open source projects are looking for:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;UX/UI improvements&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Accessibility and heuristic audits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;User research and persona development&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;User flows and wireframes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Information architecture reviews&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Design documentation and feedback systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re in a design course, you already have, or are developing, the skills that open-source projects need. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open design is an opportunity to develop by collaborating across disciplines, navigating ambiguity, and advocating for users: skills employers value. With open design, you’ll gain confidence in presenting ideas, working with international teams, and handling feedback in a real-world setting, growing in ways that classroom projects and internships often don’t offer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re aiming for a tech-focused design career, open design is one of the most impactful and distinctive ways to stand out!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;How can you start?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting started is easier than you think, even if GitHub looks scary at first. Here’s how:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Learn the basics of GitHub&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve made a &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/rIN3Tr1xRIw?si=WqMUIKZ3RrbGwUh2"&gt;video guide to understanding GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, and curated a list of other &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1sy-KSbA3WATYD20lWXOcRLIGxLOTJjZKDUhpNn-shZA/edit?tab=t.0#heading=h.cdj6wh5znx6k"&gt;videos&lt;/a&gt; to get to grips with GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start="2"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Find a project on &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://contribute.design/for-designers"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;contribute.design&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s like a job board for design contributions. These projects are waiting for you. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start="3"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Understand the project’s needs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most projects on &lt;a href="https://contribute.design/for-designers"&gt;contribute.design&lt;/a&gt; list what they’re looking for in .design file or DESIGN.md guidelines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start="4"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pick an issue, or propose your own&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Navigate to the Issues tab of the project repo, where you can filter for issues labelled for design. You can also use this tab to propose any issues you discover in the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start="5"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contribute, collaborate, grow&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start adding your ideas, questions, and solutions to issues. You’ll be collaborating, communicating, and making meaningful contributions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can explore more projects through the &lt;a href="https://github.com/explore"&gt;GitHub Explore&lt;/a&gt; page, but not every project will have a design process in place; that’s where your skills are especially valuable. If you don’t see design issues, treat the project as a blank canvas. Suggest checklists, organise a design system, or improve documentation. The power is in your hands!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reach out to maintainers, join community discussions, and don’t hesitate to introduce design-focused thinking. Your initiative can spark meaningful change and help open source become more user-friendly, one project at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;View every project as an opportunity; you don’t need an invitation to contribute, just curiosity, creativity, and the willingness to collaborate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Interested? &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re looking for universities and departments interested in introducing open design to their students. Whether that’s through a talk, module project briefs, or anything else you’d like to see, we’re excited to find ways to work together and bring open design to campus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you a program director, a design department, a student group, or an interested student? Let’s talk!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reach out at &lt;a href="mailto:opendesign@canonical.com"&gt;opendesign@canonical.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Miguel Divo (Miguel Divo)</author><category>Design</category><category>open design</category><category>University</category><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 09:39:51 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Anbox Cloud 1.28.0 is now available!</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/anbox-cloud-1-28-0-is-now-available</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Enhanced Android device simulation, smarter diagnostics, and OIDC-enforced authentication The Anbox Cloud team has been working around the clock to release Anbox Cloud 1.28.0! We’re very proud of this release that adds robust authentication, improved diagnostic tools, and expanded simulation options, making Anbox Cloud even more secure, flexible, and developer-friendly for running large-scale Android workloads. [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;Enhanced Android device simulation, smarter diagnostics, and OIDC-enforced authentication&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Anbox Cloud team has been working around the clock to release Anbox Cloud 1.28.0! We’re very proud of this release that adds robust authentication, improved diagnostic tools, and expanded simulation options, making Anbox Cloud even more secure, flexible, and developer-friendly for running large-scale Android workloads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s go over the most significant changes in this new version.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Strengthened authentication and authorization&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our OpenID Connect (OIDC)-based authentication and authorization framework is now stable with Anbox Cloud 1.28.0. This new framework provides a standardized approach for controlling access across web and command-line clients. Operators can now assign permissions through entitlements with fine-grained control, define authorization groups, and create and manage identities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Configuring user permissions, understanding the idea of identities and groups, and looking through the entire list of available entitlements are all thoroughly covered in the &lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/anbox-cloud/howto/anbox/auth/#howto-auth"&gt;new guides&lt;/a&gt; that come with this release. This represents a significant advancement in the direction of a more uniform and standards-based access model for all Anbox Cloud deployments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Simulated SMS support&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is one of our most exciting new features: developers testing telephony-enabled applications in Anbox Cloud can now simulate incoming SMS messages using the Anbox runtime HTTP API. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This new functionality allows messages to trigger notifications the same way they would on a physical device, generating more realistic end-to-end scenarios. A &lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/anbox-cloud/howto/android/simulate-incoming-sms/#howto-simulate-incoming-sms"&gt;new how-to guide&lt;/a&gt; in our documentation provides detailed instructions on how to enable and use this feature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Protection against accidental deletions&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because we know accidents happen (especially in production environments…), in order to reduce operational risk, this release introduces the ability to protect instances from accidental deletion. This option can be enabled directly in the dashboard either when creating a new instance or later from the Instance details page under the Security section. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once this protection option is turned on, the instance cannot be deleted, even during bulk delete operations, until the configuration is reset. This simple safeguard helps operators preserve important data and prevents costly mistakes in busy environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Improved ADB share management&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working with ADB (the Android Debug Bridge) has also become more flexible. Anbox Cloud now allows up to five ADB shares to be managed directly from the dashboard. For those who prefer the command line, the new amc connect command provides an alternative to the existing anbox-connect tool. Together, these improvements make it easier for developers to manage and maintain multiple debugging or testing sessions at once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;New diagnostic facility for troubleshooting&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With version 1.28.0, we’re introducing a new diagnostic facility in the dashboard. This tool is designed to simplify troubleshooting for both the instances and the streaming sessions themselves. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This feature helps collect relevant diagnostic data automatically, thereby reducing the work needed to identify and resolve issues. It also makes collaboration with our Canonical support teams more efficient, as users can now provide consistent and accurate diagnostic information in a structured, standard format.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Sensor support in the Streaming SDK&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s another hotly anticipated feature: the Anbox Streaming SDK gains expanded sensor support in this release. Our SDK now includes gyroscope, accelerometer and orientation sensors, allowing developers to test applications more interactively. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sensor support is disabled by default but can be easily enabled in the streaming client configuration. This addition opens up new possibilities for interactive use cases, such as gaming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Upgrade now and stay tuned!&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We think that Anbox Cloud 1.28.0 is our best release to date, and we are pleased to keep providing a feature-rich, scalable, and safe solution for managing Android workloads on a large scale. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This latest version makes it easier than ever for developers and operators to create and test Android apps by introducing more precise device simulation, improved troubleshooting tools, and stricter access controls, as we’ve explained above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try it now and stay tuned for further developments in our upcoming releases. For detailed instructions on how to upgrade your existing deployment, please refer to the &lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/anbox-cloud/en/latest/howto/update/upgrade-anbox/#howto-upgrade-anbox-cloud"&gt;official documentation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Further reading&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/anbox-cloud/#"&gt;Official documentation&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/anbox-cloud/howto/install-appliance/install-on-github/"&gt;Anbox Cloud Appliance&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://canonical.com/anbox-cloud"&gt;Learn more about Anbox Cloud or contact our team to discuss your use case&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Android is a trademark of Google LLC. Anbox Cloud uses assets available through the Android Open Source Project.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Bertrand Boisseau (Bertrand Boisseau)</author><category>Anbox</category><category>anbox cloud</category><category>Anbox Cloud Appliance</category><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>83% of organizations see value in adopting open source, but report major gaps in security and governance</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/state-of-global-open-source-2025</link><description>&lt;p&gt;A new Linux Foundation report reveals how organizations worldwide are adopting, using, and perceiving open source software. The Linux Foundation’s latest report, The state of global open source, has just been released in collaboration with Canonical. The report follows the Linux Foundation’s European spotlight report, released earlier this year, and confirms that many of the [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;A new Linux Foundation report reveals how organizations worldwide are adopting, using, and perceiving open source software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Linux Foundation’s latest &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/engage/world-of-open-source-global-2025"&gt;report&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;The state of global open source&lt;/em&gt;, has just been released in collaboration with Canonical. The report follows &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/blog/open-source-advantage-europe"&gt;the Linux Foundation’s European spotlight report&lt;/a&gt;, released earlier this year, and confirms that many of the trends the European spotlight report unveiled are true on a global scale. In particular, the global spotlight report confirms the role of open source software as the foundation of business-critical systems worldwide, and indicates a continued increase in adoption. However, organizations continue to lack the governance, security testing, and strategic maturity required to manage open source strategically and securely. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The report suggests that most organizations expect enterprise-grade performance from open source software, but under-invest in the required governance frameworks, security practices, and community engagement. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/engage/world-of-open-source-global-2025"&gt;&lt;button class="p-button--positive"&gt;Download the report&lt;/button&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;83% of organizations acknowledge open source is valuable to their future&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the report, the trend of increasing open source adoption in the enterprise is set to continue, as 83% of enterprises consider open source software adoption valuable to their future. Likewise, the report reveals the centrality of open source software to the modern enterprise. Globally, enterprises have adopted open source software throughout their technical stacks: 55% have adopted open source operating systems, whilst 49% have adopted open source cloud and container technologies, and 46% open source web and application development. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The widespread confidence that open source will play a pivotal role in many organizations’ futures is closely connected to a growing understanding of the benefits of open source software adoption.   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;86% report open source software improves productivity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This report confirms a shift in enterprises’ strategic mindset around open source: 82% of respondents considered open source as an asset that enables innovation. Historically, open source software was often reserved for specific projects or use cases, like setting up web servers – with wider organizational use being viewed with some scepticism. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open source is now a “must-have.” Why is this the case? Here’s what the respondents had to say: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;86% stated that open source improves productivity &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;79% reported improved software quality as a result of open source&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;78% highlighted improved security&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="701" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1180px) 1180px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1180/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F9d4b%2FGraph-Linux-Foundation-2025-World-of-Open-Source-Global-Report.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F9d4b%2FGraph-Linux-Foundation-2025-World-of-Open-Source-Global-Report.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F9d4b%2FGraph-Linux-Foundation-2025-World-of-Open-Source-Global-Report.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F9d4b%2FGraph-Linux-Foundation-2025-World-of-Open-Source-Global-Report.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F9d4b%2FGraph-Linux-Foundation-2025-World-of-Open-Source-Global-Report.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F9d4b%2FGraph-Linux-Foundation-2025-World-of-Open-Source-Global-Report.png 1920w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1180/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F9d4b%2FGraph-Linux-Foundation-2025-World-of-Open-Source-Global-Report.png 1180w" width="1180"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compared to the benefits seen by organizations using open source software in 2024, 46% reported increased business value from open source over the past year. The growing interest in and use of open source technologies is particularly clear for certain technologies, like AI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;AI technologies benefit most from being open source&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The growing value of open source can partly be attributed to the influence of AI. Since 2024, there has been an increase in the adoption of open source AI and machine learning (ML) applications from 35% to 40% – a rise of 5%. Globally, AI and ML were perceived to be the technology most benefiting from being open source. Code visibility ensures organizations can more easily audit their AI systems, which makes compliance simpler, provides more transparency into how the AI model functions, and enables companies to run the AI on their own infrastructure – ensuring sensitive data never leaves the organization’s control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With growing adoption of AI and ML come new cybersecurity risks and requirements. However, the report indicates that organizations currently lack mature governance structures for their open source estates, creating additional complications to adopting AI and ML securely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Lack of mature governance: only 34% of organizations have defined a clear open source strategy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite increasing adoption of open source technologies, many organizations still lack a mature governance strategy for their open source software. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The number of organizations that have defined a clear open source strategy has grown by just 2% in the last year, to a total of 34%. That means that nearly two-thirds of organizations rely instead on informal strategies of governance of their open source estates, primarily due to budget constraints, shifting priorities and new strategic requirements. For example, when evaluating open source components for adoption:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;44% of organizations check the activity level of the project community&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;31% use automated security testing tools&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;28% manually review the source code&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;36% evaluate the direct dependencies of the open source component&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With less than half of organizations taking these important formal strategies before adoption, the report indicates that this “creates significant risk exposure and limits organizations’ ability to capture the full strategic value of open source participation,” signalling that this is a concern that organizations must take seriously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, organizations demonstrate a lack of consensus around which security features and assurances matter to them when adopting open source components, with no single certification or assurance mechanism achieving adoption by more than a quarter of open source solutions. Almost a third of organizations (28%) don’t know which assurances would make them more likely to trust an open source solution. This opens them up to serious security risks, like supply chain attacks.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result, enterprises are increasingly turning to paid support options for their open source estates. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;54% view paid support as essential for mission-critical workloads&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than half of respondents consider paid support for their open source essential. As open source technologies have become critical to business infrastructure, expectations for open source software support are beginning to mirror that of commercial software standards: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;71% of organizations expect response times of less than 12 hours from support providers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;47% expect rapid security patching for open source software in production environments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;53% expect long term support guarantees for their open source software. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Acquiring paid support for open source software makes this level of support achievable, which organizations broadly accept. On a granular level, the industries with the highest proportion that consider paid support essential are those that process sensitive or valuable data, such as manufacturing (97%) followed by financial services (96%), IT (91%) and government (92%). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Conclusion and recommendations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Linux Foundation’s &lt;em&gt;The state of global open source&lt;/em&gt; reveals that enterprises are relying on open source software and perceiving its benefits. However, increasing engagement with open source communities, more structured governance of open source estates, and structured security evaluations of open source elements before adoption will help organizations to strengthen the resilience of their open source infrastructure. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="p-cta-block"&gt;
&lt;a class="p-button--positive" href="https://ubuntu.com/engage/world-of-open-source-global-2025"&gt;Download the report&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://canonical.com/open-source-adoption"&gt;Adopt open source in your enterprise with Canonical ›&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Canonical (Canonical)</author><pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 16:10:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Everything you need to know about FIPS 140-3 on Ubuntu | Videos </title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/everything-you-need-to-know-about-fips-140-3-on-ubuntu-videos</link><description>&lt;p&gt;We get a lot of questions about FIPS 140-3, and so we decided to put together this comprehensive collection of video resources to answer the most burning ones we’ve had so far. &lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;FIPS 140 is a highly demanding security standard that’s mandatory for almost all high-security and federal environments. It can be hard to get right and may be a daunting part of the journey for those trying to meet compliance requirements like FedRAMP or CMMC. We get &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt; of questions about FIPS 140-3, and so we decided to put together this comprehensive collection of video resources to answer the most burning ones we’ve had so far. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this collection, you’ll be able to get answers to the most frequently asked FIPS questions, including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to enable FIPS 140-3 on Ubuntu 22.04&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to check if you’re operating in FIPS mode&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to enable FIPS on public clouds: AWS, Azure, GCP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Which modules and hardware have been FIPS 140-3 certified for Ubuntu &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Which FIPS-enabled Docker containers are available in Iron Bank &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the most common issues when enabling FIPS 140-3 &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;How to enable FIPS on Ubuntu?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"&gt;&lt;div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper"&gt;
&lt;iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="304" loading="lazy" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/KcbKMMHC-KU?list=PLwFSk464RMxkQhlIXi-HdQrq4-ZjTJewL" title="How to enable FIPS 140-3 on Ubuntu" width="540"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ll start with the most common question: how do you enable FIPS on Ubuntu? The basic prerequisite is an Ubuntu Pro subscription, which is available either free for personal use or with a 30-day free trial for enterprise users. After subscribing, you’ll get access to a dashboard where you can find a token that you can attach to an Ubuntu instance and get access to the FIPS certified modules. All you need to do is open your terminal and enter the following commands: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo pro attach &amp;lt;token&amp;gt;

sudo pro enable fips-updates

sudo reboot&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should see output like the following, indicating that the FIPS packages have been installed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;Installing FIPS Updates packages

FIPS Updates enabled

A reboot is required to complete install.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enabling FIPS should be performed during a system maintenance window since this operation makes changes to underlying SSL-related libraries and requires a reboot into the FIPS-certified kernel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;How to check if you’re operating in FIPS mode&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"&gt;&lt;div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper"&gt;
&lt;iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="304" loading="lazy" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/W9ZJXHEeSNQ?list=PLwFSk464RMxkQhlIXi-HdQrq4-ZjTJewL" title="How to check if you're operating in FIPS mode" width="540"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After enabling FIPS mode, it is good to verify that it is activated. Luckily it’s very straightforward to verify that FIPS mode is enabled. Just run this command in the terminal:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;cat /proc/sys/crypto/fips_enabled&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The output that indicates that FIPS mode is enabled is “&lt;strong&gt;1&lt;/strong&gt;”. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;How to enable FIPS on public clouds&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"&gt;&lt;div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper"&gt;
&lt;iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="304" loading="lazy" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Zd4ucUhaGWU?list=PLwFSk464RMxkQhlIXi-HdQrq4-ZjTJewL" title="Enabling FIPS on public clouds" width="540"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is very easy to enable FIPS in public clouds. In contrast to on-prem usage, Ubuntu images for public clouds already have FIPS enabled. Decide on the Ubuntu version you’d like to run, visit the relevant marketplace for your public cloud provider (for example: &lt;a href="https://aws.amazon.com/marketplace/pp/prodview-o5noqh44k3uxm"&gt;AWS&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://azuremarketplace.microsoft.com/en-us/marketplace/apps/canonical.0001-com-ubuntu-pro-jammy-fips?tab=Overview"&gt;Azure&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href="https://console.cloud.google.com/compute/instancesAdd?imageId=4467206581577450407&amp;amp;imageProjectId=ubuntu-os-pro-cloud&amp;amp;pli=1"&gt;GCP&lt;/a&gt;), and search for the relevant image. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Which modules and hardware have been FIPS 140-3 certified &lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"&gt;&lt;div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper"&gt;
&lt;iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="304" loading="lazy" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/tG2Sfjr2sRk?list=PLwFSk464RMxkQhlIXi-HdQrq4-ZjTJewL" title="FIPS certified modules and hardware for Ubuntu" width="540"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes it can be tricky to figure out exactly which modules and hardware have been FIPS 140-3 certified. This video goes into extensive detail outlining the modules and components you’ll be able to make full use of with FIPS 140-3 certified Ubuntu. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To give a brief overview, the following certified cryptographic modules are available with Ubuntu 22.04 LTS:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;OpenSSL v3.0.5&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Libgcrypt v1.9.4&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;GnuTLS v3.7.3&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Linux kernel v5.15.0&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;StrongSwan v5.9.5&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These modules have been developed and tested on a range of hardware platforms:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Intel/AMD x86_64&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ARM64&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IBM z15&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;FIPS-enabled containers available in Iron Bank &lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"&gt;&lt;div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper"&gt;
&lt;iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="304" loading="lazy" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/hwdoRlKjnkA?list=PLwFSk464RMxkQhlIXi-HdQrq4-ZjTJewL" title="FIPS enabled containers" width="540"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical’s container images are trusted and pre-approved for high-security use cases. Hardened Ubuntu images are already certified and available in the U.S. Department of Defense’s Iron Bank, the official repository of security-hardened containers for government systems. You can find the code to build your own image &lt;a href="https://ironbank.dso.mil/repomap/details;registry1Path=canonical%252Fubuntu-pro-cis-fips-stig"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, or get the actual container that passed all the automated compliance checks &lt;a href="https://ironbank.dso.mil/repomap/details;registry1Path=canonical%252Fubuntu-pro-cis-fips-stig"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Note, you would need to first register to get access to the platform. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical has also &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/engage/secure-federal-cloud-native-stack-k8s"&gt;recently added FIPS and STIG-compliance to Canonical Kubernetes.&lt;/a&gt; Built on Ubuntu Pro hosts, Canonical Kubernetes now includes FIPS 140-3 validated crypto modules out of the box and can be hardened for DISA-STIG. This means you can deploy secure, compliant clusters built on Ubuntu, making it much easier to meet FedRAMP and other federal compliance requirements right from your Kubernetes base.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Common issues when enabling FIPS 140-3 &lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"&gt;&lt;div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper"&gt;
&lt;iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="304" loading="lazy" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/OwGBfrdMFlw?list=PLwFSk464RMxkQhlIXi-HdQrq4-ZjTJewL" title="Common issues when enabling FIPS" width="540"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compliance always comes with challenges, but when we know the issues, we can help. The video above explains how to solve the most common issues that teams run into when enabling FIPS 140-3, including: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;WiFi SSID should be 16 characters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;32-bit crypto library versions must be removed, if present&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Full-disk encryption requires PBKDF2
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sudo cryptsetup –pbkdf=pbkdf2 luksAddKey &amp;lt;partition&amp;gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some applications might not expect disallowed operations to fail – we will endeavor to provide fixes where possible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’d like to raise a bug/issue with FIPS compliance on Ubuntu, you can do it on Launchpad. &lt;a href="https://bugs.launchpad.net/bugs/bugtrackers/openssl-rt"&gt;Here is an example of OpenSSL bugs&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Summary &lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We hope this blog has been useful for you to learn more about FIPS 140-3 on Ubuntu. You can&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/pro/subscribe"&gt; easily get FIPS 140-3 compliance with an Ubuntu Pro subscription, which is &lt;/a&gt;free for personal use and offers a&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/pro/subscribe"&gt; free trial&lt;/a&gt; for enterprise-focused projects. Additionally, an &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/pro"&gt;Ubuntu Pro subscription&lt;/a&gt; is not limited to only FIPS 140-3: the subscription also includes access to our hardening automation tools such as &lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/security/compliance/usg/"&gt;Ubuntu Security Guide&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/security/esm"&gt;expanded security maintenance&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/landscape"&gt;Ubuntu fleet management&lt;/a&gt;, and more. And if you’re looking for assistance with more complex enterprise use cases, you can simply &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/security/fips#get-in-touch"&gt;contact us&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;More reading &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/security/fips"&gt;Learn more about FIPS on Ubuntu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/security/"&gt;Ubuntu security documentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/engage/security-compliance-US-public-sector-FIPS-DISASTIG"&gt;Ubuntu Compliance Guide for the US Public Sector&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/security/security-standards"&gt;All security standards offered on Ubuntu &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Case Study: &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/case-study/lucid-aws-fedramp-compliance-case-study"&gt;How Lucid Software became FedRAMP compliant in less than 6 months&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Henry Coggill (Henry Coggill)</author><category>CMMC</category><category>DISA STIG</category><category>FedRAMP</category><category>FIPS</category><category>FIPS certification</category><category>Hardening</category><category>Ubuntu Pro</category><pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 18:23:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A CISO’s preview of open source and cybersecurity trends in 2026 and beyond</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/a-cisos-preview-of-open-source-and-cybersecurity-trends-in-2026-and-beyond</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Where is open source going next? What’s in store for open source in the coming years, particularly in relation to security? Here’s a CISO&amp;#8217;s reflection on the state of open source, and the trends that you can expect to have an impact going into 2026. &lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;Open source has come a long way. Recently I was watching a &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lt9TAQLT0PM&amp;amp;t=31s"&gt;keynote address by our founder, Mark Shuttleworth&lt;/a&gt;, in which he discussed his vision for Ubuntu to provide quality support and security maintenance across the broad open source ecosystem, and it made me reflect on how far the open source software (OSS) community has come. Indeed, when looking at today’s interoperable open source landscape, the fragmented, disconnected landscape of the past seems like another planet. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But where is open source going next? What’s in store for open source in the coming years, particularly in relation to security? Here’s my reflection on the state of open source, and the trends that I expect to have an impact going into 2026. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;So, what is the state of open source in 2025?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open source has become a ubiquitous part of software development – just look at the numbers. The average app today contains three times as many open source files as it did just four years ago, to the point where &lt;a href="https://www.blackduck.com/resources/analyst-reports/open-source-security-risk-analysis.html"&gt;97% of all applications contain OSS&lt;/a&gt;. At the same time, research commissioned by Canonical and IDC revealed that seven out of ten organizations &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/engage/2025-state-of-software-supply-chain"&gt;consider open source to be “extremely important”&lt;/a&gt; for running their mission-critical workloads. In fact, a &lt;a href="https://www.hbs.edu/faculty/Pages/item.aspx?num=65230#:~:text=We%20find%20that%20firms%20would%20need%20to,created%20by%20only%205%25%20of%20OSS%20developers."&gt;Harvard study&lt;/a&gt; found that if OSS didn’t exist, the global expenditure on software would be 3.5 times higher. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Put simply, the modern software landscape and market depends upon open source. Open source is popular because it is transformative for businesses, blending cost-effectiveness with access to sophisticated software. For instance, one company &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/engage/oneuptime-cost-savings-case-study?_gl=1*16vyo7l*_gcl_au*OTAwNzM2NjA0LjE3Mzk5Njk3NjU."&gt;reduced their cloud total cost of ownership (TCO) by 76%&lt;/a&gt; – saving approximately $370,000 – simply by transitioning to open source cloud infrastructure from Canonical. Previously unthinkable deployments, such as carrier-grade private 5G mobile networks, are now entirely achievable with open source tools, as &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/blog/telco-bringing-automation-to-open-source-5g-software-at-ubuntu-summit-2024"&gt;we demonstrated last year in the Netherlands&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s astonishing to think that just 20 years ago, most software companies explicitly forbid the use of &lt;strong&gt;any&lt;/strong&gt; OSS in their contracts and terms of service. Open standards and interoperability – now synonymous with open source – were far from mainstream, and as a result, companies were forced into an uncomfortable decision: use the one expensive product that works, or spend months building and integrating everything from scratch. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s a lot of change in just 20 years: an entire ecosystem turned on its head. That’s why I think it’s important to pay critical attention to what’s going around us, to spot trends that could be just as revolutionary (or disastrous), and work around them so that we can keep growing in the next 20 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that I’ve covered the current state of play, let’s dive into the potential tech revolutions – or challenges – in-waiting. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Future open source cybersecurity trends and their impact on cybersecurity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Open source adoption will continue its strong rise&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The decision to move away from the constraints of proprietary systems is grounded in promise: as &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/engage/2025-state-of-software-supply-chain"&gt;research by Canonical and IDC shows&lt;/a&gt;, businesses everywhere are using open source to keep down costs, fully own their infrastructure, and open up their systems to innovation. Ensuring that this promise is reflected in reality requires a proactive, forward-thinking approach. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your ability to adopt and adapt to the latest innovations in open source software will be vital. Two things are needed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A clear plan for adopting open source&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A way to manage this open source software supply chain post-adoption&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without a clear plan, you don’t know where you’re going; and without a management system, you’ll be recreating the difficult, fragmented environment open source was 20 years ago. However, I believe that the ever wider adoption of open source will lead to interoperability and simplified supply chains becoming the norm in the software landscape – essentially, that open source software will reshape the software landscape in line with its values. People want open source software that’s quick to install, easy to learn and use, and effortless to deploy and manage. If you’re looking for a place to begin exploring how you can approach adopting open source into your project or organization, I highly recommend visiting &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/open-source-adoption"&gt;our new dedicated webpage to helping you do exactly that.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;A new age of digital sovereignty&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tumultuous geopolitical and cyberthreat landscape of 2025 has sparked a new movement towards independence and ownership in mainstream circles. Long story short, companies don’t want to be left in the cold and dark if something happens with their overseas software or services provider – with the appeal of open source software being the control and freedom it offers to users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most notably, we’ve seen a major increase in interest, from businesses and governments, in open source, and repatriated products and infrastructure. For example, communal, municipal, and government authorities in nations like Germany and Denmark have expressed strong interest in moving away from proprietary systems in favour of open source alternatives. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This doesn’t mean proprietary tools will vanish. But it does mean that the pressure will increase on software providers to give peace of mind to end users and consumers that whatever system they use will remain online and functioning – even if new terms of service, sanctions, politics, or laws present unforeseen hurdles. Product features will still be important, but things like documentation, interoperability, system-agnostic design, training for users and system admins, and clear handover processes will be a new ‘normal’ in software offerings. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Organizations must balance complexity with visibility&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The developer landscape in 2025 has no shortage of tools, libraries, and solutions. If you want to build an app or service, you could build it from scratch, get portions of the solution from open source, or use already-built solutions. The challenge today is creating systems that give you a full view of these tools, and which allow them to be used securely and sustainably in the long term, without major costs. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Security is hard. There is no one-size-fits-all solution, which introduces the challenge of complexity. Developers have a lot of shiny toys to choose from, and keeping them all securely managed within a usable, minimally complex environment will be a real challenge. Indeed, securing your ever-growing stack won’t be easy. All this new tech doesn’t just mean maximized performance and efficiency: it also means a bigger attack surface and new attack vectors born of the intricate interdependencies between systems. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is made harder by wider organizational  habits. Canonical and IDC’s research shows that in general, organizations prize stability over constant updates: over 50% do not automatically upgrade to the newest versions of software when available. Instead, they wait until new features are needed or the program of free updates stops. They also draw these updates from various places: 57% draw from upstream source repositories, such as Github or Gitlab, and 51% draw from ecosystem packages, like pip or npm. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This approach presents clear problems: if you draw packages from multiple different sources and only apply them when you’re forced to update, it leads to more manual work and less certainty that you’re meeting increasingly strict cybersecurity standards in today’s market. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Organizations still have some work to do in order to meet the challenge of complexity. Our research with IDC shows that 70% of organizations mandate vulnerability patching within 24 hours of identification for “high” and “critical” container vulnerabilities – however, just 41% of respondents are “very confident” or “completely confident” in their organization’s ability to execute this policy. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember that innovation isn’t just driven by “the good guys”: bad actors are also working to develop new attack methods and techniques, as AI becomes increasingly powerful and AI tools become more connected and widespread.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;… especially as we enter the post vibe-coding era&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve all heard about and read about vibe coding, which is when a software engineer uses AI to generate and debug code. The hype wave of AI has led to fast adoption of generative AI tools as  incredible productivity magnifiers. While the allure of faster go-to-market times and improved cost-effectiveness is undeniable, the widespread adoption of AI tools in primary codebases, especially in environments with busy developers stretching across multiple projects, is creating significant security issues. The rapid, often less scrutinized generation of code through these tools can introduce vulnerabilities and amplify existing security challenges in complex software supply chains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the next few years, I predict the rise of a new  category of cyberincidents stemming from vibecoded feature additions. Organizations everywhere will need a clear policy on use of these tools, and robust checks and quality assurance processes to ensure that the vibecoded additions don’t ignore instructions, or hallucinate package names and inadvertently execute malicious code inside production environments. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Regulation is coming, and making things harder&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve seen a wave of regulation sweep across the US, EU, and UK in the last 4 years. As open source is adopted at the biggest levels of software, it will inherit the steep, strict demands that come with operating in a prestigious global playing field. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/engage/2025-state-of-software-supply-chain"&gt;Our research with IDC&lt;/a&gt; gives a clearer view into the challenges and frustrations that organizations are experiencing with regulations and compliance:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;37% of organizations are struggling to understand how regulations apply to specific systems, technologies, and software components.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;34% are battling with how to enforce compliance standards across software systems in a consistent manner.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;29% find it hard to source the resources and expertise needed to centrally manage software compliance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class="wp-block-buttons is-layout-flex wp-block-buttons-is-layout-flex"&gt;
&lt;div class="wp-block-button"&gt;&lt;a class="wp-block-button__link wp-element-button" href="https://ubuntu.com/engage/2025-state-of-software-supply-chain" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"&gt;Download the full IDC research report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As more regulation is rolled out and tightened up, these challenges will only become harder. Simply hitting the check box of compliance or hardening needed for enterprise eligibility isn’t the point any more – security teams have their work cut out in establishing a clear, transparent track record of your software’s trust lifecycle, and embed this transparency into your development practices. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means more work for people like me whose job it is to keep open source robust and trusted. But it’s undeniably the right path. After all, we don’t just want solutions that work – we want solutions that reflect, support, and continue the legacy of openness and contribution that allowed them to exist in the first place. And we want Canonical to be a leader in transparency and accountability, and institute practices that demonstrate the trustworthiness and compliance-readiness of our software and services. &lt;a href="https://trust.canonical.com/"&gt;We recently published our Trust Center&lt;/a&gt; – a web portal with all our certifications and compliance efforts – in order to demonstrate that when it comes to that hard work of regulations, we’re doing it right. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="wp-block-buttons is-layout-flex wp-block-buttons-is-layout-flex"&gt;
&lt;div class="wp-block-button"&gt;&lt;a class="wp-block-button__link wp-element-button" href="https://trust.canonical.com/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"&gt;Visit the Canonical Trust Center&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Wrapping up&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short: the future will be characterized by even more adoption of open source, increased regulation, a surge in AI-driven attack vectors, and a critical need for organizations to implement robust security policies and practices. Businesses must prioritize security without compromising stability, manage their open source supply chains effectively, and adapt to a landscape where transparency and compliance are paramount.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No matter the upcoming challenges to security in open source, I’m truly excited about this next phase.  The openness we spent decades building has created a truly remarkable landscape of interoperability, where you can combine and integrate almost any technology into a functioning model. I’ve seen first hand how open source has changed everything in the software landscape, and I know how much more revolutionary it could be in the coming years. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Black Duck, 2025 “Open Source Security and Risk Analysis 2025. Accessed at:  &lt;a href="https://www.blackduck.com/resources/analyst-reports/open-source-security-risk-analysis.html"&gt;https://www.blackduck.com/resources/analyst-reports/open-source-security-risk-analysis.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hoffmann, Manuel, Frank Nagle, and Yanuo Zhou. “The Value of Open Source Software.” Harvard Business School Working Paper, No. 24-038, January 2024.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/engage/2025-state-of-software-supply-chain"&gt;The state of software supply chains: Security challenges, opportunities and the path to resilience with open source software&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/blog/telco-bringing-automation-to-open-source-5g-software-at-ubuntu-summit-2024"&gt;https://ubuntu.com/blog/telco-bringing-automation-to-open-source-5g-software-at-ubuntu-summit-2024&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;More reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://canonical.com/blog/what-is-application-security-appsec"&gt;What is Application Security (AppSec)?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://canonical.com/blog/a-cisos-guide-to-application-security-best-practices"&gt;A CISO’s guide to Application Security best practices&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://canonical.com/blog/how-to-implement-zero-trust-into-third-party-idps"&gt;Extra Factor Authentication: how to create zero trust IAM with third-party IdPs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://canonical.com/blog/the-cyber-resilience-act-what-it-means-for-open-source"&gt;The Cyber Resilience Act: What it means for open source &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://canonical.com/open-source-adoption"&gt;Webpage: open source adoption&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/engage/iot-compliance-in-the-global-market-a-guide-for-iot-device-manufacturers"&gt;Whitepaper: a guide to global IoT compliance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/engage/vulnerability-management"&gt;Whitepaper: a guide to open source vulnerability management&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Stephanie Domas (Stephanie Domas)</author><category>Open source</category><pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Canonical Kubernetes officially included in Sylva 1.5</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/canonical-kubernetes-officially-included-in-sylva-1-5</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Sylva 1.5 becomes the first release to include Kubernetes 1.32, bringing the latest open source cloud-native capabilities to the European telecommunications industry. With the launch of Sylva 1.5, Canonical Kubernetes is now officially part of the project’s reference architecture. This follows its earlier availability as a technology preview in Sylva 1.4. What is the Sylva [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;Sylva 1.5 becomes the first release to include Kubernetes 1.32, bringing the latest open source cloud-native capabilities to the European telecommunications industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the launch of Sylva 1.5, &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/kubernetes"&gt;Canonical Kubernetes&lt;/a&gt; is now officially part of the project’s reference architecture. This follows its earlier availability as a technology preview in Sylva 1.4.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;What is the Sylva project?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://sylvaproject.org/"&gt;Sylva&lt;/a&gt; project is backed by Europe’s largest telecom operators and vendors, including Nokia and Ericsson, and is designed to deliver an open, telco-friendly cloud-native framework. By focusing on interoperability, performance, and automation, Sylva addresses the unique requirements of telecommunications providers building Kubernetes telco platforms for their IT, 5G core, O-RAN, and edge services. Canonical is thrilled to be included as part of the Sylva project, supporting the important work of creating an open source cloud-native reference architecture capable of hosting the mission-critical workloads of the telco industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Canonical’s contribution to the Kubernetes telco ecosystem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical Kubernetes brings unique advantages to Sylva’s mission of reducing fragmentation and simplifying operations across telecom networks. One of its defining features is up to 12 years of long-term support (LTS). For operators running critical workloads, this ensures stability, ongoing security updates, and compliance with industry standards over a much longer lifecycle than other Kubernetes distributions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical Kubernetes also provides the flexibility needed for large-scale Kubernetes telco deployments, from core networks to the far edge. Operators benefit from a distribution designed to be both lightweight and maintained with security in mind, while remaining capable of handling advanced workloads such as 5G core, O-RAN, and AI-driven services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="wp-block-quote"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guillaume Nevicato, Sylva Technical Steering Committee co-chair and Orange Telco Cloud Product Manager, recognized the importance of this contribution:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;cite&gt;Canonical is a major open-source player that has achieved the integration of their Canonical Kubernetes distribution into Sylva. They fully embrace Sylva’s full-stack automation, including cluster lifecycle management, storage, networking, observability, GreenDashboard, and security enhancements. This represents a significant step forward in Sylva’s adoption.&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Accelerating the validation of Kubernetes telco workloads&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A critical part of Sylva’s role is validating network functions against its reference framework, ensuring that cloud-native network functions (CNFs) and virtualized network functions (VNFs) perform reliably across any Sylva-compliant infrastructure. Following its technical preview in the previous Sylva release, Canonical Kubernetes is now included with 1.32 LTS in Sylva 1.5. This allows it to enter the validation process with the Sylva Validation Workgroup, covering key telecom workloads such as 5G Core, O-RAN, and distributed edge services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For operators, this means they can deploy Kubernetes telco workloads with confidence, knowing that interoperability and performance have already been tested. Vendors also benefit, since a single certification process ensures compatibility across multiple Sylva-aligned platforms, reducing time to market for new services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Looking ahead: future opportunities for integration&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical is now exploring how its broader infrastructure portfolio, including technologies like &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/openstack"&gt;Canonical OpenStack,&lt;/a&gt; a featureful, highly customizable cloud, and &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/maas"&gt;MAAS&lt;/a&gt;, bare-metal server automation software, could complement Sylva’s approach in the future. These solutions could help create a more unified environment for both virtualized and cloud-native network functions, enhancing the flexibility of Kubernetes telco deployments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Sylva evolves, Canonical will continue engaging with operators, vendors, and the wider community to identify opportunities where its open source software can add value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Building the future of Kubernetes in telco&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inclusion of Canonical Kubernetes in Sylva represents a milestone in the adoption of open source telco cloud infrastructure. Operators now have access to a validated, commercially supported Kubernetes telco distribution that combines long-term stability, security, and interoperability with the innovation of cloud-native technologies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Kubernetes at the foundation, operators can accelerate the rollout of next-generation network functions and services, while benefiting from the reliability and flexibility that only open-source collaboration can deliver.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Next steps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you building your telco cloud strategy? Learn how Canonical Kubernetes can give you a stable, validated, and open foundation for 5G, O-RAN, and edge workloads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Explore &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/solutions/telco"&gt;Canonical telco solutions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find out how to &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/solutions/telco/5g-core"&gt;Transform your 5G infrastructure with Canonical&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn how &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/case-study/nova-telecommunications"&gt;Nova Telecommunications is building its next-gen telco cloud with Canonical&lt;/a&gt; in the case study&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read our in-depth white paper on how to &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/engage/kubernetes-for-telco-performance"&gt;unlock the full potential of Kubernetes for telco performance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://canonical.com/solutions/telco#get-in-touch"&gt;Get in touch with Canonical’s telco team&lt;/a&gt; to discuss how we can help design and support your Kubernetes telco deployments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Benjamin Ryzman (Benjamin Ryzman)</author><category>5g</category><category>5G core network</category><category>canonical kubernetes</category><category>Sylva</category><category>Telco</category><pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 17:37:05 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Canonical expands total coverage for Ubuntu LTS releases to 15 years with Legacy add-on</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/canonical-expands-total-coverage-for-ubuntu-lts-releases-to-15-years-with-legacy-add-on</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu Pro now supports LTS releases for up to 15 years through the Legacy add-on. More security, more stability, and greater control over upgrade timelines for enterprises.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Expansion ensures business continuity without forcing major upgrades&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, Canonical announced the expansion of the Legacy add-on for Ubuntu Pro, extending total coverage for Ubuntu LTS releases to 15 years. Starting with Ubuntu 14.04 LTS (Trusty Tahr), this extension brings the full benefits of Ubuntu Pro – including continuous security patching, compliance tooling and support for your OS – to long-lived production systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In highly regulated or hardware-dependent industries, upgrades threaten to disrupt tightly controlled security and compliance. For many organizations, maintaining production systems for more than a decade is complex, but remains a more sensible option than a full upgrade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s why, in 2024, we first &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/blog/canonical-expands-long-term-support-to-12-years-starting-with-ubuntu-14-04-lts"&gt;introduced the Legacy add-on&lt;/a&gt; for Ubuntu Pro, starting with Ubuntu 14.04 LTS (Trusty Tahr). The Legacy add-on increased the total maintenance window for Ubuntu LTS releases to 12 years: five years of standard security maintenance, five years of Expanded Security Maintenance (ESM), and two years of additional coverage with the Legacy add-on – with optional support throughout. Due to the positive reception and growing interest in longer lifecycle coverage, we’re excited to now extend the Legacy add-on to 5 years, bringing a 15-year security maintenance and support window to Ubuntu LTS releases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;A 15-year lifecycle for stability&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout this 15-year window, Ubuntu Pro provides continuous security maintenance across the entire Ubuntu base, kernel, and key open source components. Canonical’s security team actively scans, triages, and backports critical, high, and select medium CVEs to all maintained LTS releases, ensuring security without forcing disruptive major upgrades that break compatibility or require re-certification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Break/fix support remains an optional add-on. When production issues arise, you can get access to our Support team through this service and troubleshoot with experts who contribute to Ubuntu every day, who’ve seen similar problems before and know how to resolve them quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scope of the Legacy add-on itself is unchanged, but the commitment is longer, giving users additional years to manage transition timelines and maintain compliance. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This updated coverage applies from Ubuntu 14.04 LTS onward. With this extension, Ubuntu 14.04 LTS is now supported until April 2029, a full 15 years after its debut.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="511" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1071px) 1071px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1071/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F75eb%2Fimage.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F75eb%2Fimage.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F75eb%2Fimage.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F75eb%2Fimage.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F75eb%2Fimage.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F75eb%2Fimage.png 1920w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1071/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F75eb%2Fimage.png 1071w" width="1071"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By committing to a 15-year lifecycle, Canonical gives users:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Realistic timelines for planning and executing major migrations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Continuous security and compliance coverage for long-lived systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flexibility to modernize infrastructure strategically rather than reactively&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Infrastructure is complicated, and upgrades carry real costs and risks. This expansion acknowledges those realities and gives you the support duration your deployments actually require.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;A simple path to extended coverage&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Current Ubuntu Pro subscriptions will continue uninterrupted. No re-enrollment, no reinstallation, no surprise migration projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Legacy add-on is available after the first 10 years of coverage (standard security maintenance plus ESM, and optional break/bug fix support), priced at a 50% premium over standard Ubuntu Pro. This applies whether you’re approaching that milestone with 16.04 LTS or already using the Legacy add-on with 14.04 LTS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To activate coverage beyond ESM, &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/contact-us/form?product=pro"&gt;contact Canonical Sales&lt;/a&gt; or reach out to your account manager.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more information about the Legacy add-on, visit our &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/pro"&gt;Ubuntu Pro page&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn more:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/pro"&gt;Ubuntu Pro &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/support"&gt;Canonical Support&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://canonical.com/case-study/sbi-bits"&gt;Read how SBI BITS ensures business continuity with Canonical’s support&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Canonical (Canonical)</author><category>LTS</category><category>Support</category><category>Ubuntu Pro</category><pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 09:11:04 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>