<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	 xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" >

<channel>
	<title>Kotlin : A concise multiplatform language developed by JetBrains | The JetBrains Blog</title>
	<atom:link href="https://blog.jetbrains.com/kotlin/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://blog.jetbrains.com</link>
	<description>Developer Tools for Professionals and Teams</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 09:34:03 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	

<image>
	<url>https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/cropped-mstile-310x310-1-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Kotlin : A concise multiplatform language developed by JetBrains | The JetBrains Blog</title>
	<link>https://blog.jetbrains.com</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Helping Decision‑Makers Say Yes to Kotlin</title>
		<link>https://blog.jetbrains.com/kotlin/2025/11/helping-decision-makers-say-yes-to-kotlin/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alyona Chernyaeva]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 12:11:19 +0000</pubDate>
		<featuredImage>https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Blog-Featured-1280x720-3.png</featuredImage>		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://blog.jetbrains.com/?post_type=kotlin&#038;p=655947</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Guest post by Urs Peter, Senior Software Engineer and JetBrains-certified Kotlin Trainer. For readers who’d like a more structured way to build Kotlin skills, Urs also leads the&#160;Kotlin Upskill Program at Xebia Academy. This is the fourth post in The Ultimate Guide to Successfully Adopting Kotlin in a Java-Dominated Environment, a series that follows how [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><em>Guest post by <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/urs-peter-70a2882/" data-type="link" data-id="https://bit.ly/urs-peter-linked-in" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Urs Peter</a>, Senior Software Engineer and JetBrains-certified Kotlin Trainer. For readers who’d like a more structured way to build Kotlin skills, Urs also leads the&nbsp;</em><a href="https://academy.xebia.com/upskilling/kotlin-academy/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><em>Kotlin Upskill Program</em></a><em> at Xebia Academy.</em></p>



<p><em>This is the fourth post in </em><strong><em>The Ultimate Guide to Successfully Adopting Kotlin in a Java-Dominated Environment</em></strong><em>, a series that follows how Kotlin adoption grows among real teams, from a single developer’s curiosity to company-wide transformation.</em></p>



<p><strong>All parts in the series:</strong></p>



<ol>
<li><a href="https://blog.jetbrains.com/kotlin/2025/10/getting-started-with-kotlin-for-java-developers/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Getting Started With Kotlin for Java Developers</a></li>



<li><a href="https://blog.jetbrains.com/kotlin/2025/10/evaluating-kotlin-in-real-projects/" data-type="link" data-id="https://blog.jetbrains.com/kotlin/2025/10/evaluating-kotlin-in-real-projects/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Evaluating Kotlin in Real Projects</a></li>



<li><a href="https://blog.jetbrains.com/kotlin/2025/11/growing-kotlin-adoption-in-your-company/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Growing Kotlin Adoption in Your Company</a></li>
</ol>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Persuading Management: Building the Business Case for Kotlin</strong></h2>



<p>Once you have achieved a critical mass of Kotlin supporters, presenting a compelling business case to management requires moving beyond code demonstrations to hard data and strategic considerations.</p>



<p><strong>Market momentum and industry validation</strong></p>



<p>Kotlin has demonstrated remarkable growth, with 2.5 million developers worldwide now using the language. This represents sustained adoption since Google&#8217;s pivotal 2017 announcement declaring Kotlin the official language for Android development, followed by Spring Boot&#8217;s embrace of Kotlin as a first-class citizen.</p>



<p>Source: <a href="https://youtu.be/F5NaqGF9oT4" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Keynote KotlinConf 2025</a></p>



<p>The momentum has accelerated significantly. Spring Boot, which commands approximately 90% of the backend market share, formalized a strategic partnership with JetBrains in 2025 – a clear signal of Kotlin&#8217;s enterprise viability and long-term trajectory.</p>



<p><strong>Framing the strategic decision</strong></p>



<p>While these adoption metrics demonstrate Kotlin&#8217;s market validation, management decisions require a comprehensive cost-benefit analysis. Technology adoption at scale involves significant investments in training, tooling, and potential migration efforts. The key is presenting both the tangible benefits and realistic implementation costs, allowing leadership to make an informed strategic decision rather than a purely technical one.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>The business gains unlocked by embracing Kotlin</strong></h3>



<p>These are the business gains when choosing Kotlin:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-table"><table><tbody><tr><td><strong>Advantage</strong></td><td><strong>Details</strong></td><td><strong>Business/Team impact</strong></td></tr><tr><td><strong>~30% less code. Better code clarity.</strong></td><td>~30% less to write, read, fix, and maintain.</td><td>➜ Increased productivity.<br>➜ Improved maintainability.</td></tr><tr><td><strong>25% fewer bugs thanks to safety features</strong></td><td>Kotlin reduces defects out of the box – no extra skills required – through features like null safety, safe APIs, and sensible defaults.</td><td>➜ Better quality – happier customers and developers.<br>➜ More time for new features.<br>➜ Faster time-to-market.</td></tr><tr><td><strong>Invest in just one new language: Kotlin</strong></td><td>Keep existing frameworks (e.g. SpringBoot, Micronaut, Quarkus).</td><td>➜ Framework knowledge is preserved.</td></tr><tr><td><strong>Better choice for AI</strong></td><td>Kotlin is more AI-friendly due to noise reduction, clarity, fluency, and more, which aligns with how LLMs process code.</td><td>➜ Better productivity with AI, which is increasingly influencing coding.</td></tr><tr><td><strong>Fully interoperable with Java</strong></td><td>Kotlin is fully interoperable with Java; no rewrite of libraries required.</td><td>➜ Investments based on Java are preserved.</td></tr><tr><td><strong>Well supported</strong></td><td>Backed by strong players: JetBrains, Google, and Meta.</td><td>➜ Future-proof choice.</td></tr><tr><td><strong>Gradual adoption</strong></td><td>Kotlin supports incremental migration paths.</td><td>➜ No “Big Bang” needed.</td></tr><tr><td><strong>Increase in developer happiness</strong></td><td>In surveys and studies, Kotlin developers consistently report better developer experience and higher job satisfaction.</td><td>➜ Attract new developers.<br>➜ Better retention 😃😃😃.</td></tr><tr><td><strong>Faster audit, safer compliance</strong></td><td>Kotlin’s type safety, immutability, and clear data structures make systems easier to trace, validate, and certify. These qualities support transparent and reliable software processes across regulated domains. For a real-world example, see <a href="https://yurigeronimus.medium.com/kotlin-in-payment-gateways-and-fintech-a-strategic-fit-for-2026-architectures-f049a01059f9" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>Kotlin in Payment Gateways and Fintech: A Strategic Fit for 2026 Architectures</em></a>.</td><td>➜ Easier internal and external audits.&nbsp;&nbsp;<br>➜ Lower compliance effort and risk.&nbsp;<br>➜ Greater organizational transparency.</td></tr></tbody></table></figure>



<p><strong>Some words on developer happiness</strong></p>



<p>Looking at my career, I was greatly rewarded for letting go of my attachment to the seemingly <em>safe</em> career choice of Java. Daily, I’m empowered with a language that is a joy to work with and helps me express what I want to achieve in the best possible way, concisely, safely, and productively.&nbsp;</p>



<p>It’s a fact that, personally, I&#8217;ve become a happier developer (human ;-)?) using Kotlin. Though this is subjective, developer satisfaction data tells the same unmistakable story:</p>



<p><strong>Backend developers who migrate from Java to Kotlin report dramatically higher happiness levels across every major industry survey.</strong><a href="https://stackoverflow.blog/2025/01/01/developers-want-more-more-more-the-2024-results-from-stack-overflow-s-annual-developer-survey/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><strong>&nbsp;</strong></a></p>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://stackoverflow.blog/2025/01/01/developers-want-more-more-more-the-2024-results-from-stack-overflow-s-annual-developer-survey/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Stack Overflow&#8217;s Developer Survey</a> data shows Kotlin consistently ranking among the top five most loved languages at ~63% satisfaction, significantly outpacing Java&#8217;s ~54% rating.</li>



<li>The <a href="http://mercedes-benz.io" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mercedes-Benz.io</a> backend team documented &#8220;significantly more concise code than Java, reducing boilerplate and improving readability&#8221; while achieving measurable productivity gains in their microservices architecture.</li>



<li><a href="https://tylerrussell.dev/2025/01/10/my-thoughts-on-kotlin-perspectives-after-4-years/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Tyler Russell</a>, a backend developer with 15 years of Java experience, reports after four years with Kotlin: &#8220;I really like Kotlin&#8230; it feels like it enables productivity significantly more than it hinders it&#8221;, and never wants to return to Java.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Corporate Kotlin to Java backend migrations demonstrate that these happiness improvements scale effectively across enterprise environments.</strong><a href="https://medium.com/insiden26/5-reasons-why-n26-is-moving-to-kotlin-f920b184ab58" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><strong>&nbsp;</strong></a></p>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/insiden26/5-reasons-why-n26-is-moving-to-kotlin-f920b184ab58" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">N26&#8217;s backend engineering team converted 60% of their microservices to Kotlin within two years, reporting enhanced developer satisfaction and reduced production issues</a>.</li>



<li><a href="https://medium.com/ing-blog/kotlin-adoption-inside-ing-5-years-later-df6421b14dc4" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">ING&#8217;s five-year backend adoption journey shows sustained organic growth, with 8% of their 20,000+ technical staff repositories now using Kotlin, demonstrating that developers voluntarily choose Kotlin when given the option</a>.</li>
</ul>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>The cost / return on investment of embracing Kotlin:</strong></h3>



<p>These are the investments required for choosing Kotlin.&nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-table"><table><tbody><tr><td><strong>Investment&nbsp;</strong></td><td><strong>Description</strong></td><td><strong>Expected Return / Impact</strong></td></tr><tr><td><strong>Developer training</strong></td><td>Training sessions, workshops, and onboarding materials.</td><td>➜ Experienced developers new to Kotlin are productive in 2–3 weeks.<br>➜ ROI in ~1–4 months.</td></tr><tr><td><strong>Codebase migration (if applicable)</strong></td><td>A gradual rewrite or a mixed Kotlin/Java code setup strategy is required.</td><td>➜ No need for big bang rewrite<br>➜ Maintains delivery speed.</td></tr><tr><td><strong>Knowledge sharing</strong></td><td>Internal Kotlin champions, brown bag sessions, shared repos with examples.</td><td>➜ Faster team-wide adoption.<br>➜ Reuse of best practices.</td></tr><tr><td><strong>Hiring / upskilling</strong></td><td>Hire Kotlin-experienced devs or upskill existing Java devs.</td><td>➜ Higher retention.<br>➜ Broader talent pool.</td></tr></tbody></table></figure>



<p>One of the most common concerns when considering Kotlin adoption is the perceived shortage of experienced Kotlin developers. But rather than a roadblock, this can be a <strong>strategic advantage</strong>:</p>



<ul>
<li><strong>✅ Fast upskilling for Java developers<br></strong>Kotlin is designed to be intuitive for Java developers. With the right guidance, most can become productive in just <strong>2–3 weeks</strong>.</li>



<li><strong>✅ Kotlin attracts high-quality developers<br></strong>Those who actively pursue Kotlin are often <strong>curious, modern, and quality-driven</strong> – traits you want in your engineering team.</li>



<li><strong>✅ Kotlin enhances your company image<br></strong>Adopting Kotlin signals that you embrace <strong>modern, forward-looking technology</strong>, which helps attract top-tier talent.</li>



<li><strong>✅ Kotlin boosts developer happiness and retention</strong></li>
</ul>



<p>Kotlin developers consistently report <strong>higher job satisfaction</strong>, making it easier to retain engaged and motivated team members.</p>



<p>In short: Kotlin isn’t just a smart tech choice – it’s a <strong>strategic people decision</strong>.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Up next in the series</h3>



<p>We shift focus from convincing developers to persuading decision-makers. The next post shows how to build a compelling business case for Kotlin adoption, grounded in real data and measurable outcomes. You’ll learn how to translate developer wins into management arguments, link productivity gains to cost savings, and demonstrate why Kotlin is more than a technical upgrade&nbsp;<strong>–</strong>&nbsp;it’s a strategic move for teams and companies alike.</p>


    <div class="about-author ">
        <div class="about-author__box">
            <div class="row">
                                                            <div class="about-author__box-img">
                            <img style="width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;" decoding="async" src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/a3f7-400o400o1-QYUavRYyARnAVJLCpM1m8M.webp" alt="" loading="lazy">
                        </div>
                                        <div class="about-author__box-text">
                                                    <h4>Urs Peter</h4>
                                                <p>Urs is a seasoned software engineer, solution architect, conference speaker, and trainer with over 20 years of experience in building resilient, scalable, and mission-critical systems, mostly involving Kotlin and Scala.</p>
<p>Besides his job as a consultant, he is also a passionate trainer and author of a great variety of courses ranging from language courses for Kotlin and Scala to architectural trainings such as Microservices and Event-Driven Architectures.</p>
<p>As a people person by nature, he loves to share knowledge and inspire and get inspired by peers on meetups and conferences. Urs is a JetBrains certified Kotlin trainer.</p>
                    </div>
                            </div>
        </div>
    </div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Google Summer of Code 2025: What Our Contributors Built</title>
		<link>https://blog.jetbrains.com/kotlin/2025/11/google-summer-of-code-2025/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ksenia Shneyveys]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 20:49:21 +0000</pubDate>
		<featuredImage>https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Blog-Featured-1280x720-2.png</featuredImage>		<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[news]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gsoc]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[open-source]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://blog.jetbrains.com/?post_type=kotlin&#038;p=658902</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Congrats to all GSoC 2025 contributors and mentors! This year’s projects have made a real impact on the Kotlin ecosystem and the contributions are already being integrated, used, and appreciated. Thank you all for your hard work! Join our #gsoc channel on Slack Let’s take a closer look at this year’s projects: IntelliJ Platform Gradle [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Congrats to all GSoC 2025 contributors and mentors! This year’s projects have made a real impact on the Kotlin ecosystem and the contributions are already being integrated, used, and appreciated. Thank you all for your hard work!</p>



<p align="center"><a class="ek-link jb-download-button" title="Join our #gsoc channel on Slack" href="https://slack-chats.kotlinlang.org/c/gsoc" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Join our #gsoc channel on Slack</a></p>



<p>Let’s take a closer look at this year’s projects:</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">IntelliJ Platform Gradle Plugin – Gradle Reporting and Parallel Verifications</h2>


    <div class="blockquote">
                    <blockquote><p>“GSoC was the perfect opportunity to give back to the tools I use daily and move from user to contributor because I&#8217;d already been building IntelliJ plugins myself.”</p></blockquote>
            <div class="blockquote__author">
                                    <img style="width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;" decoding="async" class="blockquote__author-img" src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Profile-copy.jpeg" alt="Victoria Alajemba">
                                <div class="blockquote__author-info">
                                            <strong class="blockquote__author-title">Victoria Chuks Alajemba</strong>
                                                        </div>
            </div>
            </div>



<p><a href="https://dev.to/victoria_chuks_7e772e1688/gsoc-2025-kotlin-foundation-final-report-3p4c" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Project page</strong></a></p>



<p><strong>Mentor</strong>: Jakub Chrzanowski (JetBrains)</p>



<p>For Victoria Alajemba, a Software Engineer from Nigeria studying in Paris, GSoC was a bridge between learning and impact. Working on the IntelliJ Platform Gradle Plugin, she integrated Gradle’s Problems API and Reporting API, creating richer, standardized reports and exploring parallel verification for faster builds. Guided by Jakub Chrzanowski from JetBrains, she strengthened key workflows used by thousands of plugin developers.</p>



<p><a href="https://kotlinfoundation.org/news/gsoc-2025-intellij-gradle-plugin/" data-type="link" data-id="https://kotlinfoundation.org/news/gsoc-2025-intellij-gradle-plugin/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Learn more about Victoria’s project →</a></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Improving Configuration Cache in Key Gradle Plugins</h2>


    <div class="blockquote">
                    <blockquote><p>“Working with my mentors was an amazing experience. They provided invaluable guidance, from high-level architectural advice to detailed feedback on pull requests.”</p></blockquote>
            <div class="blockquote__author">
                                    <img style="width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;" decoding="async" class="blockquote__author-img" src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/image-10.jpeg" alt="Nouran Atef">
                                <div class="blockquote__author-info">
                                            <strong class="blockquote__author-title">Nouran Atef</strong>
                                                        </div>
            </div>
            </div>



<p><a href="https://community.gradle.org/events/gsoc/2025/configuration-cache-and-lock-contention/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Project page</strong></a></p>



<p><strong>Mentors</strong>: Oleg Nenashev (ex-Gradle), Rafael Chaves (Gradle), Rodrigo Oliveira (Gradle)</p>



<p>Hailing from Cairo, Nouran Atef spent her summer making Gradle builds faster and more reliable. Her project tackled Configuration Cache compatibility across major community plugins, refactoring them to remove bottlenecks and enable smarter caching. She contributed fixes, documentation, and patterns now adopted across plugins, boosting performance for developers everywhere.</p>



<p><a href="https://kotlinfoundation.org/news/gsoc-2025-gradle-cache/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Read Nouran’s full story →</a></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Enhanced Kotlin Code Quality Reporting with Gradle Problem API: Integration with Detekt and Ktlint</h2>


    <div class="blockquote">
                    <blockquote><p>“Participating in GSoC opened my eyes to the open-source community. Collaboration, communication, and more Kotlin all helped me grow into a better, well-rounded engineer. To anyone considering GSoC, especially beginners, I would say to apply! It is very beginner friendly and you can acquire valuable skills that you would not easily gain elsewhere.”</p></blockquote>
            <div class="blockquote__author">
                                    <img style="width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;" decoding="async" class="blockquote__author-img" src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/IMG_3512.jpg" alt="Vanessa Johnson">
                                <div class="blockquote__author-info">
                                            <strong class="blockquote__author-title">Vanessa Johnson</strong>
                                                        </div>
            </div>
            </div>



<p><a href="https://community.gradle.org/events/gsoc/2025/kotlin-code-quality-with-problems-api/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Project page</strong></a></p>



<p><strong>Mentors</strong>: Donát Csikós and Reinhold Degenfellner (both from Gradle)</p>



<p>Based in New York City, Android Engineer Vanessa Johnson spent her summer improving how Kotlin developers experience code quality. Her project integrated the Gradle Problems API into popular tools like Detekt and Ktlint, unifying error reporting across consoles, IDEs, and HTML reports for cleaner, more actionable feedback.</p>



<p><a href="https://kotlinfoundation.org/news/gsoc-2025-kotlin-quality-reporting/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Read Vanessa’s full story →</a></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Support Android and iOS Targets in Kotlin Multiplatform for Gemini Using Vertex AI in Firebase</h2>


    <div class="blockquote">
                    <blockquote><p>“GSoC ultimately strengthened my passion for the developer experience and mobile infrastructure, inspiring me to keep building tools that make complex technologies more accessible.”</p></blockquote>
            <div class="blockquote__author">
                                    <img style="width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;" decoding="async" class="blockquote__author-img" src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/image-15.jpeg" alt="Sean Chin Jun Kai">
                                <div class="blockquote__author-info">
                                            <strong class="blockquote__author-title">Sean Chin Jun Kai</strong>
                                                        </div>
            </div>
            </div>



<p><a href="https://github.com/SeanChinJunKai/firebase-ai-kmp" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><strong>Project page</strong></a></p>



<p><strong>Mentor</strong>: Matt Dyor (Google)</p>



<p>As one of the first Firebase libraries with native Kotlin Multiplatform (KMP) support, Sean’s project bridges Android and iOS with a shared Gemini-powered Firebase AI layer. His modular SDK and Swift-Kotlin bridge simplify AI feature integration across platforms, answering one of the top community requests for Firebase. Mentored by Matt Dyor from Google, Sean’s work lays the foundation for future official KMP-compatible Firebase libraries.</p>



<p><a href="https://kotlinfoundation.org/news/gsoc-2025-gemini-vertex-firebase/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Explore Sean’s full project →</a></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Gradle Convention Plugin for Developing Jenkins Plugins</h2>


    <div class="blockquote">
                    <blockquote><p>“The moment that acceptance email landed in my inbox, I couldn’t stop smiling. Working with my mentors was one of the most rewarding parts of this journey. <br />
”</p></blockquote>
            <div class="blockquote__author">
                                    <img style="width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;" decoding="async" class="blockquote__author-img" src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/image-12.jpeg" alt="Aarav Mahajan">
                                <div class="blockquote__author-info">
                                            <strong class="blockquote__author-title">Aarav Mahajan</strong>
                                                        </div>
            </div>
            </div>



<p><a href="https://community.gradle.org/events/gsoc/2025/jenkins-plugins-toolchain/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Project page</strong></a></p>



<p><strong>Mentors</strong>: Oleg Nenashev (ex-Gradle), Rahul Somasunderam (Netflix), Steve Hill (Netflix)</p>



<p>For Aarav Mahajan, a computer engineering student from Punjab, India, it wasn’t just writing a Gradle plugin – it was about expanding what’s possible for Jenkins developers and modernizing plugin development for Gradle.</p>



<p>The Gradle Convention Plugin introduces a clean, Kotlin-first way to build, test, and publish Jenkins plugins, standardizing best practices, automating checks, and bringing long-requested Gradle parity to the community.</p>



<p><a href="https://kotlinfoundation.org/news/gsoc-2025-gradle-plugin-jenkins/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Read Aarav’s full story →</a></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Maven Central Publishing Plugin for Gradle (New APIs)</h2>


    <div class="blockquote">
                    <blockquote><p>“GSoC really broadened my perspective. It taught me what it takes to build, promote, and grow an open-source project, which is especially meaningful since becoming a maintainer is one of my long-term goals.”</p></blockquote>
            <div class="blockquote__author">
                                    <img style="width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;" decoding="async" class="blockquote__author-img" src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Yongjun.png" alt="Yongjun Hong">
                                <div class="blockquote__author-info">
                                            <strong class="blockquote__author-title">Yongjun Hong</strong>
                                                        </div>
            </div>
            </div>



<p><a href="https://community.gradle.org/events/gsoc/2025/maven-central-publishing-with-new-api/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Project page</a></p>



<p><strong>Mentor</strong>: Oleg Nenashev (ex-Gradle)</p>



<p>Yongjun Hong set out to make publishing to Maven Central easier. His new Gradle plugin brings modern Kotlin DSL support, automatic validation, and smart inheritance of shared metadata, turning a tedious, error-prone process into a smooth, consistent workflow. Mentored by Oleg Nenashev, Yongjun delivered a tool that not only simplifies multi-module publishing, but also improves build reliability and compliance – a small change that will save countless hours for open-source maintainers.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Build a Modern, Compiler-Integrated Kotlin Language Server</h2>


    <div class="blockquote">
                    <blockquote><p>“It was incredibly rewarding to see my work tested, reviewed, and used by others in the community.”</p></blockquote>
            <div class="blockquote__author">
                                    <img style="width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;" decoding="async" class="blockquote__author-img" src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/image-9.jpeg" alt="Aarav Mahajan">
                                <div class="blockquote__author-info">
                                            <strong class="blockquote__author-title">Hemram</strong>
                                                        </div>
            </div>
            </div>



<p><a href="https://github.com/h4-mm-3r/kotlin-lsp" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Project page</strong></a></p>



<p><strong>Mentors</strong>: Shauvik Roy Choudhary, Ryan U, Michael Noah, Claudia Babescu (all from Uber)</p>



<p>From picking up Kotlin from scratch to building a compiler-integrated Language Server with the new Analysis API, Hemram’s project expanded the boundaries of Kotlin tooling.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Working with mentors from Uber and the Kotlin Foundation, he delivered a modern, open foundation for editor integrations and future AI-assisted tools for the Kotlin Language Server Protocol.</p>



<p><a href="https://kotlinfoundation.org/news/gsoc-2025-kotlin-lps/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Read Hemram’s story →</a></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator aligncenter has-alpha-channel-opacity is-style-dots"/>



<p>Thank you to our contributors and mentors from the Kotlin Foundation member companies and other great partners supporting open-source – Google, Gradle, Uber, Netflix, and JetBrains – and to everyone who reviewed issues, gave feedback, and merged PRs.</p>



<p>If you are considering taking part in GSoC, check out the blogs from this year’s contributors – they’re full of insights on writing strong proposals and what the program can teach you. </p>



<p>To stay up to date on the next GSoC, join <a href="https://slack-chats.kotlinlang.org/c/gsoc" data-type="link" data-id="https://slack-chats.kotlinlang.org/c/gsoc" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">our #gsoc channel on Slack</a>.</p>



<p>If you’d like to go deeper, check out the linked contributor posts and repos above.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Let’s keep building great things together!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Building AI Agents in Kotlin – Part 1: A Minimal Coding Agent </title>
		<link>https://blog.jetbrains.com/ai/2025/11/building-ai-agents-in-kotlin-part-1-a-minimal-coding-agent/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Fatimazahra El Akkary]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 08:35:38 +0000</pubDate>
		<featuredImage>https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/JB-social-BlogFeatured-1280x720-1-4.png</featuredImage>		<product ><![CDATA[kotlin]]></product>
		<category><![CDATA[tutorials]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ai]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ai-agents]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://blog.jetbrains.com/?post_type=ai&#038;p=657070</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Building agents is weird. You&#8217;re not writing code that does things. You&#8217;re writing code that gives an LLM the ability to do things, and the LLM decides what to do. What is an agent? An agent is an LLM that calls your functions in a loop until it decides the task is complete. That shift [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Building agents is weird. You&#8217;re not writing code that does things. You&#8217;re writing code that gives an LLM the ability to do things, and the LLM decides what to do.</p>


<aside style="background: #f8f9fa;border-left: 4px solid #007bff;padding: 1rem 1.5rem;margin: 1.5rem 0;border-radius: 4px">
<p style="font-weight: 600;margin-bottom: 0.5rem;color: #333;font-size: 1.05rem">What is an agent?</p>
<p style="margin: 0;color: #555">An agent is an LLM that calls your functions in a loop until it decides the task is complete.</p>
</aside>


<p>That shift takes some getting used to. You give the agent the ability to read files, and it decides which files to read and when. You might expect it to start with the main file. Instead, it reads three test files first to understand the patterns. You didn&#8217;t tell it to do that. It just did.</p>



<p>So what abilities do you give it? Too many and it picks poorly. Too few and it can&#8217;t do the job. Finding that balance means trying things, observing what fails, and adjusting.</p>



<p><strong>In this blog series</strong>, we&#8217;ll explore AI agents by building a real coding agent together, starting with three basic tools and transforming the agent into a complete one over the course of the series. You&#8217;ll learn about how agents actually work, how to observe and debug their behavior, and the architectural decisions that matter. By the end, you&#8217;ll understand not just this agent, but how to build your own. All in Kotlin.</p>



<p>We&#8217;ll start simple by building an agent that can navigate a codebase and make targeted changes. We&#8217;ll&nbsp;use <a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/koog/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Koog</a>, an open-source framework from JetBrains that handles the execution loop: sending prompts, parsing tool calls, and executing them, repeating until done. The execution loop can get complex, but we&#8217;ll start with a basic one and focus on the more interesting question: what capabilities should your agent actually have?</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Building the agent piece by piece</strong></h2>



<p>Before we write anything, let&#8217;s think about what we actually want. An agent that can&#8230; do what exactly?</p>



<p>Fix bugs? Write features? Refactor old code?</p>



<p>We want it to do all of those things. But what does that actually mean? It means we need an agent that can navigate a codebase and make targeted changes.</p>



<p>It needs to be able to <strong>see</strong> what files are in a project, <strong>read</strong> those files, and <strong>edit</strong> them or create new ones – three capabilities that we&#8217;ll give it through three tools.</p>


<aside style="background: #f8f9fa;border-left: 4px solid #007bff;padding: 1rem 1.5rem;margin: 1.5rem 0;border-radius: 4px">
<p style="font-weight: 600;margin-bottom: 0.5rem;color: #333;font-size: 1.05rem">What are tools?</p>
<p style="margin: 0;color: #555">Tools are functions the LLM can call when needed. You decide which ones are present, and the LLM decides when to use them.</p>
</aside>


<p>These three tools are already built and bundled into <a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/koog/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Koog</a>. We&#8217;ll look at how each one works, and then connect them all to GPT-5-Codex. That will give us a complete agent that can explore a codebase, read files, and make changes.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Teaching it to see</strong></h3>



<p>First, we add this tool to give our agent a way to explore:</p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">tool(ListDirectoryTool(JVMFileSystemProvider.ReadOnly))</pre>



<p>Now it can look around to see what files exist. But here&#8217;s the thing: If you just dump a list of file paths at an agent, it doesn&#8217;t really help. The agent needs to understand the structure.</p>



<p>To make understanding the structure easier, the tool formats output intelligently. JVM projects have deep package structures. A typical path might be <code>src/main/kotlin/com/example/service/impl/UserServiceImpl.kt.</code> If the tool showed every intermediate directory, the output would be cluttered with single-child directories that add no information. </p>



<p>So when it finds a long chain of single directories, it collapses them:</p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="generic" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">/project/src/main/kotlin/Main.kt (&lt;0.1 KiB, 20 lines)</pre>



<p>When there are multiple files at the same level, it shows a tree:</p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">/project/src/main/kotlin/
  Main.kt (&lt;0.1 KiB, 20 lines)
  Utils.kt (&lt;0.1 KiB, 10 lines)</pre>



<p>Notice the file sizes and line counts are right there. Why show them?</p>



<p>Without them, you&#8217;ll run into a problem we hit.&nbsp; When we first built this, we didn&#8217;t include file sizes. The agent would explore the directory and see filenames, but have no idea about their size. So when it needed to understand a file, it would just read the entire thing.</p>



<p>Then we hit a real case: the agent tried to read<a href="https://github.com/pydata/xarray/blob/d998eac1e7acf04dbf6f81ebe51247c02d3adb5c/xarray/tests/test_dataset.py" target="_blank" rel="noopener"> a Python test file that was over 7,700 lines long</a>. The LLM&#8217;s context window filled up with just that one file. When the agent tried to continue working, it had lost track of other files it had read, what it was supposed to be doing, and what changes it needed to make. The single massive file had pushed everything else out of context.</p>



<p>That&#8217;s why line counts and file sizes are in the directory listing. Now, when the agent explores the codebase, it sees that <code>test_dataset.py</code> is 7,700 lines before trying to read it. It can decide to read just specific sections instead of the whole thing, or skip it entirely if it&#8217;s not relevant to the task.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Reading code</strong></h3>



<p>Next, the agent needs to read files:</p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">tool(ReadFileTool(JVMFileSystemProvider.ReadOnly))</pre>



<p>See <code>JVMFileSystemProvider.ReadOnly? </code>That’s because this tool doesn&#8217;t call <code>java.nio.file</code> APIs directly. It&#8217;s built against Koog&#8217;s <code>FileSystemProvider</code> interface.</p>



<p>Why? So you can write a tool once and use it anywhere. <code>ReadFileTool</code> just calls methods on the provider. It doesn&#8217;t care if that provider reads from your local disk, from files over SSH, or from cloud storage. If you pass it to a different provider, the tool works the same way. If you&#8217;re building your own file tools, you can implement <code>FileSystemProvider</code> for your storage backend and pass it to Koog&#8217;s file tools, and they’ll work.</p>



<p>We&#8217;re using <code>JVMFileSystemProvider.ReadOnly</code> here. Why is it <code>ReadOnly?</code> By separating read and write permissions at the provider level, you can compose agents with different permission levels. Need an agent that only explores and analyzes code? Give it tools that use <code>ReadOnly</code> providers, and you know for certain it can&#8217;t modify anything. For this agent, we&#8217;ll add modification capabilities next. <code>EditFileTool</code> will use <code>JVMFileSystemProvider.ReadWrite</code> instead. Clear separation means you control exactly what each agent can and can&#8217;t do.<br></p>



<p>The tool also supports line ranges:</p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">readFile("Main.kt", startLine = 45, endLine = 72)</pre>



<p>Remember those line counts in <code>ListDirectoryTool</code>? This is why. When the agent sees a file with thousands of lines in the directory listing, it knows to be more strategic about reading it. It might read the file in chunks, avoid rereading it multiple times, or extract specific sections. This helps prevent context exhaustion from large files like that 7,700-line Python test file example.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Modifying code</strong></h3>



<p>Now we give the agent the power to actually change things:</p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">tool(EditFileTool(JVMFileSystemProvider.ReadWrite))</pre>



<p><code>EditFileTool</code> does find-and-replace. Give it a file path, the text to find, and what to replace it with. Simple enough.</p>



<p>But here&#8217;s what&#8217;s interesting: Those three parameters can do different things, depending on what you pass.</p>



<p>Want to replace text? Specify the original text and the replacement:</p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">edit_file(
    path = "Main.kt", 
    original = "Hello World!", 
    replacement = "Hello Koog!"
)</pre>



<p>Want to delete something? Just make the replacement empty:</p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">edit_file(
    path = "Main.kt", 
    original = "Hello World!", 
    replacement = ""
)</pre>



<p>Want to create a whole new file? Make the original empty:</p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">edit_file(
    path = "Main.kt", 
    original = "", 
    replacement = "fun main() { println(\"Hello World!\") }"
)</pre>



<p>Same tool. Three different operations.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Learning from failures</strong></h4>



<p>The tool works, but we discovered something when testing with real agents. After several edits, the file was different. The agent tried to make another edit, but the text it was looking for didn’t exist anymore. Earlier edits had changed it.</p>



<p>The tool was returning &#8220;Edit failed&#8221;. We figured the agent would re-read the file and try again. Want to guess what happened instead?</p>



<p>The agent saw &#8220;Edit failed&#8221; and thought, “Something&#8217;s wrong with this file. Maybe I don&#8217;t have permission? I&#8217;ll just create a new file with my changes!” Suddenly, there were new files everywhere. Code that should have been edited ended up in new files instead.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The fix was simple. We just needed to tell the agent what actually went wrong. We changed the error message to <a href="https://github.com/JetBrains/koog/blob/c433b8e14c9450c5800245c36efe36021d2740b2/agents/agents-ext/src/commonMain/kotlin/ai/koog/agents/ext/tool/file/patch/TokenNormalizedPatchApplier.kt#L55" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&#8220;The original text to replace was not found in the file content. Consider re-reading the file to check if the original has changed since last read&#8221;</a>. And that worked. The agents learned: “Oh, text not found, I should re-read and try again.”</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Putting the pieces together</strong></h2>



<p>We have three tools. Now we need to connect them to GPT-5-Codex.</p>



<p>If you were building this from scratch without a framework, you&#8217;d write an execution loop: Send a prompt to GPT-5-Codex, parse the response, check if it wants to call a tool, execute that tool, send the results back, repeat. You&#8217;d need to handle API requests, error cases, token limits, and the tool calling protocol. That’s a lot of setup and effort.</p>



<p>Here, Koog&#8217;s <code>AIAgent</code> handles that loop. You give it an LLM, tools, and instructions:</p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">val agent = AIAgent(
    promptExecutor = simpleOpenAIExecutor(System.getenv("OPENAI_API_KEY")),
    llmModel = OpenAIModels.Chat.GPT5Codex,</pre>



<p>This connects the agent to GPT-5-Codex. promptExecutor is Koog&#8217;s way of handling LLM communication. You give it an API key and model, and it takes care of the rest.</p>



<p>Now tell it about your tools:</p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">    toolRegistry = ToolRegistry {
        tool(ListDirectoryTool(JVMFileSystemProvider.ReadOnly))
        tool(ReadFileTool(JVMFileSystemProvider.ReadOnly))
        tool(EditFileTool(JVMFileSystemProvider.ReadWrite))
    },</pre>



<p><code>ToolRegistry</code> is where you list your tools. Koog takes each tool, converts it into the JSON format GPT-5-Codex expects, and handles calling them when GPT-5-Codex requests it. </p>



<p>Give it instructions:</p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">    systemPrompt = """
        You are a highly skilled programmer tasked with updating the provided codebase according to the given task.
        Your goal is to deliver production-ready code changes that integrate seamlessly with the existing codebase 
        and solve given task.
    """.trimIndent(),</pre>



<p>This is the system prompt that tells the agent what its job is. Notice &#8220;updating the provided codebase&#8221;? That&#8217;s what makes the agent actually modify files instead of just explaining what should change.</p>



<p>Tell it how to run:</p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">    strategy = singleRunStrategy(),
    maxIterations = 100</pre>



<p>The strategy is the agent loop. <a href="https://api.koog.ai/agents/agents-core/ai.koog.agents.core.agent/single-run-strategy.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">singleRunStrategy()</a> is Koog&#8217;s built-in basic version. The agent calls tools until it decides the task is complete. We&#8217;ll explore how to write complex custom strategies in future articles, but this one works for most tasks.</p>



<p>But what if it never stops? We once had an agent read a 7,000-line file, hit the token limit, lose context, and then read the same file again – over and over. Luckily <code>maxIterations = 200</code> stopped it before burning through our API budget. After 200 steps, the agent quits. Each tool call costs 2 steps (one for the call, one for the response), so that&#8217;s 100 calls max.</p>



<p>Sometimes the agent will run for a bit, leaving you sitting there wondering if it&#8217;s working or stuck. We want to add some visibility to the agent, so we can see what it’s doing. The <code>handleEvents</code> block is how you watch what&#8217;s going on in Koog:</p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">{
    handleEvents {
        onToolCallStarting { ctx -&gt; println("Tool '${ctx.tool.name}' called with args:" +
                " ${ctx.toolArgs.toString().take(100)}")
        }
    }
}</pre>



<p>Koog gives you different events to hook into, like <code>onToolCallStarting</code>, <code>onToolCallFinished</code>, <code>onAgentFinished</code>, and<a href="https://docs.koog.ai/agent-events/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"> others</a>. We&#8217;re using <code>onToolCallStarting</code> here, which runs right before each tool executes, so we can log what&#8217;s about to happen.&nbsp;</p>



<p>You&#8217;ll want to tune what you log, though. The first time we did this, we printed everything. <code>EditFileTool</code> scrolled hundreds of lines past us. Then we tried just the tool name. <code>EditFileTool</code> ran three times, and we had no idea what it was editing. We print 100 characters now. You can follow what&#8217;s happening without staring at too much text.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Running our agent</strong></h2>



<p>The agent is built. Now we need a way to actually use it:</p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">fun main(args: Array&lt;String&gt;) = runBlocking {
    if (args.size &lt; 2) {
        println("Error: Please provide the project absolute path and a task as arguments")
        println("Usage: &lt;absolute_path&gt; &lt;task&gt;")
        return@runBlocking
    }

    val (path, task) = args
    val input = "Project path: $path\n\n$task"
    val result = agent.run(input)
    println(result)
}</pre>



<p>The agent needs to know two things: where the project lives and what to do. With this block of code, we grab both from command line arguments. If they&#8217;re missing, we show an error. Otherwise, we combine them into one input string and call <code>agent.run()</code>.</p>



<p>The agent takes over from there. It explores the project, reads files, and makes changes, looping until done. When it finishes, we print the result.</p>



<p>Here&#8217;s what it looks like in action:</p>


                                                <figure class="wp-block-image">
                    <img style="width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;" decoding="async" src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/output.gif" alt="" class="wp-image-657876"/>
                </figure>
                        


<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Does it work?</strong></h2>



<p>Once we had the agent running, we wanted to see what these three tools could actually accomplish. So we tested it on SWE-bench Verified, a benchmark of 500 coding tasks from GitHub issues.&nbsp;</p>



<p>It completed around 50% of them – not bad for 50 lines of code.</p>



<p>But the agent never verifies anything. Can&#8217;t compile. Can&#8217;t run tests. It reads code and makes changes based on what it sees, but has no way to know if those changes actually work.</p>



<p>And we’ve used three tools without showing you how to build one. You know what they do, but you don&#8217;t know how they work or how to make your own.</p>



<p><strong>That&#8217;s what my colleague Bruno shows you in the next article of this series.</strong> He builds a shell execution tool from scratch so the agent can run commands, see the output, and learn from what breaks. And he walks through how Koog tools work, because 50 lines of code only matter if you can extend the agent with tools for your specific problems.</p>



<p><a href="https://github.com/JetBrains/koog/blob/develop/examples/code-agent/step-01-minimal-agent/src/main/kotlin/Main.kt" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The code&#8217;s on GitHub</a>. Try it and share your experience with us.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Growing Kotlin Adoption in Your Company</title>
		<link>https://blog.jetbrains.com/kotlin/2025/11/growing-kotlin-adoption-in-your-company-2/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alyona Chernyaeva]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 11:15:53 +0000</pubDate>
		<featuredImage>https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Blog-Featured-1280x720-2-2.png</featuredImage>		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://blog.jetbrains.com/?post_type=kotlin&#038;p=655765</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Guest post by Urs Peter, Senior Software Engineer and JetBrains-certified Kotlin Trainer. For readers who’d like a more structured way to build Kotlin skills, Urs also leads the&#160;Kotlin Upskill Program at Xebia Academy. This is the third post in The Ultimate Guide to Successfully Adopting Kotlin in a Java-Dominated Environment, a series that follows how [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><em>Guest post by <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/urs-peter-70a2882/" data-type="link" data-id="https://bit.ly/urs-peter-linked-in" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Urs Peter</a>, Senior Software Engineer and JetBrains-certified Kotlin Trainer. For readers who’d like a more structured way to build Kotlin skills, Urs also leads the&nbsp;</em><a href="https://academy.xebia.com/upskilling/kotlin-academy/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><em>Kotlin Upskill Program</em></a><em> at Xebia Academy.</em></p>



<p><em>This is the third post in </em><strong><em>The Ultimate Guide to Successfully Adopting Kotlin in a Java-Dominated Environment</em></strong><em>, a series that follows how Kotlin adoption grows among real teams, from a single developer’s curiosity to company-wide transformation.</em></p>



<p><strong>All parts in the series:</strong></p>



<ol>
<li><a href="https://blog.jetbrains.com/kotlin/2025/10/getting-started-with-kotlin-for-java-developers/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Getting Started With Kotlin for Java Developers</a></li>



<li><a href="https://blog.jetbrains.com/kotlin/2025/10/evaluating-kotlin-in-real-projects/" data-type="link" data-id="https://blog.jetbrains.com/kotlin/2025/10/evaluating-kotlin-in-real-projects/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Evaluating Kotlin in Real Projects</a></li>



<li><a href="https://blog.jetbrains.com/kotlin/2025/11/growing-kotlin-adoption-in-your-company/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Growing Kotlin Adoption in Your Company</a></li>



<li><a href="https://blog.jetbrains.com/kotlin/2025/11/helping-decision-makers-say-yes-to-kotlin/" target="_blank" data-type="link" data-id="https://blog.jetbrains.com/kotlin/2025/11/helping-decision-makers-say-yes-to-kotlin/" rel="noreferrer noopener">Helping Decision‑Makers Say Yes to Kotlin</a></li>
</ol>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Spread the Word: Win the Hearts and Minds of your Fellow Developers</strong></h2>



<p>By now, you have a core team convinced of Kotlin&#8217;s benefits. Now comes the critical phase: How do you expand adoption?&nbsp;</p>



<p>Key in this phase is to win the hearts and minds of skeptical Java developers. Hard and soft factors can make the difference here:</p>



<p>Hard factors: the code</p>



<ul>
<li>Let the code speak</li>
</ul>



<p>Soft factors: support and connect developers</p>



<ul>
<li>Facilitate easy onboarding</li>



<li>Offer self-study material</li>



<li>Establish an in-house Kotlin community</li>



<li>Be patient…</li>
</ul>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Let the code speak</strong></h3>



<p>Double down on the experience you gained by (re-)writing an application in Kotlin and show the benefits in a tangible, accessible way:</p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Show, don’t tell</strong>: present the gained conciseness of Kotlin by comparing Java with Kotlin snippets.&nbsp;</li>



<li><strong>Zoom out to focus on the overarching paradigms</strong>: Kotlin is not just <em>different</em> from Java: Kotlin is built on the foundation of safety, conciseness for maximal readability and maintainability, functions as a first-class citizen, and extensibility, which together solve fundamental shortcomings of Java, while still being fully interoperable with the Java ecosystem.</li>
</ul>



<p>Here are some tangible examples:</p>



<p><strong>1. Null-safety: No more billion-dollar mistakes&nbsp;</strong></p>



<p><strong>Java</strong></p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="java" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">//This is why we have the billion-dollar mistake (not only in Java…)
Booking booking = null; //🤨 This is allowed but causes:
booking.destination; //Runtime error 😱

Optional&lt;Booking> booking = null; //Optionals aren’t safe from null either: 🤨
booking.map(Destination::destination); //Runtime error 😱</pre>



<p>Java has added some null-safety features over time, like Optional and Annotations (<code>@NotNull</code> etc.), but it has failed to solve this fundamental problem. Additionally, project <a href="https://openjdk.org/projects/valhalla/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Valhalla</a> (Null-Restricted and Nullable types) will not introduce null-safety to Java, but rather provide more options to choose from.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Kotlin</strong></p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">//Important to realize that null is very restricted in Kotlin:
val booking:Booking? = null //…null can only be assigned to Nullable types ✅ 
val booking:Booking = null //null assigned to a Non-nullable types yields a Compilation error 😃 

booking.destination //unsafely accessing a nullable type directly causes a Compilation error 😃
booking?.destination //only safe access is possible  ✅</pre>



<p>The great thing about Kotlin’s null-safety is that it is not only safe, but also offers great usability. A classic example of “have your cake and eat it, too”:</p>



<p>Say we have this Domain:</p>



<p><strong>Kotlin</strong></p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">data class Booking(val destination:Destination? = null)
data class Destination(val hotel:Hotel? = null)
data class Hotel(val name:String, val stars:Int? = null)</pre>



<p><strong>Java</strong></p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="java" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">public record Booking(Optional&lt;Destination> destination) {

   public Booking() { this(Optional.empty()); }

   public Booking(Destination destination) {
       this(Optional.ofNullable(destination));
   }
}

public record Destination(Optional&lt;Hotel> hotel) {

   public Destination() { this(Optional.empty()); }

   public Destination(Hotel hotel) {
       this(Optional.ofNullable(hotel));
   }
}

public record Hotel(String name, Optional&lt;Integer> stars) {

   public Hotel(String name) {

       this(name, Optional.empty());

   }

   public Hotel(String name, Integer stars) {
       this(name, Optional.ofNullable(stars));
   }
}</pre>



<p><strong>Constructing objects</strong></p>



<p><strong>Java</strong></p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="java" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">//Because Optional is a wrapper, the number of nested objects grows, which doesn’t help readability
final Optional&lt;Booking> booking = Optional.of(new Booking(
      Optional.of(new Destination(Optional.of(
            new Hotel("Sunset Paradise", 5))))));</pre>



<p><strong>Kotlin</strong></p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">//Since nullability is part of the type system, no wrapper is needed: The required type or null can be used. 
val booking:Booking? = Booking(Destination(Hotel("Sunset Paradise", 5)))</pre>



<p><strong>Traversing nested objects</strong></p>



<p><strong>Java</strong></p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="java" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">//traversing a graph of Optionals requires extensive unwrapping
final var stars = "*".repeat(booking
                          .flatMap(Booking::getDestination)
                          .flatMap(Destination::getHotel)
                          .map(Hotel::getStars).orElse(0)); //-> "*****"</pre>



<p><strong>Kotlin</strong></p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">//Easily traverse a graph of nullable types with: ‘?’, use  ?: for the ‘else’ case.
val stars = "*".repeat(booking?.destination?.hotel?.stars ?: 0) //-> "*****"</pre>



<p><strong>Unwrap nested object</strong></p>



<p><strong>Java</strong></p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="java" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">//extensive unwrapping is also needed for printing a leaf 
booking.getDestination()
       .flatMap(Destination::getHotel)
       .map(Hotel::getName)
       .map(String::toUpperCase)
         .ifPresent(System.out::println);</pre>



<p><strong>Kotlin</strong></p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">//In Kotlin we have two elegant options:
//1. we can again traverse the graph with ‘?’
booking?.destination?.hotel.?name?.uppercase()?.also(::println)

//2. We can make use of Kotlin’s smart-cast feature
if(booking?.destination?.hotel != null) {
   //The compiler has checked that all the elements in the object graph are not null, so we can access the elements as if they were non-nullable types
   println(booking.destination.hotel.uppercase())
}</pre>



<p>The lack of null-safety support in Java is a key pain-point for developers, leading to defensive programming, different nullability constructs (or none at all), including increased verbosity. Moreover, NullPointerExceptions are responsible for roughly one-third of application crashes (<a href="https://blog.jetbrains.com/kotlin/2020/11/productive-server-side-development-with-kotlin-stories/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">The JetBrains Blog</a>). Kotlin&#8217;s compile-time null checking prevents these runtime failures entirely. That’s why, still today, <strong>Null-safety is the primary driver for migration to Kotlin</strong>.</p>



<p><strong>2. Collections are your friend, not your enemy</strong></p>



<p>The creator of Spring, Rod Johnson, stated in a recent interview that it was not Nullable-types that made him try out Kotlin, but the overly complicated Java Streams API: <a href="https://youtu.be/Rx3XZoqbi78?t=1018" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Creator of Spring: No desire to write Java</a>.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The following example depicts the various reasons why the Java Streams API is so horribly complicated and how Kotlin solves all of the issues:</p>



<p><strong>Java</strong></p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="java" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">public record Product(String name, int... ratings){}
List&lt;Product> products = List.of(
  new Product("gadget", 9, 8, 7), 
  new Product("goody", 10, 9)
);

Map&lt;String, Integer> maxRatingsPerProduct =

   //🤨 1. Stream introduces indirection
   products.stream()
     //🤨 1. Always to and from Stream conversion
      .collect(
        //🤨 2. Lacks extension methods, so wrappers are required
        Collectors.groupingBy(
           Product::name,
            //🤨 2. Again…
           Collectors.mapping( groupedProducts ->
                //🤨 3. (too) low-level types, arrays, and primitives cause extra complexity
                //🤨 4. No API on Array, always wrap in stream 
               Arrays.stream(groupedProducts.ratings())
                   .max()
                      //🤨 5. Extra verbosity due to Optional
                      .orElse(0.0),
               //🤨 6. No named arguments: what does this do?
                Collectors.reducing(0, Integer::max)
              )
            ));</pre>



<p><strong>Kotlin</strong></p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">//😃 rich and uniform Collection API - even on Java collections - due to extension methods
val maxRatingsPerProduct = products.
      .groupBy { it.name }
      .mapValues { (_, groupedProducts) -> //😃 destructuring for semantic precision
            //😃 built-in nullability support, and the same API for 
            //arrays like other Collections
            groupedProducts.flatMap { it.ratings }
                  .maxOrNull() ?: 0 
            }
      }</pre>



<p>Due to Kotlin’s uniform Collection framework, converting between different collection types is very straightforward:<br><strong>Java</strong></p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="java" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">int[] numbers = {1, 3, 3, 5, 2};

Set&lt;Integer> unique = Arrays.stream(numbers).boxed().collect(Collectors.toSet());

Map&lt;Integer, Boolean> evenOrOdd = unique.stream()
       .collect(Collectors.toMap(
               n -> n,
               n -> n % 2 == 0));</pre>



<p><strong>Kotlin</strong></p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">val numbers = arrayOf(1, 3, 3, 5, 2)

val unique: Set&lt;Int> = numbers.toSet() //😃 simply call to&lt;Collection> to do the conversion

val evenOrOdd: Map&lt;Int, Boolean> = unique.associateWith { it % 2 == 0 }</pre>



<p><strong>Net effect:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Feature-rich, intuitive Collection API:</strong> pipelines read left-to-right like English, not inside nested collector calls.</li>



<li><strong>Less boilerplate and complexity:</strong> no Collectors.groupingBy, no Stream, no Optional, no Arrays.stream.</li>



<li><strong>One mental model:</strong> whether you start with a <code>List</code>, <code>Set</code>, <code>Array</code>, or primitive array, you reach for the <em>same</em> collection operators.</li>



<li><strong>Performance without pain:</strong> the compiler inserts boxing/unboxing only where unavoidable; you write normal code.</li>



<li>​​<strong>Null-safety integrated: </strong>Collection API fully supports nullability with various helpers often suffixed with <code>orNull(...)</code>.</li>



<li><strong>Seamless Java-interop with idiomatic wrappers:</strong> Due to extension methods, you get the “best of both worlds” – feature-rich Collections on top of Java collections.</li>
</ul>



<p>Put simply, Kotlin lifts the everyday collection tasks – filtering, mapping, grouping etc. – into first-class, <em>composable</em> functions, so you express <em>what</em> you want, not the ceremony of <em>how</em> to get there.</p>



<p><strong>3. No more checked Exceptions, yet safer code in Kotlin</strong></p>



<p>Java is one of the only languages that still supports checked Exceptions. Though initially implemented as a safety feature, they have not lived up to their promise. Their verbosity, pointless catch blocks that do nothing or rethrow as an Exception as a <code>RuntimeException</code>, and their misalignment with lambdas are a few reasons why they get in the way rather than making your code safer.</p>



<p>Kotlin follows the proven paradigm used by almost all other programming languages –C#, Python, Scala, Rust, and Go – of using exceptions only for unrecoverable situations.</p>



<p>The following examples highlight the obstacles that checked Exceptions introduce into your code, without adding any safety:<br><br><strong>Java</strong></p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="java" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">public String downloadAndGetLargestFile(List&lt;String> urls) {
   List&lt;String> contents = urls.stream().map(urlStr -> {
               Optional&lt;URL> optional;
               try {
                   optional = Optional.of(new URI(urlStr).toURL());
                   //🤨 Within lambdas checked exceptions are not supported and must always be caught...
               } catch (URISyntaxException | MalformedURLException e) {
                   optional = Optional.empty();
               }
               return optional;
           }).filter(Optional::isPresent)       //Quite a mouthful to get rid of the Optional...
           .map(Optional::get)
           .map(url -> {
               try (InputStream is = url.openStream()) {
                   return new String(is.readAllBytes(), StandardCharsets.UTF_8);
               } catch (IOException e) {
                   //🤨… or re-thrown, which is annoying, I don’t really care about IOE
                   throw new IllegalArgumentException(e);
               }
           }).toList();
   //🤨 An empty List results in a NoSuchElementException, so why is it not checked? The chance that the List is empty is as high as the other two cases above...
   return Collections.max(contents);
}</pre>



<p><strong>Kotlin</strong></p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">//😃 safe return type
fun downloadAndGetLargestFile(urls: List&lt;String>): String? =
   urls.mapNotNull {    //😃 convenient utility methods to rid of null
       //😃 try catch is possible, yet runCatching is an elegant way to convert an exception to null
       runCatching { URI(it).toURL() }.getOrNull()
   }.maxOfOrNull{  //😃 safe way to retrieve the max value
       it.openStream().use{ it.reader().readText() }  //😃 convenient extension methods to make java.io streams fluent
   }</pre>



<p><strong>4. Functions as first-class citizens</strong></p>



<p>Kotlin treats functions as first-class citizens, which may raise questions if you’re coming from Java: What does that mean, and why does it matter?</p>



<p>The key difference lies in Java’s limited approach – its functional capabilities focus mostly on the call-site via lambdas, while the declaration-side remains tied to verbose and less intuitive functional interfaces. In Kotlin, you can define, pass, return, and compose functions without any boilerplate, making functional programming far more expressive and natural.</p>



<p><strong>Java</strong></p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="java" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">public void doWithImage(
      URL url, 
      //🤨 Function interfaces introduce an indirection: because we don’t see the signature of a Function we don’t know what a  BiConsumer does, unless we look it up
      BiConsumer&lt;String, BufferedImage> f) throws IOException {
        f.accept(url.getFile(), ImageIO.read(url));
}

//🤨 Same here
public void debug(Supplier&lt;String> f) {
   if(isDebugEnabled()) {
      logger.debug("Debug: " + f.get());
   }
}

//🤨 calling no-argument lambdas is verbose
debug(() -> "expensive concat".repeat(1000));</pre>



<p><strong>Kotlin</strong></p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">fun doWithImage(
   url: URL,
  //😃 Kotlin has a syntax for declaring functions: from the signature, we see what goes in and what goes out 
   f:(String, BufferedImage) -> Unit) = 
      f(url.file, ImageIO.read(url))

  //😃 same here: nothing goes in, a String goes out
fun debug(msg: () -> String) {
   if(isDebugEnabled) {
            logger.debug(msg())
   }
}

//😃 convenient syntax to pass a lambda: {&lt;lambda body>}
debug{"expensive concat".repeat(1000)}</pre>



<p>Kotlin provides a clear and concise syntax for declaring functions – just from the signature, you can immediately see what goes in and what comes out, without having to navigate to an external functional interface.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Java “leaks” its functional programming features through a large set of <code>java.util.function.*</code> interfaces with verbose and complex signatures, which often makes functional programming cumbersome to use. Kotlin, by contrast, treats functions as first-class citizens: these interfaces remain hidden from the developer, yet remain fully interoperable with Java’s approach:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/unnamed-16.png" alt="" class="wp-image-655829" style="aspect-ratio:1.1355932203389831;width:510px;height:auto; width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;"/></figure>



<p>As a result, using functions in Kotlin is significantly more straightforward and intuitive, which lowers the threshold considerably for leveraging this powerful programming concept in your own code.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>5. Headache-free concurrency with coroutines</strong></p>



<p>If you need high throughput, parallel processing within a single request, or streaming, the only option you have in Java is a reactive library, like Reactor and RxJava, available in frameworks like Spring WebFlux, Vert.X, Quarkus etc.</p>



<p>The problem with these libraries is that they are notoriously complicated, forcing you into functional programming. As such, they have a steep learning curve, yet it is very easy to make errors that can have dire consequences when the application is under load. That’s most probably why reactive programming never became mainstream.&nbsp;</p>


                    <div class="alert ">
            <p><strong>Note:</strong> VirtualThreads are not a replacement for reactive libraries, even though there is some overlap. VirtualThreads offer non-blocking I/O, but do not provide features such as parallel processing or reactive streams. Structured concurrency and Scoped Values will also enable parallel processing once the major frameworks have support for it. For reactive streams, you will always have to rely on a reactive library.<br />
</p>
        </div>
    






<p>So let’s assume you are a Java developer using Spring Boot and you want to make a parallel call within a single request. This is what you end up with:&nbsp;</p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="java" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">@PostMapping("/users")
@ResponseBody
@Transactional
public Mono&lt;User> storeUser(@RequestBody User user) {
   Mono&lt;URL> avatarMono = avatarService.randomAvatar();
   Mono&lt;Boolean> validEmailMono = emailService.verifyEmail(user.getEmail());
   //🤨 what does ‘zip’ do?
   return Mono.zip(avatarMono, validEmailMono).flatMap(tuple -> 
       if(!tuple.getT2()) //what is getT2()? It’s the validEmail Boolean…
        //🤨 why can I not just throw an exception?
         Mono.error(new InvalidEmailException("Invalid Email"));
       else personDao.save(UserBuilder.from(user)
                                          .withAvatarUrl(tuple.getT1()));
     );  
  }</pre>



<p>Even though, from a runtime perspective, this code performs perfectly well, the accidental complexity introduced is enormous:&nbsp;</p>



<ul>
<li>The code is dominated by <code>Mono/Flux</code>-es, throughout the whole call chain, which enforces you to wrap all domain objects.</li>



<li>There are many complex operators everywhere, like <code>zip</code>, <code>flatMap</code>, etc.</li>



<li>You cannot use standard programming constructs like throwing exceptions&nbsp;</li>



<li>The business intent of your code suffers significantly: the code focuses on <code>Monos</code> and <code>flatMap</code>, thereby obscuring what is truly happening from a business perspective.</li>
</ul>



<p>The good news is that there is a powerful remedy in the form of Kotlin Coroutines. Coroutines can be framed as a reactive implementation on the language level. As such, they combine the best of both worlds:&nbsp;</p>



<ul>
<li>You write sequential code like you did before.</li>



<li>The code is executed asynchronously / in parallel at runtime.</li>
</ul>



<p>The above Java code converted to coroutines looks as follows:</p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">@GetMapping("/users")
@ResponseBody
@Transactional
suspend fun storeUser(@RequestBody user:User):User = coroutineScope {
   val avatarUrl = async { avatarService.randomAvatar() }
   val validEmail = async { emailService.verifyEmail() }
   if(!validEmail.await()) throw InvalidEmailException("Invalid email")
   personRepo.save(user.copy(avatar = avatarUrl.await()))
}</pre>



<p>Kotlin’s suspend keyword enables structured, non-blocking execution in a clear and concise manner. Together with <code>async{}</code> and <code>await()</code>, it facilitates parallel processing without the need for deeply nested callbacks or complex constructs such as <code>Mono</code> or <code>CompletableFuture</code>.</p>



<p>That’s why complexity will decrease, and developer joy and maintainability will increase, with the exact same performance characteristics.&nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img style="width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;" decoding="async" src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/unnamed-17.png" alt="" class="wp-image-655845"/></figure>



<p><strong>Note</strong>: Not all major Java-based web frameworks support Coroutines as well. Spring does an excellent job, as does Micronaut. Quarkus currently offers limited Coroutine support.</p>



<p><strong>6. But hey, Java is evolving too!</strong></p>



<p>Java keeps moving forward with features like records, pattern matching, and upcoming projects such as Amber, Valhalla, and Loom. This steady evolution strengthens the JVM and benefits the entire ecosystem.</p>



<p>But here’s the catch: most of these “new” Java features are things Kotlin developers have enjoyed for years. Null safety, value classes, top-level functions, default arguments, concise collections, and first-class functions are all baked into Kotlin’s design – delivered in a more unified and developer-friendly way. That’s why Kotlin code often feels cleaner, safer, and far more productive.</p>



<p>And there is more: Kotlin also profits from Java’s innovation. JVM-level advances like Virtual Threads and Loom in general, or Valhalla’s performance boosts apply seamlessly to Kotlin too.</p>



<p>In short: Java evolves, but Kotlin was designed from day one to give developers the modern tools they need – making it a safe, modern, and forward-looking choice for building the future.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img style="width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;" decoding="async" src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/kotlin-castle-1.png" alt="" class="wp-image-655858"/></figure>



<p><strong>7. Kotlin&#8217;s evolutionary advantage</strong></p>



<p>Older programming languages inevitably carry legacy baggage compared to modern alternatives. Updating a language while supporting massive existing codebases presents unique challenges for language designers. Kotlin enjoys two crucial advantages:</p>



<p><strong>Standing on the shoulders of giants</strong>: Rather than reinventing the wheel, Kotlin&#8217;s initial design team gathered proven paradigms from major programming languages and unified them into a cohesive whole. This approach maximized evolutionary learning from the broader programming community.</p>



<p><strong>Learning from Java&#8217;s shortcomings</strong>: Kotlin&#8217;s designers could observe Java&#8217;s pitfalls and develop solid solutions from the ground up.</p>



<p>For deeper insights into Kotlin&#8217;s evolution, Andrey Breslav from Kotlin&#8217;s original design team gave an excellent talk at KotlinDevDay Amsterdam: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7z_K-hTTeqI&amp;ab_channel=Xebia" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><em>Shoulders of Giants: Languages Kotlin Learned From</em> – Andrey Breslav</a></p>



<p><strong>Soft factors: Support and connect developers in their Kotlin adoption journey</strong></p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>1. Facilitate easy onboarding</strong></h3>



<p>The goal of the expressive Java vs. Kotlin code snippets is to whet the appetite for Kotlin. Code alone, however, is not enough to win the hearts and minds of Java developers. To accelerate adoption and ensure a smooth start, provide:</p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Sample project</strong>: A ready-to-run project with both Java and Kotlin code side-by-side, giving teams a practical reference during migration.<br></li>



<li><strong>Built-in quality checks</strong>: Preconfigured with tools like SonarQube, ktlint, and detekt to promote clean, consistent, and maintainable code from day one. This will enable you to apply consistent lint rules, testing frameworks, libraries, and CI pipelines to reduce friction across teams.<br></li>



<li><strong>Coaching and support</strong>: Experienced Kotlin engineers available to coach new teams, answer questions, and provide hands-on advice during the early stages of development.
<ul>
<li>This one is particularly important: with only a few hours of guidance from an experienced developer from another team who has gone through these stages before, much damage and technical debt can be prevented.&nbsp;</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>



<p>A bit of support and coaching is the most powerful way to nurture lasting enthusiasm for Kotlin.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>2. Offer (self-)study material</strong></h3>



<p>Especially when coming from Java, learning the Kotlin basics can be done on your own. Providing some resources upfront eases the path to getting productive with Kotlin and lowers the threshold.&nbsp;</p>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://kotlinlang.org/docs/getting-started.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>JetBrains “Tour of Kotlin” (Get Started guide)</strong><br></a>A short, browser-based tutorial on the official Kotlin site.</li>



<li><a href="https://kotlinlang.org/docs/koans.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Kotlin Koans<br></strong></a>A set of bite-sized coding challenges maintained by JetBrains.</li>



<li><a href="https://www.udacity.com/course/kotlin-bootcamp-for-programmers--ud9011" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Udacity “Kotlin Bootcamp for Programmers”</strong><br></a>A full video-based course created in partnership with Google.</li>
</ul>


                    <div class="alert ">
            <p><strong>Note:</strong> Although self-study is valuable for grasping the basics, it also has some drawbacks. One of these drawbacks is an optionality: being caught up in the day&#8217;s frenzy, it&#8217;s tempting to skip self-study. Moreover, you will lack feedback from a practitioner who knows the subtle nuances of correctly applied idiomatic Kotlin. There is a big chance that after a self-study course, you will write Java-ish Kotlin, which gives you some benefits but does not unlock the full potential of the language. </p>
        </div>
    






<p>Unless you don’t have good coaching, a classical course can be very beneficial. There is a need to attend; you can exchange with peers of the same level and have your questions answered by an experienced professional, which will get you up to speed much faster with less non-idiomatic Kotlin during the initial transition.&nbsp;</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>3. Establish an in-house Kotlin community</strong></h3>



<p>One of the fastest ways to level up Kotlin expertise across your company is to create and foremost nurture an in-house community.</p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Launch an internal Kotlin community</strong>
<ul>
<li>First look for a core-team of at least 3–6 developers who are willing to invest in a Kotlin community. Also ensure they get time and credits from their managers for their task.</li>



<li>Once the team is formed, organize a company-wide kick-off with well-known speakers from the Kotlin community. This will ignite the Kotlin flame and give it momentum.</li>



<li>Schedule regular meet-ups (monthly or bi-weekly) so momentum never drops.</li>



<li>Create a shared chat channel/wiki where questions, code snippets, and event notes live.<br></li>
</ul>
</li>



<li><strong>Invite (external) speakers</strong>
<ul>
<li>Bring in engineers who’ve shipped Kotlin in production to share candid war stories.</li>



<li>Alternate between deep-dive technical talks (coroutines, KMP, functional programming) and higher-level case studies (migration strategies, tooling tips).<br></li>
</ul>
</li>



<li><strong>Present lessons learned from other in-house projects</strong>
<ul>
<li>Ask project leads to present their Kotlin learnings – what worked, what didn’t, and measurable outcomes.</li>



<li>These insights can be captured in a “Kotlin playbook” that new teams can pick up.<br></li>
</ul>
</li>



<li><strong>Give your own developers the stage</strong>
<ul>
<li>Run lightning-talk sessions where anyone can demo a neat trick, library, or failure they overcame in 5–10 minutes.</li>



<li>Celebrate contributors publicly – shout-outs in all-hands or internal newsletters boost engagement and knowledge-sharing.<br></li>
</ul>
</li>



<li><strong>Keep feedback loops tight</strong>
<ul>
<li>After each session, collect quick polls on clarity and usefulness, then tweak future agendas accordingly.</li>



<li>Rotate organizational duties so the community doesn’t hinge on a single champion and stays resilient long-term.<br></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Note</strong>: Many of the suggestions above sound straightforward. However, the effort needed to keep a community vibrant and alive should not be underestimated.&nbsp;</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>4. Be patient…</strong></h3>



<p>Cultural change takes time. The danger of being enthusiastic about a tool that makes a difference for you is pushing things, which can be counterproductive. An effective approach is to nurture the adoption process with all the activities discussed above, with <em>show, don’t tell</em> as prior guidance.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Up next in the series</h3>



<p>We shift focus from convincing developers to persuading decision-makers. The next post shows how to build a compelling business case for Kotlin adoption, grounded in real data and measurable outcomes. You’ll learn how to translate developer wins into management arguments, link productivity gains to cost savings, and demonstrate why Kotlin is more than a technical upgrade&nbsp;<strong>–</strong>&nbsp;it’s a strategic move for teams and companies alike.</p>


    <div class="about-author ">
        <div class="about-author__box">
            <div class="row">
                                                            <div class="about-author__box-img">
                            <img style="width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;" decoding="async" src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/a3f7-400o400o1-QYUavRYyARnAVJLCpM1m8M.webp" alt="" loading="lazy">
                        </div>
                                        <div class="about-author__box-text">
                                                    <h4>Urs Peter</h4>
                                                <p>Urs is a seasoned software engineer, solution architect, conference speaker, and trainer with over 20 years of experience in building resilient, scalable, and mission-critical systems, mostly involving Kotlin and Scala.</p>
<p>Besides his job as a consultant, he is also a passionate trainer and author of a great variety of courses ranging from language courses for Kotlin and Scala to architectural trainings such as Microservices and Event-Driven Architectures.</p>
<p>As a people person by nature, he loves to share knowledge and inspire and get inspired by peers on meetups and conferences. Urs is a JetBrains certified Kotlin trainer.</p>
                    </div>
                            </div>
        </div>
    </div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Finding Order in the Mayhem: A Novel Concurrency Testing Tool that Improved the Kotlin Compiler</title>
		<link>https://blog.jetbrains.com/research/2025/10/litmuskt-concurrency-testing/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Katie Fraser]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 12:12:14 +0000</pubDate>
		<featuredImage>https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/KT-social-BlogFeatured-1280x720-1-3.png</featuredImage>		<product ><![CDATA[kotlin]]></product>
		<category><![CDATA[kotlin]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[concurrency]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jetbrains-research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[testing]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://blog.jetbrains.com/?post_type=research&#038;p=652763</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[If you’ve ever tried to track down a bug in concurrent programs, you know how chaotic and frustrating it can be: everything seems to work fine, then suddenly crashes, and you can’t quite pin down why – all while the bugs slip through.&#160; To bring order to this chaos, at JetBrains Research we built LitmusKt [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>If you’ve ever tried to track down a bug in concurrent programs, you know how chaotic and frustrating it can be: everything seems to work fine, then suddenly crashes, and you can’t quite pin down why – all while the bugs slip through.&nbsp;</p>



<p>To bring order to this chaos, at <a style="color:#6B57FF;" href="https://lp.jetbrains.com/research/software-engineering/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">JetBrains Research</a> we built <a style="color:#6B57FF;" href="https://github.com/Jetbrains-Research/litmuskt" target="_blank" rel="noopener">LitmusKt</a> — a novel testing tool for Kotlin’s multiplatform concurrency. Designed specifically for Kotlin’s unique mix of JVM, Native, and JavaScript backends, LitmusKt helps developers uncover and eliminate subtle, platform-specific concurrency errors that traditional testing can’t catch.</p>



<p>In our <a style="color:#6B57FF;" href="https://blog.jetbrains.com/research/2025/07/fuzzing-the-kotlin-compiler/">previous post</a>, we discussed a new approach to fuzzing the Kotlin compiler. Now we’re exploring how LitmusKt takes that work further – systematically revealing concurrency bugs hidden deep in the Kotlin runtime and compiler. In this post, we will:</p>



<ul>
<li>Talk about why concurrent programming is complex and why automated testing is particularly tricky.</li>



<li>Explain how LitmusKt was needed for the Kotlin compiler and describe its cool technical features.</li>



<li>Lay out the history of LitmusKt, from its infancy as a research prototype, some of the bugs it found, and how it is now integrated into Kotlin/Native development.</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Concurrent programming</h2>



<p>When multiple tasks or computations are executed simultaneously rather than sequentially, the approach is called <em>concurrent programming</em>. Although it may sound like a simple concept, it can sometimes act erratically when implemented improperly.&nbsp;</p>



<p>If it is so tricky, why is concurrent programming even implemented? Well, many programming problems are naturally concurrent: there are numerous tasks and external events running at the same time. Consider also how modern hardware itself is inherently concurrent, as most CPUs have multiple cores. Without concurrent code, we would not be able to use the cores to their full potential.</p>



<p>In Per Brinch Hansen’s <a style="color:#6B57FF;" href="https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-1-4757-3472-0_1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The Invention of Concurrent Programming</a> (which covers the history of concurrent programming up to 2001), he tells a story where he and Peter Kraft needed to design a real-time system for a large chemical plant. For this, a computer would perform a fixed number of tasks simultaneously. The tasks’ speed could be manually adjusted by the plant operators, which means that there was no set speed.&nbsp;</p>



<p>So they were working with simultaneous tasks and needed some sort of process synchronization. Sequential, task-independent programming wasn’t going to cut it. If you want to know what happens next, you can find it in Part I of <a style="color:#6B57FF;" href="https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-1-4757-3472-0_1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">their book</a> (spoiler: they implemented <a style="color:#6B57FF;" href="https://pure.tue.nl/ws/files/4279816/344354178746665.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Edsger Dijkstra’s semaphores</a>).</p>



<p>Concurrent programming provides a number of advantages, including:</p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Improved performance and throughput</strong>. More tasks are completed in a given timeframe. This is especially beneficial on multi-core processors, where different tasks can run on different cores.</li>



<li><strong>Efficient resource use</strong>, because system resources (like the CPU) can be used for other tasks while one task is waiting for input/output or another event. This reduces idle time and maximizes hardware efficiency.</li>



<li><strong>Better responsiveness and user experience</strong>, because applications like web browsers, graphical user interfaces, and real-time systems remain responsive to input while other tasks run in the background. This supports smooth and uninterrupted user interactions.</li>
</ul>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Challenges in concurrent programming</h3>



<p>When concurrent programming was first introduced in the 1960s, the operating systems running it were rather unstable. Challenges included the following:</p>



<ul>
<li>A small programming error could cause a lot of problems but be really difficult to test for and therefore fix.</li>



<li><a style="color:#6B57FF;" href="https://webdocs.cs.ualberta.ca/~tony/OldPapers/dead.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Deadlocks</a>, or when all parts of a concurrent process are blocked, usually due to a lack of resources.</li>
</ul>



<p>Concurrent programming inherently involves simultaneously executed tasks. For this reason, challenges like the above arise because concurrent programming is highly dependent on unpredictable factors such as scheduling order or real-world timing. Let’s look at an example.</p>



<p>Consider a program that initializes two shared variables, <code>x</code> and <code>y</code>, with <code>0</code>, and starts two threads running in parallel. Each thread writes <code>1</code> to its associated variable. Then, each reads the other variable and stores that value as its result (<code>r1</code> and <code>r2</code>, respectively, which are also initialized with <code>0</code>).</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center"><img style="width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;" decoding="async" src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/LitmusKt_introweak2.png" alt="" /></p>



<p>At first glance, the outcomes for <code>r1</code> and <code>r2</code> seem limited and predictable. Either:</p>



<ul>
<li>One thread finishes first, so it writes <code>1</code> to <code>x</code>, reads <code>0</code> from <code>y</code>, and the other reads the updated value <code>1</code>, giving us straightforward outcomes of <code>(0, 1)</code> or <code>(1, 0)</code>, depending on which thread finished first.</li>



<li>Or both threads execute at the same time, so they both write <code>1</code>, and both read <code>1</code>, yielding another expected result: <code>(1, 1)</code>.</li>
</ul>



<p>But then, after running the program many times, a seemingly impossible outcome starts to appear: Each thread reads <code>0</code>, even though both have written <code>1</code>.</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center"><img style="width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;" decoding="async" src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/LitmusKt_introweak.png" alt="" /></p>



<p>This sort of bizarre outcome is called <strong><mark style="background-color:#fcf84a" class="has-inline-color">weak behavior</mark></strong>. It can happen for one of two reasons:</p>



<ul>
<li>Compiler optimizations, where compilers rearrange instructions or eliminate redundant memory operations to increase performance. This can result in subtle bugs, or even break the code, as dependencies may be lost in the shuffle.</li>



<li>CPU buffering and reordering, where the hardware itself may buffer, delay, or reorder reads and writes to maximize efficiency. Modern CPUs have <em>weak memory models</em> that allow operations to happen in surprising sequences, invisible in regular single-threaded programs.</li>
</ul>



<p>Weak behaviors caused by the above are a central focus in analyzing and testing concurrent programs with specialized tools. If the programmer only looks at the code or thinks in terms of simple statement interleaving, these outcomes seem impossible.&nbsp;</p>



<p>In reality, compiler and CPU optimizations change the story, making concurrent programming far more elusive and unpredictable than it appears at first glance. This creates headaches for programmers and those designing programming languages. Because reasoning about these subtle interactions is so challenging, <strong>thorough testing is essential to ensure reliability</strong>.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Testing concurrent programs</h3>



<p>Concurrent programming is difficult to test because nondeterministic thread interactions can produce subtle, non-reproducible failures. These are often called Heisenbugs, and they only appear under specific timings or schedules, making them inherently hard to find and troubleshoot. The same input can pass a test and then fail the very same test depending on subtle, uncontrollable sources of nondeterminism, and even the act of observing or debugging can mask or alter the bug’s behavior, contributing to flaky tests and prolonged debugging cycles.</p>



<p>Traditional testing approaches struggle here because listing all possible thread schedules is infeasible in practice, and even systematic methods that control scheduling to capture nondeterminism are time-consuming and resource-intensive. This challenge is compounded by state space explosion, where the number of possible interleavings grows combinatorially with threads and synchronization points, necessitating reductions such as partial-order reduction and guided exploration to avoid redundant paths.</p>



<p>For testing these notoriously tricky programs, developers use a variety of strategies. Some common ones are listed in the table below.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/LitmusKt_table-1.png" alt="" class="wp-image-652894" style="width:750px; width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;"/></figure>



<p>While code review and static analysis are both useful for early detection of concurrency bugs, they come with disadvantages as well. Namely, code review is susceptible to the reviewers’ errors and knowledge gaps; static analysis can generate false positives, thereby creating more work, and can miss runtime-only errors.</p>



<p>Random/<a style="color:#6B57FF;" href="https://blog.jetbrains.com/research/2025/07/fuzzing-the-kotlin-compiler/">fuzz</a>/<a style="color:#6B57FF;" href="https://testsigma.com/blog/software-stress-testing/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">stress</a> testing types are great for detecting rare or subtle bugs. They test programs under extreme conditions, for example with random inputs and under heavy load. These tests (especially stress testing) can also be useful to ensure smooth operation of a program in critical situations. These methods are usually resource-intensive, and they can sometimes produce false positives or miss more complex issues.</p>



<p>Many strategies work well with business logic and modest concurrency patterns, but fall short with the subtle hardware or compiler optimizations that lead to “impossible” results, like the (0,0) outcome above. For example, stress testing or fuzzing may uncover these bugs eventually, but a specific type of tests called <strong><strong><mark style="background-color:#fcf84a" class="has-inline-color">litmus tests</mark></strong></strong> is designed to systematically target these subtle behaviors and confirm theoretical predictions. This strategy is highly effective for environments with well-defined memory models, like the Java Virtual Machine (JVM), or specific CPUs.</p>



<p>For the rest of this post, we will concentrate on litmus testing and then tell you about a specific litmus testing tool developed by JetBrains researchers.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Litmus testing</h3>



<p>Litmus testing is like stress testing for concurrency: you write small concurrent programs (i.e., litmus tests) and run them thousands of times to catch rare, weird behaviors that only happen under specific timing conditions. Established tools like <a style="color:#6B57FF;" href="https://github.com/openjdk/jcstress" target="_blank" rel="noopener">JCStress</a> for Java and <a style="color:#6B57FF;" href="https://github.com/herd/herdtools7" target="_blank" rel="noopener">herdtools</a> for assembly language have successfully found real bugs in production systems.</p>



<p><em>JCStress</em>, for instance, is used by OpenJDK developers to test the JVM, catching subtle race conditions and memory model violations that could cause catastrophic failures in production. <em>herdtools</em> goes even deeper, testing assembly-level programs against processor memory models to ensure hardware behaves as expected. While these tools are useful for the respective languages, they run into limitations with multi-platform languages like <a style="color:#6B57FF;" href="https://kotlinlang.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Kotlin</a>.</p>



<p>Unlike other languages, a key feature of Kotlin is that it compiles to JVM, Native, JavaScript, and WebAssembly, and each platform has its own distinct concurrency semantics and memory models. This diversity means some bugs cannot be caught with tools designed for just one backend – and so far existing tools hadn&#8217;t been able to handle this complexity. In other words, <strong>Kotlin needed its own litmus testing tool</strong>.</p>



<p>We took on the challenge of helping to discover bugs in the Kotlin compiler, and the result is a new tool that makes testing these tricky programs far easier.&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Testing concurrency programs with LitmusKt</h2>



<p>To overcome the lack of a proper Kotlin testing tool for concurrency programming, we  at  <a style="color:#6B57FF;" href="https://lp.jetbrains.com/research/software-engineering/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">JetBrains Research</a>) decided to build our own solution, <a style="color:#6B57FF;" href="https://github.com/Jetbrains-Research/litmuskt" target="_blank" rel="noopener">LitmusKt</a> (see <a style="color:#6B57FF;" href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2501.07472" target="_blank" rel="noopener">their recent paper</a>). This section will tell you about its design and tech highlights, as well as its practical applications.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">LitmusKt’s design and cool technical features</h3>



<p>LitmusKt allows developers to write litmus tests once and run them across both Kotlin/JVM and Kotlin/Native platforms. The tool uses a custom domain-specific language that makes writing tests straightforward. A few examples of what LitmusKt does:</p>



<ul>
<li>Declare shared states, such as shared variables, between threads.</li>



<li>Write thread behavior so that it’s clear what each thread should do.</li>



<li>Label expected outcomes as <em>acceptable</em>, <em>interesting</em> (i.e., noteworthy but allowed), or <em>forbidden</em>.</li>
</ul>



<p>By using a custom DSL, developers can express thread interactions, shared variables, and outcome conditions flexibly, all within Kotlin. This<strong> lowers the barrier for writing complex concurrency tests</strong>.</p>



<p>Let’s run through an example. Below you can find the code for the Store Buffering test, which is a standard litmus test (it’s also the program we saw in the example before). The test involves (i) defining a shared state, (ii) running code for several threads, and (iii) specifying&nbsp; test outcomes; we will go through each one step by step.</p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="generic" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">object StoreBuffering {
 val Plain = litmusTest({
    object : LitmusIIOutcome() {
	var x = 0
	var y = 0
    }
}) {
   thread { x = 1; r1 = y }
   thread { y = 1; r2 = x }
   spec {
	accept(r1 = 0, r2 = 1)
	accept(r1 = 1, r2 = 0)
	accept(r1 = 1, r2 = 1)
	interesting(r1 = 0, r2 = 0)
   }
   reset { x = 0; y = 0 }
}</pre>



<p>First, the test itself needs to be declared: we declare the state which will eventually be shared between the threads. In the example below, this comprises two <code>int</code> variables.&nbsp;</p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">object StoreBuffering {
 val Plain = litmusTest({
    object : LitmusIIOutcome() {
	var x = 0
	var y = 0
    }</pre>



<p>Next comes the code for each thread, shown below.</p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">}) {
   thread { x = 1; r1 = y }
   thread { y = 1; r2 = x }</pre>



<p>Finally, we must declare the outcomes and their labels. The possible outcomes are:</p>



<ul>
<li><strong><mark style="background-color:rgba(0, 0, 0, 0);color:#5e5d5d" class="has-inline-color">Acceptable</mark></strong>: sequentially consistent outcomes</li>



<li><strong><mark style="background-color:rgba(0, 0, 0, 0);color:#fc801d" class="has-inline-color">Interesting</mark></strong>: weak but tolerable outcomes according to the semantics of the programming language</li>
</ul>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group=""> spec {
	accept(r1 = 0, r2 = 1)
	accept(r1 = 1, r2 = 0)
	accept(r1 = 1, r2 = 1)
	interesting(r1 = 0, r2 = 0)
   }</pre>



<p>If you recall the example above, the result where <code>r1 = 0</code> and <code>r2 = 0</code> was unexpected, because it is <strong><strong><mark style="background-color:#fcf84a" class="has-inline-color">weak behavior</mark></strong></strong>. In the code for the test, this result will be labelled as <strong><strong><mark style="background-color:rgba(0, 0, 0, 0);color:#fc801d" class="has-inline-color">interesting</mark></strong></strong>, meaning it is acceptable but noteworthy. The other listed results are expected and therefore will be labelled as <strong><mark style="background-color:rgba(0, 0, 0, 0);color:#5e5d5d" class="has-inline-color">acceptable</mark></strong>.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Let’s look at what happens when we run the test with LitmusKt. How often do we see weak behavior in one million tests?</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center"><img style="width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;" decoding="async"  src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/LitmusKt_interesting.png" ></p>



<p>The above screenshot shows that <strong><strong><strong><mark style="background-color:rgba(0, 0, 0, 0);color:#fc801d" class="has-inline-color">interesting</mark></strong></strong></strong> outcomes do occur, but that they are relatively rare, at less than five percent. To increase the frequency of finding these weak but tolerable outcomes, LitmusKt enables the user to apply different parameters to increase the number of complex interactions (see the paper for further details).</p>



<p>Now that we know how to write a test in LitmusKt, let’s look at the more technical details. Our team built a custom Kotlin/Native test runner from scratch because no solutions existed up until then. The test runner is built on techniques from other litmus testing tools, such as careful thread synchronization and CPU affinity control. We created a test runner so that the threads modify different states simultaneously many times over, significantly increasing the likelihood that a concurrent interaction occurs and weak behavior can be detected.</p>



<p>For Kotlin/JVM, we integrated the tool with the existing JCStress framework, as it is known to be successful in uncovering concurrency bugs in various JVM implementations. Despite some integration challenges, the end interface is seamless for the user.</p>



<p>To summarize, LitmusKt incorporates proven methods to maximize the frequency of rare behaviors and provides powerful reporting tools for manual and automated analysis. Users can also interact via a rich command-line interface, adjusting test parameters, durations, and system settings.</p>



<p>Considering all these features, has LitmusKt caught any Kotlin bugs? As we will see in the next section, it has.&nbsp;</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">LitmusKt and real code</h3>



<p>We applied LitmusKt and several litmus tests to analyze the behavior of Kotlin programs, therefore testing the results of the Kotlin compiler and looking for previously unknown issues. The possible outcomes here are:</p>



<ul>
<li><strong><strong><mark style="background-color:rgba(0, 0, 0, 0);color:#5e5d5d" class="has-inline-color">Acceptable</mark></strong></strong>: sequentially consistent outcomes</li>



<li><strong><strong><strong><mark style="background-color:rgba(0, 0, 0, 0);color:#fc801d" class="has-inline-color">Interesting</mark></strong></strong></strong>: weak but tolerable outcomes according to the semantics of the programming language</li>



<li><strong><mark style="background-color:rgba(0, 0, 0, 0);color:#f01b02" class="has-inline-color">Forbidden</mark></strong>: weak intolerable outcomes, indicating bugs</li>
</ul>



<p>In contrast to the Store Buffering Test above, this analysis includes two weak outcomes: one tolerable and one intolerable, where the latter outcome represents a bug. The testing results are shown in the following image, where ACC, INT, and FORB stand for <strong><strong><mark style="background-color:rgba(0, 0, 0, 0);color:#5e5d5d" class="has-inline-color">acceptable</mark></strong></strong>, <strong><strong><strong><mark style="background-color:rgba(0, 0, 0, 0);color:#fc801d" class="has-inline-color">interesting</mark></strong></strong></strong>, and <strong><strong><mark style="background-color:rgba(0, 0, 0, 0);color:#f01b02" class="has-inline-color">forbidden</mark></strong></strong>.&nbsp;</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center"><img style="width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;" decoding="async" src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/LitmusKt_analysis.png" ></p>



<p>We can see that there are a number of tests uncovering <strong><strong><strong><mark style="background-color:rgba(0, 0, 0, 0);color:#fc801d" class="has-inline-color">interesting</mark></strong></strong></strong> results, and one test in particular with <strong><strong><strong><mark style="background-color:rgba(0, 0, 0, 0);color:#f01b02" class="has-inline-color">forbidden</mark></strong></strong> </strong>results. The test abbreviated as UPUB in the table is <em>unsafe publication</em>. The forbidden results represent a situation where objects could be accessed before proper initialization, potentially causing rare and critical failures in production environments. The fact that memory-unsafe behavior could slip through in a memory-safe language like Kotlin demonstrates why <strong>systematic concurrency testing is essential</strong>.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Let’s look more closely at <em>unsafe publication</em>, shown in the code below,<em> </em>and what unexpected outcomes arose.</p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="generic" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">class IntHolder(val x: Int = 0)
 val UnsafePublication = litmusTest({
    object : LitmusIIOutcome() {
	var h : IntHolder? = null
    }
}) {
   thread { h = IntHolder() }
   thread { r1 = h?.x ?: -1 }
   spec { accept(0); accept(-1) }
   reset { h = null }
}</pre>



<p>In the code above, we can see a simple class <code>IntHolder</code> with a single integer. The shared state is a reference to this class. Then, we have two threads: one which is going to create a new class, and one which will try to read its variable.</p>



<p>The outcome of running the <em>unsafe publication</em> test was expected to be one of two scenarios:&nbsp;</p>



<ol>
<li>The class <code>IntHolder</code> is initialized —&gt; <code>0</code></li>



<li>The class <code>IntHolder</code> is not initialized —&gt; <code>-1</code></li>
</ol>



<p>The actual outcome of running the <em>unsafe publication</em> test with Kotlin 1.9 is shown in the following image. Any result which is not declared as interesting or acceptable is considered <strong><strong><strong><mark style="background-color:rgba(0, 0, 0, 0);color:#f01b02" class="has-inline-color">forbidden</mark></strong></strong></strong>.</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center"><img style="width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;" decoding="async" src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/LitmusKt_forbidden-1.png" ></p>



<p>Unexpectedly, garbage values could be read from uninitialized memory. A memory-safe language like Kotlin definitely should not let this happen. In other words, <strong>our team found a new compiler bug thanks to LitmusKt</strong>. Since identifying the bug, our team has already <a style="color:#6B57FF;" href="https://github.com/JetBrains/kotlin/commit/d2e0361b4e6de7e804c6c079e7195354cd77ced9" target="_blank" rel="noopener">fixed</a> and merged it. As of Kotlin 1.9.20 and later, this bug no longer occurs.&nbsp;</p>



<p>We found further issues while running <em>unsafe publication</em> with LitmusKt (see <a style="color:#6B57FF;" href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2501.07472" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the paper</a> for more details). As these are valuable insights for the Kotlin compiler, and after discussion with the Kotlin/Native development team, <a style="color:#6B57FF;" href="https://github.com/JetBrains/kotlin/commit/c409279a3833105caf9a4c18c479358c14293ad7" target="_blank" rel="noopener">LitmusKt is now embedded in the Kotlin CI/CD pipeline</a>.</p>



<p>In addition to the issues arising from running different tests, we discovered more noteworthy outcomes. The below image contains the partial code of a standard litmus test and the resulting outcomes.</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center"><img style="width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;" decoding="async" src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/LitmusKt_noweak_horiz.png" ></p>



<p>As can be seen in the above image, the test produces only three outcomes. So far, nothing crazy. The interesting bit happens when the code is slightly altered with semantically equivalent changes. That is, these changes theoretically should not result in any additional thread interactions. However, as the below image shows, another outcome actually does show up.</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center"><img style="width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;" decoding="async" src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/LitmusKt_semanticchange_horiz.png" ></p>



<p>This extra outcome, marked in pink in the above image, is actually a <strong><mark style="background-color:#fcf84a" class="has-inline-color">weak outcome</mark></strong>, as it cannot be achieved by interleaving execution of threads. We suspect that such behavior is caused by compiler optimizations. In the future, it might be worthwhile to combine compiler fuzzing (i.e., with random code mutations) with litmus testing to discover more edge cases.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Bringing order to Kotlin concurrency</h2>



<p>LitmusKt proves that even in the mayhem of concurrent programming, order can be found. By catching bugs that once slipped through the cracks of the Kotlin compiler, it has made multiplatform Kotlin development more reliable than ever.</p>



<p>With LitmusKt now part of Kotlin’s CI pipeline, every new compiler version benefits from systematic concurrency testing – ensuring that subtle memory model violations are caught before they reach developers.</p>



<p>We didn’t just build a tool; we established a new way to think about concurrency testing for multiplatform languages.</p>



<p>In short, LitmusKt:</p>



<ul>
<li>Brings automated, multiplatform litmus testing to Kotlin for the first time.</li>



<li>Uncovered and helped fix multiple concurrency bugs in Kotlin/Native.</li>



<li>Opened new possibilities for hybrid testing approaches that combine compiler fuzzing with concurrency analysis.</li>
</ul>



<p>LitmusKt is open-source and ready to help you explore, understand, and test the complex behaviors of concurrent programs across Kotlin’s many platforms.</p>


    <div class="buttons">
        <div class="buttons__row">
                                                <a href="https://github.com/Jetbrains-Research/litmuskt" class="btn " target="_blank" rel="noopener">Try LitmusKt on GitHub</a>
                                    </div>
    </div>







<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Further reading</strong></h2>



<p>Curious to explore the research or try out litmus testing on your own code? Check out these resources!</p>



<ul>
<li><a style="color:#6B57FF;" href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2501.07472" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Our paper</a> on LitmusKt by Denis Lochmelis, Evgenii Moiseenko, Yaroslav Golubev, and Anton Podkopaev in the <em>33rd ACM International Conference on the Foundations of Software Engineering </em>proceedings</li>
</ul>



<ul>
<li><a style="color:#6B57FF;" href="https://shipilev.net/#jmm" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Talks</a> by Aleksey Shipilëv on concurrency in the Java Memory Model</li>



<li>Our <a style="color:#6B57FF;" href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1134/S0361768821060050" target="_blank" rel="noopener">paper</a> (<a style="color:#6B57FF;" href="https://media.githubusercontent.com/media/anlun/publicFiles/master/papers/Moiseenko-al-Programming21-full.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">PDF</a>), A Survey of Programming Language Memory Models by Evgenii Moiseenko, Anton Podkopaev, and Dmitrii Koznov in <em>Programming and Computer Software</em>&nbsp;</li>



<li>A <a style="color:#6B57FF;" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=q0qW4uALSDA" target="_blank" rel="noopener">video</a> by Anton Podkopaev, one of our LitmusKt researchers, on problems, solutions, and directions for programming language memory models.</li>



<li>Weak memory consistency <a style="color:#6B57FF;" href="https://people.mpi-sws.org/~viktor/wmc/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">course</a> by Ori Lahav and Viktor Vafeiadis</li>



<li><a style="color:#6B57FF;" href="https://docs.oracle.com/javase/specs/jls/se8/html/jls-17.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Chapter</a> on Java Memory Model specification</li>



<li>LLVM Atomic Instructions and Concurrency <a style="color:#6B57FF;" href="https://llvm.org/docs/Atomics.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Guide</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Evaluating Kotlin in Real Projects</title>
		<link>https://blog.jetbrains.com/kotlin/2025/10/evaluating-kotlin-in-real-projects/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alyona Chernyaeva]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 14:56:06 +0000</pubDate>
		<featuredImage>https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Blog-Featured-1280x720-1-2.png</featuredImage>		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://blog.jetbrains.com/?post_type=kotlin&#038;p=653509</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Guest post by Urs Peter, Senior Software Engineer and JetBrains-certified Kotlin Trainer. For readers who’d like a more structured way to build Kotlin skills, Urs also leads the&#160;Kotlin Upskill Program at Xebia Academy. This is the second post in The Ultimate Guide to Successfully Adopting Kotlin in a Java-Dominated Environment, a series that follows how [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><em>Guest post by <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/urs-peter-70a2882/" target="_blank" data-type="link" data-id="https://bit.ly/urs-peter-linked-in" rel="noreferrer noopener">Urs Peter</a>, Senior Software Engineer and JetBrains-certified Kotlin Trainer. For readers who’d like a more structured way to build Kotlin skills, Urs also leads the&nbsp;</em><a href="https://academy.xebia.com/upskilling/kotlin-academy/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><em>Kotlin Upskill Program</em></a><em> at Xebia Academy.</em></p>



<p><em>This is the second post in </em><strong><em>The Ultimate Guide to Successfully Adopting Kotlin in a Java-Dominated Environment</em></strong><em>, a series that follows how Kotlin adoption grows among real teams, from a single developer’s curiosity to company-wide transformation.</em></p>



<p><strong>All parts in the series:</strong></p>



<ol>
<li><a href="https://blog.jetbrains.com/kotlin/2025/10/getting-started-with-kotlin-for-java-developers/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Getting Started With Kotlin for Java Developers</a></li>



<li><a href="https://blog.jetbrains.com/kotlin/2025/10/evaluating-kotlin-in-real-projects/" data-type="link" data-id="https://blog.jetbrains.com/kotlin/2025/10/evaluating-kotlin-in-real-projects/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Evaluating Kotlin in Real Projects</a></li>



<li><a href="https://blog.jetbrains.com/kotlin/2025/11/growing-kotlin-adoption-in-your-company/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Growing Kotlin Adoption in Your Company</a></li>



<li><a href="https://blog.jetbrains.com/kotlin/2025/11/helping-decision-makers-say-yes-to-kotlin/" data-type="link" data-id="https://blog.jetbrains.com/kotlin/2025/11/helping-decision-makers-say-yes-to-kotlin/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Helping Decision‑Makers Say Yes to Kotlin</a></li>
</ol>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>The Evaluation Stage: Beyond Kotlin as a Playground</strong></h2>



<p>Once you&#8217;re comfortable with Kotlin in tests, it&#8217;s time for a more substantial evaluation. You have two main approaches:</p>



<ol>
<li><a href="#1.-build-a-new-microservice/application-in-kotlin" data-type="link" data-id="https://blog.jetbrains.com/#1.-build-a-new-microservice/application-in-kotlin">Build a new microservice / application in Kotlin</a></li>



<li><a href="#2.-extend/convert-an-existing-java-application" data-type="link" data-id="https://blog.jetbrains.com/#2.-extend/convert-an-existing-java-application">Extend / convert an existing Java application</a></li>
</ol>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="1.-build-a-new-microservice/application-in-kotlin"><strong>1. Build a new microservice/application in Kotlin</strong></h3>



<p>Starting fresh with a new application or microservice provides the full Kotlin experience without the constraints of legacy code. This approach often provides the best learning experience and showcases Kotlin&#8217;s strengths most clearly.</p>



<div class="wp-block-columns is-layout-flex wp-container-3 wp-block-columns-is-layout-flex">
<div class="wp-block-column is-layout-flow wp-block-column-is-layout-flow" style="flex-basis:66.66%">
<p><strong>Pro tip</strong>: Get expert help during this stage. While developers are naturally confident in their abilities, avoiding early mistakes in the form of Java-ish Kotlin and a lack of Kotlin-powered libraries can save months of technical debt. </p>
</div>



<div class="wp-block-column is-layout-flow wp-block-column-is-layout-flow" style="flex-basis:33.33%">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img style="width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/unnamed-5.png" alt="" class="wp-image-646384"/></figure>
</div>
</div>



<p>This is how you can avoid common pitfalls when using Kotlin from a Java background:</p>



<p><em>Pitfall: Choosing a different framework from the one you use in Java.</em></p>



<p>Tip: <strong>Stick to your existing framework</strong>.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Most likely, you were using Spring Boot with Java, so use it with Kotlin too. Spring Boot Kotlin support is first-class, so there is no additional benefit in using something else. Moreover, you are forced to learn not only a new language but also a new framework, which only adds complexity without providing any advantage.<br><br><strong>Important</strong>: Spring interferes with Kotlin’s ‘inheritance by design’ principle, which requires you to explicitly mark classes open in order to extend them.<br><br>In order to avoid adding the open keyword to all Spring-related classes (like <code>@Configuration</code>, etc.), use the following build plugin: <a href="https://kotlinlang.org/docs/all-open-plugin.html#spring-support" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">https://kotlinlang.org/docs/all-open-plugin.html#spring-support</a>. If you create a Spring project with the well-known online <a href="https://start.spring.io/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Spring initializr tool</a>, this build plugin is already configured for you.</p>



<p><em>Pitfall: Writing Kotlin in a Java-ish way, relying on common Java APIs rather than Kotlin’s standard library:</em><em>&nbsp;</em></p>



<p>This list can be very long, so let’s focus on the most common pitfalls:</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><em>Pitfall 1: Using Java Stream rather than Kotlin Collections</em></h4>



<p>Tip: <strong>Always use Kotlin Collections.</strong></p>



<p>Kotlin Collections are fully interoperable with Java Collections, yet equipped with straightforward and feature-rich higher-order functions that make Java Stream obsolete.&nbsp;</p>



<p>As follows is an example that aims to pick the top 3 products by revenue (price * sold) grouped by product category:</p>



<p><strong>Java</strong></p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="java" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">record Product(String name, String category, double price, int sold){}

List&lt;Product> products = List.of(
           new Product("Lollipop", "sweets", 1.2, 321),
           new Product("Broccoli", "vegetable", 1.8, 5);

Map&lt;String, List&lt;Product>> top3RevenueByCategory =
       products.stream()
          .collect(Collectors.groupingBy(
                Product::category,
                Collectors.collectingAndThen(
                    Collectors.toList(),
                    list -> list.stream()
                              .sorted(Comparator.comparingDouble(
                                  (Product p) -> p.price() * p.sold())
                                   .reversed())
                                   .limit(3)
                                   .toList()
                       		)
          )
);</pre>



<p><strong>Kotlin</strong></p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">val top3RevenueByCategory: Map&lt;String, List&lt;Product>> =
   products.groupBy { it.category }
       .mapValues { (_, list) ->
           list.sortedByDescending { it.price * it.sold }.take(3)
       }</pre>



<p>Kotlin Java interop lets you work with Java classes and records as if they were native Kotlin, though you could also use a Kotlin (data) class instead.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><em>Pitfall 2: Keeping on using Java’s Optional.</em></h4>



<p>Tip: <strong>Embrace Nullable types</strong>.&nbsp;</p>



<p>One of the key reasons Java developers switch to Kotlin is for Kotlin’s built-in nullability support, which waves NullPointerExceptions goodbye. Therefore, try to use Nullable types only, no more Optionals. Do you still have Optionals in your interfaces? This is how you easily get rid of them by converting them to Nullable types:</p>



<p><strong>Kotlin</strong></p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">//Let’s assume this repository is hard to change, because it’s a library you depend on
class OrderRepository {
      //it returns Optional, but we want nullable types
      fun getOrderBy(id: Long): Optional&lt;Order> = …
}

//Simply add an extension method and apply the orElse(null) trick
fun OrderRepository.getOrderByOrNull(id: Long): Order? = 
                                    getOrderBy(id).orElse(null)

//Now enjoy the safety and ease of use of nullable types:

//Past:
 val g = repository.getOrderBy(12).flatMap { product ->
     product.goody.map { it.name }
}.orElse("No goody found")

//Future:
 val g = repository.getOrderByOrNull(12)?.goody?.name ?: "No goody found"</pre>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><em>Pitfall 3: Continuing to use static wrappers.</em></h4>



<p>Tip: <strong>Embrace Extension methods</strong>.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Extension methods give you many benefits:</p>



<ul>
<li>They make your code much more fluent and readable than wrappers.</li>



<li>They can be found with code completion, which is not the case for wrappers.</li>



<li>Because Extensions need to be imported, they allow you to selectively use extended functionality in a specific section of your application.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Java</strong></p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="java" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">//Very common approach in Java to add additional helper methods
public class DateUtils {
      public static final DateTimeFormatter DEFAULT_DATE_TIME_FORMATTER = 
           DateTimeFormatter.ofPattern("yyyy-MM-dd HH:mm:ss");

      public String formatted(LocalDateTime dateTime, 
		              DateTimeFormatter formatter) {
         return dateTime.format(formatter);
      }

      public String formatted(LocalDateTime dateTime) {
         return formatted(dateTime, DEFAULT_DATE_TIME_FORMATTER);
      }
}

//Usage
 formatted(LocalDateTime.now());
</pre>



<p><strong>Kotlin</strong></p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">val DEFAULT_DATE_TIME_FORMATTER: DateTimeFormatter = 
DateTimeFormatter.ofPattern("yyyy-MM-dd HH:mm:ss")

//Use an extension method, including a default argument, which omits the need for an overloaded method. 
fun LocalDateTime.asString(
   formatter: DateTimeFormatter = DEFAULT_DATE_TIME_FORMATTER): String = 
      this.format(formatter)

//Usage
LocalDateTime.now().formatted()</pre>



<p>Be aware that Kotlin offers top-level methods and variables. This implies that we can simply declare e.g. the <em><code>DEFAULT_DATE_TIME_FORMATTER</code></em> top level without the need to bind to an object like is the case in Java.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><em>Pitfall 4: Relying on (clumsily) Java APIs</em></h4>



<p>Tip: <strong>Use Kotlin’s slick counterpart.&nbsp;</strong></p>



<p>The Kotlin standard library uses extension methods to make Java libraries much more user-friendly, even though the underlying implementation is still Java. Almost all major third-party libraries and frameworks, like Spring, have done the same.</p>



<p><strong>Example standard library:</strong></p>



<p><strong>Java</strong></p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="java" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">String text;
try (
       var reader = new BufferedReader(
                  new InputStreamReader(new FileInputStream("out.txt"), 
            StandardCharsets.UTF_8))) {
   text = reader
            .lines()
            .collect(Collectors.joining(System.lineSeparator()));
}
System.out.println("Downloaded text: " +  text + "\n");</pre>



<p><strong>Kotlin</strong></p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">//Kotlin has enhanced the Java standard library with many powerful extension methods, like on java.io.*, which makes input stream processing a snap due to its fluent nature, fully supported by code completion

val text = FileInputStream("path").use {
             it.bufferedReader().readText()
           }
println("Downloaded text: $text\n");</pre>



<p><strong>Example Spring:</strong><br><strong>Java</strong></p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="java" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">final var books =  RestClient.create()
       .get()
       .uri("http://.../api/books")
       .retrieve()
       .body( new ParameterizedTypeReference&lt;List&lt;Book>>(){}); // ⇦ inconvenient ParameterizedTypeReference</pre>



<p><strong>Kotlin</strong></p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">import org.springframework.web.client.body
val books = RestClient.create()
   .get()
   .uri("http://.../api/books")
   .retrieve()
   .body&lt;List&lt;Book>>() //⇦ Kotlin offers an extension that only requires the type without the need for a ParameterizedTypeReference</pre>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><em>Pitfall 5: Using a separate file for each public class</em></h4>



<p>Tip: <strong>Combine related public classes in a single file.&nbsp;</strong></p>



<p>This allows you to get a good understanding of how a (sub-)domain is structured without having to navigate dozens of files.<br><br><strong>Java</strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img style="width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/unnamed-15.png" alt="" class="wp-image-647331"/></figure>



<p><strong>Kotlin</strong></p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">//For domain classes consider data classes - see why below
data class User(val email: String,
            //Use nullable types for safety and expressiveness
           val avatarUrl: URL? = null, 
           var isEmailVerified: Boolean)

data class Account(val user:User,
              val address: Address,
              val mfaEnabled:Boolean,
              val createdAt: Instant)

data class Address(val street: String,
              val city: String,
              val postalCode: String)</pre>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><em>Pitfall 6: Relying on the mutable programming paradigm</em></h4>



<p>Tip: <strong>Embrace immutability – the default in Kotlin</strong></p>



<p>The trend across many programming languages – including Java – is clear: immutability is winning over mutability.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The reason is straightforward: immutability prevents unintended side effects, making code safer, more predictable, and easier to reason about. It also simplifies concurrency, since immutable data can be freely shared across threads without the risk of race conditions.</p>



<p>That’s why most modern languages – Kotlin among them – either emphasize immutability by default or strongly encourage it. In Kotlin, immutability is the default, though mutability remains an option when truly needed.</p>



<p>Here’s a quick guide to Kotlin’s <strong>immutability power pack</strong>:</p>



<p>1. Use <code>val</code> over <code>var</code></p>



<p>Prefer <code>val</code> over <code>var</code>. IntelliJ IDEA will notify you if you used a <code>var</code>, for which a <code>val</code> could be used.&nbsp;</p>



<p>2. Use (immutable) data classes with <code>copy(...)</code></p>



<p>For domain-related classes, use <code>data</code> classes with <code>val</code>. Kotlin <code>data</code> classes are often compared with Java <code>records</code>. Though there is some overlap, <code>data</code> classes offer the killer feature <code>copy(...)</code>, whose absence makes transforming <code>record</code> – which is often needed in business logic – so tedious:</p>



<p><strong>Java</strong></p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="java" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">//only immutable state
public record Person(String name, int age) {
   //Lack of default parameters requires overloaded constructor
   public Person(String name) { 
       this(name, 0);
   }
   //+ due to lack of String interpolation
  public String sayHi() {
       return "Hello, my name is " + name + " and I am " + age + " years old.";
   }
}

//Usage
final var jack = new Person("Jack", 42);
jack: Person[name=Jack, age=5]

//The issue is here: transforming a record requires manually copying the identical state to the new instance ☹️
final var fred = new Person("Fred", jack.age());</pre>



<p><strong>Kotlin</strong></p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">//also supports mutable state (var)
data class Person(val name: String,
                  val age: Int = 0) {
  //string interpolation
  fun sayHi() = "Hi, my name is $name and I am $age years old."
}
val jack = Person("Jack", 42)
jack: Person(name=Jack, age=42)

//Kotlin offers the copy method, which, due to the ‘named argument’ feature, allows you to only adjust the state you want to change 😃
val fred = jack.copy(name = "Fred")
fred: Person(name=Fred, age=42)</pre>



<p>Moreover, use data classes for domain-related classes whenever possible. Their immutable nature ensures a safe, concise, and hassle-free experience when working with your application’s core.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>Tip: <strong>Prefer Immutable over Mutable Collections</strong></p>



<p>Immutable Collections have clear benefits regarding thread-safety, can be safely passed around, and are easier to reason about. Although Java collections offer some immutability features for Collections, their usage is dangerous because it easily causes exceptions at runtime:</p>



<p><strong>Java</strong></p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="java" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">List.of(1,2,3).add(4); //❌unsafe 😬! .add(...) compiles, but throws UnsupportedOperationException</pre>



<p><strong>Kotlin</strong></p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">//The default collections in Kotlin are immutable (read-only)
listOf(1,2,3).add(4);  //✅safe: does not compile

val l0 = listOf(1,2,3) 
val l1 = l0 + 4 //✅safe: it will return a new list containing the added element
l1 shouldBe listOf(1,2,3,4) //✅</pre>



<p>The same applies for using <code>Collections.<em>unmodifiableList(...)</em></code><em>, </em>which is not only unsafe, but also requires extra allocation:</p>



<p><strong>Java</strong></p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="java" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">class PersonRepo {
   private final List&lt;Person> cache = new ArrayList&lt;>();
   // Java – must clone or wrap every call
   public List&lt;Person> getItems() {
       return Collections.unmodifiableList(cache);   //⚠️extra alloc
   }
}

//Usage
personRepo.getItems().add(joe) //❌unsafe 😬! .add(...) can be called but throws UnsupportedOperationException</pre>



<p><strong>Kotlin</strong></p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">class PersonRepo {

//The need to type ‘mutable’ for mutable collections is intentional: Kotlin wants you to use immutable ones by default. But sometimes you need them:

   private val cache: MutableList&lt;Person> = mutableListOf&lt;Person>()

   fun items(): List&lt;Person> = cache //✅safe: though the underlying collection is mutable, by returning it as its superclass List&lt;...>, it only exposes the read-only interface

}

//Usage
personRepo.items().add(joe) //✅safe:😬! Does not compile</pre>



<p>When it comes to concurrency, immutable data structures, including collections, should be preferred. In Java, more effort is required with special Collections that offer a different or limited API, like <code>CopyOnWriteArrayList</code>. In Kotlin, on the other hand, the read-only <code>List&lt;...&gt;</code> does the job for almost all use cases.&nbsp;</p>



<p>If you need mutable, Thread-Safe Collections, Kotlin offers Persistent Collections (<code>persistentListOf(...)</code>, <code>persistentMapOf(...)</code>), which all share the same powerful interface.</p>



<p><strong>Java</strong></p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="java" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">ConcurrentHashMap&lt;String, Integer> persons = new ConcurrentHashMap&lt;>();
persons.put("Alice", 23);
persons.put("Bob",   21);

//not fluent and data copying going on
Map&lt;String, Integer> incPersons = new HashMap&lt;>(persons.size());
persons.forEach((k, v) -> incPersons.put(k, v + 1));

//wordy and data copying going on
persons
   .entrySet()
   .stream()
   .forEach(entry -> 
      entry.setValue(entry.getValue() + 1));</pre>



<p><strong>Kotlin</strong></p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">persistentMapOf("Alice" to 23, "Bob" to 21)
         .mapValues { (key, value) -> value + 1 } //✅same rich API like any other Kotlin Map type and not data copying going on</pre>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><em>Pitfall 7: Keeping on using builders (or even worse: trying to use Lombok)&nbsp;</em></h4>



<p>Tip: <strong>Use named arguments.</strong></p>



<p>Builders are very common in Java. Although they are convenient, they add extra code, are unsafe, and increase complexity. In Kotlin, they are of no use, as a simple language feature renders them obsolete: named arguments.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Java</strong></p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="java" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">public record Person(String name, int age) {

   // Builder for Person
   public static class Builder {
       private String name;
       private int age;

       public Builder() {}

       public Builder name(String name) {
           this.name = name;
           return this;
       }

       public Builder age(int age) {
           this.age = age;
           return this;
       }

       public Person build() {
           return new Person(name, age);
       }
   }
}

//Usage
new JPerson.Builder().name("Jack").age(36).build(); //compiles and succeeds at runtime

new JPerson.Builder().age(36).build(); //❌unsafe 😬: compiles but fails at runtime.</pre>



<p><strong>Kotlin</strong></p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">data class Person(val name: String, val age: Int = 0)

//Usage - no builder, only named arguments.
Person(name = "Jack") //✅safe: if it compiles, it always succeeds at runtime
Person(name = "Jack", age = 36) //✅</pre>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="2.-extend/convert-an-existing-java-application"><strong>2. Extend/convert an existing Java application</strong></h3>



<p>If you have no greenfield option for trying out Kotlin, <a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/help/idea/get-started-with-kotlin.html#add-kotlin-dependency" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">adding new Kotlin features or whole Kotlin modules to an existing Java codebase </a>is the way to go. Thanks to Kotlin&#8217;s seamless Java interoperability, you can write Kotlin code that looks like Java to Java callers. This approach allows for:</p>



<ul>
<li>Gradual migration without big-bang rewrites</li>



<li>Real-world testing of Kotlin in your specific context</li>



<li>Building team confidence with production Kotlin code</li>
</ul>



<p>Rather than starting <em>somewhere</em>, consider these different approaches:</p>



<p><strong>Outside-in:</strong></p>



<p>Start in the “leaf” section of your application, e.g. controller, batch job, etc. and then work your way towards the core domain. This will give you the following advantages:&nbsp;</p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Compile-time isolation</strong>: Leaf classes rarely have anything depending <em>on them</em>, so you can flip them to Kotlin and still build the rest of the system unchanged.</li>



<li><strong>Fewer ripple edits.</strong> A converted UI/controller can call existing Java domain code with almost no changes thanks to seamless interop.</li>



<li><strong>Smaller PRs, easier reviews.</strong> You can migrate file-by-file or feature-by-feature.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Inside-out:</strong></p>



<p>Starting at the core and then moving to the outer layers is often a riskier approach, as it compromises the advantages of the outside-in approach mentioned above. However, it is a viable option in the following cases:</p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Very small or self-contained core.</strong> If your domain layer is only a handful of POJOs and services, flipping it early may be cheap and immediately unlock idiomatic constructs (data class, value classes, sealed hierarchies).</li>



<li><strong>Re-architecting anyway.</strong> If you plan to refactor invariants or introduce DDD patterns (value objects, aggregates) while you migrate, it’s sometimes cleaner to redesign the domain in Kotlin first.</li>



<li><strong>Strict null-safety contracts.</strong> Putting Kotlin at the center turns the domain into a “null-safe fortress”; outer Java layers can still send null, but boundaries become explicit and easier to police.<br></li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Module by module</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>If your architecture is organized by functionality rather than layers, and the modules have a manageable size, converting them one by one is a good strategy.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Language features for converting Java to Kotlin</strong></p>



<p>Kotlin offers a variety of features – primarily annotations – that allow your Kotlin code to behave like native Java. This is especially valuable in hybrid environments where Kotlin and Java coexist within the same codebase.<br><strong>Kotlin</strong></p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">class Person @JvmOverloads constructor(val name: String,
                          var age: Int = 0) {
  companion object {

  @JvmStatic
  @Throws(InvalidNameException::class)
  fun newBorn(name: String): Person = if (name.isEmpty()) 
       throw InvalidNameException("name not set")
     else Person(name, 0)

   @JvmField
   val LOG = LoggerFactory.getLogger(KPerson.javaClass)
  }
}</pre>



<p><strong>Java</strong></p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="java" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">//thanks to @JvmOverloads an additional constructor is created, propagating Kotlin’s default arguments to Java
var john =  new Person("John");

//Kotlin automatically generates getters (val) and setters (var) for Java
john.setAge(23);
var name = ken.getName();

//@JvmStatic and @JvmField all accessing (companion) object fields and methods as statics in Java

//Without @JvmStatic it would be: Person.Companion.newBorn(...)
var ken =  Person.newBorn("Ken"); 

//Without @JvmField it would be: Person.Companion.LOG
Person.LOG.info("Hello World, Ken ;-)");

//@Throws(...) will put the checked Exception in the method signature 
try {
  Person ken =  Person.newBorn("Ken");
} catch (InvalidNameException e) {
  //…
}</pre>



<p><strong>Kotlin</strong></p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">@file:JvmName("Persons")
package org.abc

@JvmName("prettyPrint")

fun Person.pretty() =
      Person.LOG.info("$name is $age old")</pre>



<p><strong>Java</strong></p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="java" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">//@JvmName for files and methods makes accessing static fields look like Java: without it would be: PersonKt.pretty(...)
Persons.prettyPrint(ken)</pre>



<p><strong>IntelliJ IDEA’s Java to Kotlin Converter</strong></p>



<p>IntelliJ IDEA offers a Java to Kotlin Converter, so theoretically, the tool can do it for you. However, the resulting code is far from perfect, so use it only as a starting point. From there, convert it to a more Kotlin-esque representation. More on this topic will be discussed in the final section of this blog post series:<em> Success Factors for Large-Scale Kotlin Adoption.</em></p>



<p>Taking Java as a starting point will most likely make you write Java-ish Kotlin, which gives you some benefits, but will not unleash the power of Kotlin’s potential. Therefore, writing a new application is the approach I prefer.&nbsp;</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Next in the series</h3>



<p>This installment in our <em>Ultimate Guide to Successfully Adopting Kotlin in a Java-Dominated Environment</em> series of blog posts demonstrated how Kotlin experiments can evolve into production code. Our next post focuses on the human side of adoption: convincing your peers. It explains how to present clear, code-driven arguments, guide new developers, and create a small but lasting Kotlin community within your team.</p>


    <div class="about-author ">
        <div class="about-author__box">
            <div class="row">
                                                            <div class="about-author__box-img">
                            <img style="width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;" decoding="async" src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/a3f7-400o400o1-QYUavRYyARnAVJLCpM1m8M.webp" alt="" loading="lazy">
                        </div>
                                        <div class="about-author__box-text">
                                                    <h4>Urs Peter</h4>
                                                <p>Urs is a seasoned software engineer, solution architect, conference speaker, and trainer with over 20 years of experience in building resilient, scalable, and mission-critical systems, mostly involving Kotlin and Scala.</p>
<p>Besides his job as a consultant, he is also a passionate trainer and author of a great variety of courses ranging from language courses for Kotlin and Scala to architectural trainings such as Microservices and Event-Driven Architectures.</p>
<p>As a people person by nature, he loves to share knowledge and inspire and get inspired by peers on meetups and conferences. Urs is a JetBrains certified Kotlin trainer.</p>
                    </div>
                            </div>
        </div>
    </div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		                    <language>
                        <code><![CDATA[zh-hans]]></code>
                        <url>https://blog.jetbrains.com/zh-hans/kotlin/2025/10/evaluating-kotlin-in-real-projects/</url>
                    </language>
                	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Kodee’s Kotlin Roundup: Finally Back with News</title>
		<link>https://blog.jetbrains.com/kotlin/2025/10/kodees-kotlin-roundup-october-edition/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kodee]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 13:19:53 +0000</pubDate>
		<featuredImage>https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Blog-featured.png</featuredImage>		<category><![CDATA[news]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://blog.jetbrains.com/?post_type=kotlin&#038;p=653032</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[It’s been a while since you last heard from me – I know, I’ve been a busy bee! Between releases and launches, time just flew by. But I’ve got plenty of updates to share with you. Let’s start with some of the biggest highlights from September and October, and if you’re curious, scroll down for [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>It’s been a while since you last heard from me – I know, I’ve been a busy bee! Between releases and launches, time just flew by. But I’ve got plenty of updates to share with you. Let’s start with some of the biggest highlights from September and October, and if you’re curious, scroll down for more goodies you might’ve missed.</p>


            <div class="newsletter">
                            <h2>Kodee-Approved Spotlight</h2>
                                                            <article class="newsletter__post">
                                                                                    <img style="width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;" decoding="async" class="newsletter__post-img" src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/2.2.21-video.jpg" alt="What's new in Kotlin 2.2.21 (and 2.2.20!)">
                                                                            <div class="newsletter__post-text">
                                                            <h3>What&#8217;s New in Kotlin 2.2.21 (and 2.2.20!)</h3>
                                                        <p>Sebastian Aigner prepared a great video overview of <a href="https://github.com/JetBrains/kotlin/releases/tag/v2.2.20" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Kotlin 2.2.20</a> and <a href="https://github.com/JetBrains/kotlin/releases/tag/v2.2.21" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Kotlin 2.2.21</a> – and wow, there’s a lot to unpack! New dataflow checks allow more flexible when expressions than before, and contracts are getting an overhaul. Kotlin Multiplatform is promoting Kotlin for WebAssembly to the Beta stage, and Swift Export is now available out of the box in your KMP projects. Pretty impressive, right? Sit back, relax, and enjoy!</p>
                                                            <a href="https://youtu.be/QWpp5-LlTqA?si=f3NUtMM2RWXD92-V" class="btn" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Watch now</a>
                                                    </div>
                    </article>
                                    <article class="newsletter__post">
                                                                                    <img style="width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;" decoding="async" class="newsletter__post-img" src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/KT-social-BlogSocialShare-1280x720-1-1.png" alt="The Kotlin AI Stack: Build AI Agents With Koog, Code Smarter With Junie, and More">
                                                                            <div class="newsletter__post-text">
                                                            <h3>The Kotlin AI Stack: Build AI Agents With Koog, Code Smarter With Junie</h3>
                                                        <p>I know – everyone is talking about AI a lot these days, but hear me out, this one is worth the hype! Kotlin helps you build AI-powered apps and boosts your developer workflow with smart AI tools. Curious? Check out our blog post about the Kotlin AI stack.</p>
                                                            <a href="https://blog.jetbrains.com/kotlin/2025/09/the-kotlin-ai-stack-build-ai-agents-with-koog-code-smarter-with-junie-and-more/" class="btn" target="_blank">Explore the Kotlin AI stack</a>
                                                    </div>
                    </article>
                                    <article class="newsletter__post">
                                                                                    <img style="width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;" decoding="async" class="newsletter__post-img" src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/KT-social-BlogSocialShare-1280x720-1-1.png" alt="From Python to Kotlin: A Transition Worth Making">
                                                                            <div class="newsletter__post-text">
                                                            <h3>From Python to Kotlin: A Transition Worth Making – by Marcin Moskała</h3>
                                                        <p>Python is great for quick scripts and data analysis, but large codebases can be, well, tricky. The JVM, one of the fastest runtime platforms, makes Java nearly as efficient as C, but Java can feel a bit verbose at times. Kotlin, built on the same foundation, brings the speed, safety, and clarity modern developers love. Interested? Learn more in our latest blog post by Marcin Moskała, Kotlin instructor and founder of Kt. Academy, an official JetBrains partner.</p>
                                                            <a href="https://blog.jetbrains.com/kotlin/2025/10/from-python-to-kotlin-a-transition-worth-making/" class="btn" target="_blank">Read more</a>
                                                    </div>
                    </article>
                                    <article class="newsletter__post">
                                                                                    <img style="width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;" decoding="async" class="newsletter__post-img" src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Blog-Social-share-1280x720-1-2.png" alt="Getting Started With Kotlin for Java Developers">
                                                                            <div class="newsletter__post-text">
                                                            <h3>Getting Started With Kotlin for Java Developers – by Urs Peter</h3>
                                                        <p>Ever wondered how to bring Kotlin into a Java-heavy world? This guest post by Urs Peter, Senior Software Engineer and JetBrains-certified Kotlin Trainer, kicks off <i>The Ultimate Guide to Successfully Adopting Kotlin in a Java-Dominated Environment</i>. The series follows real teams on their Kotlin adoption journeys – from one curious developer to a company-wide shift. This first post is about where it all begins: that first spark and the small wins that make a big difference.</p>
                                                            <a href="https://blog.jetbrains.com/kotlin/2025/10/getting-started-with-kotlin-for-java-developers/" class="btn" target="_blank">Start your journey</a>
                                                    </div>
                    </article>
                                    <article class="newsletter__post">
                                                                                    <img style="width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;" decoding="async" class="newsletter__post-img" src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Wolt-case.jpg" alt="Wolt: A Kotlin for Server-Side Case Study">
                                                                            <div class="newsletter__post-text">
                                                            <h3>Wolt: A Kotlin for Server-Side Case Study</h3>
                                                        <p>Yes, that Wolt, operating in 30 countries with over 50 million users. In this new case study, Andrei Nevedomskii, Kotlin Competence Lead at Wolt, shares how Kotlin became a core part of their engineering culture. With over 150 engineers and just as many repositories, Wolt uses Ktor and Spring for flexibility, speed, and productivity. Want to see how they launch new services in mere minutes?</p>
                                                            <a href="https://youtu.be/puBXoKkQInE?si=vxocy6TirN0b57YA" class="btn" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Watch the full video</a>
                                                    </div>
                    </article>
                                    <article class="newsletter__post">
                                                                                    <img style="width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;" decoding="async" class="newsletter__post-img" src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/KT-social-BlogSocialShare-1280x720-2x.png" alt="Compose Multiplatform for web goes Beta">
                                                                            <div class="newsletter__post-text">
                                                            <h3>Compose Multiplatform for Web Goes Beta</h3>
                                                        <p>Big news for the Kotlin Multiplatform ecosystem – Compose Multiplatform for web is now in Beta. It’s no longer experimental, but ready for real-world use by early adopters. I’m so excited that you can now bring your existing Compose skills and coding patterns to the web with minimal effort, creating new apps or extending ones from mobile and desktop.</p>
                                                            <a href="https://blog.jetbrains.com/kotlin/2025/09/compose-multiplatform-1-9-0-compose-for-web-beta/" class="btn" target="_blank">Learn more</a>
                                                    </div>
                    </article>
                                    <article class="newsletter__post">
                                                                                    <img style="width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;" decoding="async" class="newsletter__post-img" src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/KM-social-BlogSocialShare-1280x720-1.png" alt="Kotlin Multiplatform Survey 2025">
                                                                            <div class="newsletter__post-text">
                                                            <h3>We Are Running Our Yearly Kotlin Multiplatform Survey </h3>
                                                        <p>Our yearly Kotlin Multiplatform survey is live! And no, it’s not just another survey – it gives us vital insights into how you use Kotlin Multiplatform and how recent updates affect your workflow. So, Kotlin devs, please take a few minutes to share your thoughts. You’ll not only make one purple fluffy creature very happy, but also help the team focus on what matters most.</p>
                                                            <a href="https://surveys.jetbrains.com/s3/KMP-Survey-2025-KN" class="btn" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Take the survey</a>
                                                    </div>
                    </article>
                                    <article class="newsletter__post">
                                                                                    <img style="width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;" decoding="async" class="newsletter__post-img" src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Blog-Featured-1280x720-1-2.png" alt="Crafting Your KotlinConf Proposal: Expert Tips to Help You Stand Out">
                                                                            <div class="newsletter__post-text">
                                                            <h3>Crafting Your KotlinConf Proposal: Expert Tips to Help You Stand Out</h3>
                                                        <p>We’re looking for talent! The KotlinConf 2026 Call for Speakers is in full swing, and if you haven’t submitted your session yet, now’s the time. Standing out can be tricky, so why not learn from those who actually review the proposals? ? We’ve gathered best practices and insider advice from JetBrains speakers, KotlinConf program committee members, and seasoned presenters.</p>
                                                            <a href="https://blog.jetbrains.com/kotlin/2025/10/crafting-your-kotlinconf-proposal-expert-tips/" class="btn" target="_blank">Learn from the experts</a>
                                                    </div>
                    </article>
                                    </div>
    


<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Where You Can Learn More:</h2>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://blog.jetbrains.com/kotlin/2025/09/ktor-roadmap-2025/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Ktor Roadmap and Previews</a></li>



<li><a href="https://blog.jetbrains.com/ai/2025/10/koog-0-5-0-is-out-smarter-tools-persistent-agents-and-simplified-strategy-design/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Koog 0.5.0 Is Out: Smarter Tools, Persistent Agents, and Simplified Strategy Design</a></li>



<li><a href="https://blog.jetbrains.com/ai/2025/10/koog-a2a-building-connected-ai-agents-in-kotlin/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Koog × A2A: Building Connected AI Agents in Kotlin </a></li>



<li><a href="https://blog.jetbrains.com/kotlin/2025/10/kotlin-multiplatform-contest-2026/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Build a Kotlin Multiplatform Project and Win a Trip to KotlinConf 2026 </a></li>



<li><a href="https://blog.jetbrains.com/amper/2025/10/amper-update-october-2025/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Amper Update, October 2025 – Compose Hot Reload and UX Improvements </a></li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">YouTube Highlights:</h2>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/1zY4_iDyFco?si=2ILixUSs9PxxH3Sb" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Discussing Kotlin Coroutines with Marcin Moskała | Talking Kotlin 141</a></li>



<li><a href="https://youtu.be/3IxDICQTutw?si=uPhFxR7cmDNqP7Xn" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">How Kotlin Server-Side Development Delivers Real Business Results for Worldline</a></li>



<li><a href="https://youtu.be/RpvP6k_YQto?si=8NcT2I3YuG7Bdhug" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">From Junior Developer to CEO: A Conversation with JetBrains CEO | KotlinConfersations&#8217;25</a></li>



<li><a href="https://youtu.be/TAtU7joTGaA?si=KgRAXhVD2HurwADX" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Your First AI Agent in Kotlin | Tutorial</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Getting Started With Kotlin for Java Developers</title>
		<link>https://blog.jetbrains.com/kotlin/2025/10/getting-started-with-kotlin-for-java-developers/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alyona Chernyaeva]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 10:51:33 +0000</pubDate>
		<featuredImage>https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Blog-Featured-1280x720-1-1.png</featuredImage>		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://blog.jetbrains.com/?post_type=kotlin&#038;p=652284</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Guest post by Urs Peter, Senior Software Engineer and JetBrains-certified Kotlin Trainer. For readers who’d like a more structured way to build Kotlin skills, Urs also leads the&#160;Kotlin Upskill Program at Xebia Academy. This post opens The Ultimate Guide to Successfully Adopting Kotlin in a Java-Dominated Environment, a series that follows how Kotlin adoption grows [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><em>Guest post by <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/urs-peter-70a2882/" target="_blank" data-type="link" data-id="https://bit.ly/urs-peter-linked-in" rel="noreferrer noopener">Urs Peter</a>, Senior Software Engineer and JetBrains-certified Kotlin Trainer. For readers who’d like a more structured way to build Kotlin skills, Urs also leads the&nbsp;</em><a href="https://academy.xebia.com/upskilling/kotlin-academy/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><em>Kotlin Upskill Program</em></a><em> at Xebia Academy.</em></p>



<p><em>This post opens </em><strong><em>The Ultimate Guide to Successfully Adopting Kotlin in a Java-Dominated Environment</em></strong><em>, a series that follows how Kotlin adoption grows among real teams, from a single developer’s curiosity to company-wide transformation.</em></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p class="has-text-align-left">                  “<em>You don’t flip a switch to ‘go Kotlin’.</em></p>



<p class="has-text-align-left">                  <em>You de-risk, you measure, you celebrate the wins,</em></p>



<p class="has-text-align-left">                   <em>and only then do you double down.</em>”</p>



<p>Adopting Kotlin in an established Java environment isn&#8217;t just a technical decision – it&#8217;s a journey that requires careful planning, strategic thinking, and most importantly, winning the hearts and minds of your peers.&nbsp;</p>



<p>After training over 1,000 developers and helping numerous organizations successfully transition to Kotlin, I&#8217;ve seen what works and what doesn&#8217;t. This guide will walk you through successful recipes for adopting Kotlin, which I have collected over time, from your first experimental playground to large-scale organizational transformation.</p>



<p>This is the journey this series will take you through:</p>



<ul>
<li><a href="#it-always-starts-with-a-spark,-initiated-by-you" data-type="link" data-id="https://blog.jetbrains.com/#it-always-starts-with-a-spark,-initiated-by-you">It Always Starts With a Spark, Initiated by You!</a></li>



<li><a href="#the-play-around-stage-start-small-–-with-tests">The Play Around Stage: Start Small – With Tests</a></li>



<li><a href="https://blog.jetbrains.com/kotlin/2025/10/evaluating-kotlin-in-real-projects/#the-evaluation-stage-beyond-kotlin-as-a-playground" target="_blank" data-type="link" data-id="https://blog.jetbrains.com/kotlin/2025/10/evaluating-kotlin-in-real-projects/#the-evaluation-stage-beyond-kotlin-as-a-playground" rel="noreferrer noopener">The Evaluation Stage: Beyond Kotlin as a Playground</a></li>



<li><a href="https://blog.jetbrains.com/kotlin/2025/11/growing-kotlin-adoption-in-your-company-2/#spread-the-word-win-the-hearts-and-minds-of-your-fellow-developers" target="_blank" data-type="link" data-id="https://blog.jetbrains.com/kotlin/2025/11/growing-kotlin-adoption-in-your-company/#spread-the-word-win-the-hearts-and-minds-of-your-fellow-developers" rel="noreferrer noopener">Spread the Word: Win the Hearts &amp; Minds of Your Fellow Developers</a></li>



<li><a href="https://blog.jetbrains.com/kotlin/2025/11/helping-decision-makers-say-yes-to-kotlin/#persuading-management-building-the-business-case-for-kotlin" target="_blank" data-type="link" data-id="https://blog.jetbrains.com/kotlin/2025/11/helping-decision-makers-say-yes-to-kotlin/#persuading-management-building-the-business-case-for-kotlin" rel="noreferrer noopener">Persuading Management: Building the Business Case for Kotlin</a></li>



<li>Success Factors for Large-Scale Kotlin Adoption</li>



<li>To Kotlin or Not to Kotlin: What Kind of Company Do You Want to Be?</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>It Always Starts With a Spark, Initiated by You!</strong></h2>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img style="width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/unnamed-12.png" alt="It Always Starts With a Spark, Initiated by You!" class="wp-image-647072"/></figure>



<p><em>Why take the effort to switch to Kotlin? Why not just stick with Java and move on?&nbsp;</em></p>



<p>The answer depends on numerous factors. While the data clearly shows Kotlin&#8217;s advantages across multiple domains, the decision isn&#8217;t purely technical. Subjectivity (“I like my language because I like it”) and skepticism towards something new, which is generally a good thing, play an important role.&nbsp;</p>



<p>However, the evolution of programming languages shows that our preferences and needs change over time. Crucially, each new generation of languages incorporates fresh paradigms – (null)-safety, concise and light-weight syntax, functions as first class citizens, rich standard library, async concurrency, multiplatform support, generative-AI friendly, etc. – that give developers and organizations a decisive advantage.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Without this natural progression, we’d still be coding everything in COBOL or another archaic language, unable to meet today’s demands. Evolution is therefore not optional; it’s built into the history of our industry.</p>



<p>For this evolution to take root inside a company, though, it takes more than technical merit. It requires enablers – people willing to explore, advocate, and show the value of these new paradigms in practice. In my experience, three types of engineers typically become these catalysts for Kotlin adoption:</p>



<ol>
<li><strong>The pragmatic, productivity-focused Java Engineer</strong>: Experienced developers who see Java as a tool, not a religion. They&#8217;re always looking for better ways to get the job done faster.</li>



<li><strong>The quality-minded, modern language enthusiast</strong>: Engineers who prioritize readable, concise, and maintainable code. These are often the same people who would have moved to Scala in the past.</li>



<li><strong>Junior Developers</strong>: Juniors who ask the simple but powerful question: &#8220;Why should I use Java if I can use Kotlin?&#8221; Without the baggage of years of Java experience, Kotlin is often a no-brainer for them.</li>
</ol>



<p>To which group do you belong?&nbsp;</p>



<p>These early adopters ignite the first stage. But how do you start? Read on… ;-)&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>The Play Around Stage: Start Small – With Tests</strong></h2>



<p>You&#8217;ve heard about Kotlin and want to give it a try without committing to it immediately.&nbsp;</p>



<p>So the first thing you need is a developer tool where your very first Kotlin seeds can be planted. Here are some options:</p>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://play.kotlinlang.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">https://play.kotlinlang.org/</a> is a great online playground, simply type and run Kotlin code not only on the JVM but also for various other platforms (JS, WASM, etc.).<img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-647084" style="width: 650px;; width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;" src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/unnamed-13.png" alt="Kotlin Playground"> </li>
</ul>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://kotlinlang.org/docs/kotlin-notebook-overview.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Kotlin Notebook</a> is a powerful feature for IntelliJ IDEA that allows you to easily import dependencies, execute code, and even work with data, draw graphs, etc. Here is an example that shows how easy it is to do a REST call with Spring’s RestClient:<img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-647095" style="width: 650px;; width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;" src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/unnamed-11.png" alt="Kotlin Notebook"></li>
</ul>



<ul>
<li>IntelliJ IDEA has first-class support for Kotlin. This is no surprise, since JetBrains is the maker of Kotlin, and a large portion of IntelliJ IDEA is written in it. So, to start using Kotlin in <a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/help/idea/get-started-with-kotlin.html#add-kotlin-dependency" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">IntelliJ IDEA</a> – even in your existing Java project – is a breeze:
<ul>
<li>For <a href="https://kotlinlang.org/docs/maven.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Maven</a>, simply configure the <code>kotlin-maven-plugin</code> and the Kotlin standard library <code>kotlin-stdlib</code>.</li>



<li>For <a href="https://kotlinlang.org/docs/gradle-configure-project.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Gradle</a>, you configure the kotlin plugin.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>



<p>…and off you go!</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/unnamed-14.png" alt="" class="wp-image-647106" style="aspect-ratio:1.1216216216216217;width:320px;height:auto; width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;"/></figure>



<ul>
<li>And there’s more! JetBrains recently released the Kotlin Language Server, bringing a full-featured Kotlin development experience to other IDEs beyond IntelliJ IDEA – such as VS Code. Check it out: <a href="https://github.com/Kotlin/kotlin-lsp" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">https://github.com/Kotlin/kotlin-lsp</a>&nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<p>Now, you can write Kotlin in your favorite development environment. How can you evaluate the language in a real-world context with minimal impact and maximal insights? In the test suite of an existing Java project!&nbsp;</p>



<p>Learn how to test Java code using Kotlin and JUnit <a href="https://kotlinlang.org/docs/jvm-test-using-junit.html" target="_blank" data-type="link" data-id="https://kotlinlang.org/docs/jvm-test-using-junit.html" rel="noreferrer noopener">in this tutorial</a>.</p>



<p>This safe and realistic approach to experimenting with Kotlin offers several advantages:</p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Low Risk</strong>: Tests don&#8217;t affect production code.</li>



<li><strong>Learning Opportunity</strong>: You can explore the language features in a familiar context.</li>



<li><strong>Gradual Introduction</strong>: Team members can get comfortable with Kotlin syntax without pressure.</li>
</ul>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Tips</strong></h3>



<ol>
<li>Try Kotest + MockK: to immediately feel the expressiveness of Kotlin’s testing DSLs (Domain-Specific Language), like the feature-rich assertions (<code>shouldHaveSize(...)</code>, infix (<code>value shouldBe 1</code>), etc.</li>



<li>Use the concise and powerful Kotlin Collections rather than Java Streams.</li>



<li>Play with various language features like Nullable types, destructuring, immutability (<code>val</code>, <code>data classes</code>), expression constructs (<code>when</code>, <code>try-catch</code>, <code>if else</code>), and many more.</li>
</ol>



<p>This is what you get:</p>



<p><strong>Java</strong></p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="java" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">@Test
void shouldGetAverageRating() {
   when(productRepository.findAll()).thenReturn(products);

   Map&lt;String, Double> ratings = productService.averageRatings();

   assertAll(
           () -> assertThat(ratings).hasSize(4),
           () -> assertEquals(ratings, products
                   .stream()
                   .collect(Collectors.groupingBy(
                           Product::getName,
                           Collectors.flatMapping(
                                   p -> p.getRatings()
                                    .stream()
                                    .mapToDouble(Integer::doubleValue)
                                    .boxed(),   
                              Collectors.averagingDouble(Double::doubleValue)
                           )))
           )
   );
   verify(productRepository).findAll();

}
</pre>



<p><strong>Kotlin</strong></p>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">@Test
fun `should get average rating`() { //descriptive tests using ``
   every { productRepository.findAll() } returns products

   val ratings = productService.averageRatings()

   assertSoftly(ratings) { 		//powerful testing DSLs (Kotest)
       shouldHaveSize(4)
       this shouldBe productRepository.findAll()
           .groupBy { it.name }   			//concise collections
           .mapValues { (_, products) -> 		//destructuring
                  products.flatMap { it.ratings }.average() }
   }
    verify { productRepository.findAll() }
}</pre>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Next in the series</h3>



<p>Kotlin adoption usually starts with one person exploring and a few tests proving useful. Those first moments of discovery naturally lead to something larger: evaluating Kotlin in a real project.</p>



<p>The next post in this series will describe that stage and explain how to test Kotlin in production environments.</p>


    <div class="about-author ">
        <div class="about-author__box">
            <div class="row">
                                                            <div class="about-author__box-img">
                            <img style="width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;" decoding="async" src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/a3f7-400o400o1-QYUavRYyARnAVJLCpM1m8M.webp" alt="" loading="lazy">
                        </div>
                                        <div class="about-author__box-text">
                                                    <h4>Urs Peter</h4>
                                                <p>Urs is a seasoned software engineer, solution architect, conference speaker, and trainer with over 20 years of experience in building resilient, scalable, and mission-critical systems, mostly involving Kotlin and Scala.</p>
<p>Besides his job as a consultant, he is also a passionate trainer and author of a great variety of courses ranging from language courses for Kotlin and Scala to architectural trainings such as Microservices and Event-Driven Architectures.</p>
<p>As a people person by nature, he loves to share knowledge and inspire and get inspired by peers on meetups and conferences. Urs is a JetBrains certified Kotlin trainer.</p>
                    </div>
                            </div>
        </div>
    </div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		                    <language>
                        <code><![CDATA[zh-hans]]></code>
                        <url>https://blog.jetbrains.com/zh-hans/kotlin/2025/10/getting-started-with-kotlin-for-java-developers/</url>
                    </language>
                	</item>
		<item>
		<title>From Python to Kotlin: A Transition Worth Making</title>
		<link>https://blog.jetbrains.com/kotlin/2025/10/from-python-to-kotlin-a-transition-worth-making/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alina Dolgikh]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 11:29:44 +0000</pubDate>
		<featuredImage>https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/KT-social-BlogFeatured-1280x720-1-2.png</featuredImage>		<category><![CDATA[industry-trends]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[kotlin]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[python]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[news]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://blog.jetbrains.com/?post_type=kotlin&#038;p=594572</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This article was written by an external contributor. When it comes to writing short scripts or CRUDs, Python is a great choice. With its rich ecosystem and broad adoption, it can be easily used to scrape some data or to perform data analysis. However, maintaining a large codebase in Python can be very problematic. Python&#8217;s [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><em>This article was written by an external contributor.</em></p>


    <div class="about-author ">
        <div class="about-author__box">
            <div class="row">
                                                            <div class="about-author__box-img">
                            <img style="width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;" decoding="async" src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/image-96.png" alt="" loading="lazy">
                        </div>
                                        <div class="about-author__box-text">
                                                    <h4>Marcin Moskała</h4>
                                                <p>Marcin is a highly experienced developer and Kotlin instructor, founder of Kt. Academy, an official JetBrains partner specializing in Kotlin training. He is also a Google Developers Expert and a well-known contributor to the Kotlin community. Marcin is the author of several widely recognized books, including <em data-start="450" data-end="468">Effective Kotlin</em>, <em data-start="470" data-end="489" data-is-only-node="">Kotlin Coroutines</em>, <em data-start="491" data-end="510">Functional Kotlin</em>, <em data-start="512" data-end="529">Advanced Kotlin</em>, <em data-start="531" data-end="550">Kotlin Essentials</em>, and <em data-start="556" data-end="589">Android Development with Kotlin</em>.</p>
<p><a href="https://kt.academy/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Website</a></p>
                    </div>
                            </div>
        </div>
    </div>



<p>When it comes to writing short scripts or CRUDs, Python is a great choice. With its rich ecosystem and broad adoption, it can be easily used to scrape some data or to perform data analysis. However, maintaining a large codebase in Python can be very problematic.</p>



<p>Python&#8217;s dynamic typing and mutable nature, while offering flexibility for rapid development, may present additional considerations in larger codebases. Event-loop-based coroutines can be tricky and may lead to<a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Kotlin/comments/1lsnytm/from_python_to_kotlin_why_we_rewrote_our_scraping/" target="_blank" data-type="link" data-id="https://www.reddit.com/r/Kotlin/comments/1lsnytm/from_python_to_kotlin_why_we_rewrote_our_scraping/" rel="noreferrer noopener"> subtle issues in practice</a> . Finally, the single-threaded and dynamically typed nature of this language makes Python code significantly less efficient than most of its modern competitors.&nbsp;</p>



<p>JVM is one of the fastest runtime platforms, making Java nearly as efficient as C. <a href="https://benchmarksgame-team.pages.debian.net/benchmarksgame/fastest/python.html" target="_blank" data-type="link" data-id="https://benchmarksgame-team.pages.debian.net/benchmarksgame/fastest/python.html" rel="noreferrer noopener">Most benchmarks show that Python code is 10 to 100 times slower than Java code</a>. One <a href="https://greenlab.di.uminho.pt/wp-content/uploads/2017/10/sleFinal.pdf" target="_blank" data-type="link" data-id="https://greenlab.di.uminho.pt/wp-content/uploads/2017/10/sleFinal.pdf" rel="noreferrer noopener">big research paper</a> compared the performance of multiple languages and showed that Python code is 74x more CPU-expensive than code in C, where Java code is only 1.8x more expensive. However, due to its long-standing commitment to backward compatibility, Java can feel verbose for certain tasks. Kotlin, building on that same ecosystem and offering the same efficiency, gives you access to a powerful typesystem, with modern language features focused on performance and developer ergonomics.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Those are the key reasons we can hear from companies or teams that decide to switch from Python to Kotlin. The Kotlin YouTube channel recently published <a href="https://youtu.be/puBXoKkQInE?si=wt32jWKXBy9eXbFw" target="_blank" data-type="link" data-id="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=puBXoKkQInE" rel="noreferrer noopener">Wolt’s success story</a>, but that is only one voice among many. Kotlin is an all-around sensible choice for a range of projects, as it shares many similarities with Python. At the same time, Kotlin offers better performance, safety, and a much more powerful concurrency model. Let’s see those similarities and differences in practice.&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Similarities between Python and Kotlin</h2>



<p>When teaching Kotlin to both Python and Java developers, I was often surprised to discover that many Kotlin features are more frequently reported as intuitive by Python developers than their Java counterparts. Both languages offer concise syntax. Let&#8217;s compare some very simple use cases in both languages:</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"></h4>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">val language = "Kotlin"
println("Hello from $language")
// prints "Hello from Kotlin"

val list = listOf(1, 2, 3, 4, 5)
for (item in list) {
  println(item)
}
// prints 1 2 3 4 5 each in a new line

fun greet(name: String = "Guest") {
  println("Hello, $name!")
}
greet() // prints "Hello, Guest!"</pre>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="python" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">language = "Python"
print(f"Hello from {language}")
# prints "Hello from Python"

list = [1, 2, 3, 4, 5]
for item in list:
  print(item)
# prints 1 2 3 4 5 each in a new line

def greet(name="Guest"):
  print(f"Hello, {name}!")
greet()  # prints "Hello, Guest!"</pre>



<p>At first glance, there are only minor syntactic differences. Kotlin presents features well-known to Python developers, like string interpolation, concise loops, and default parameters. However, even in this simple example, we can see some advantages that Kotlin has over Python. All properties are statistically typed, so <code>language</code> is of type <code>String</code>, and <code>list</code> is of type <code>List&lt;Int&gt;</code>. That not only allows for low-level optimizations, but it also brings enhanced safety and better IDE support. All variables in the code above are also defined as immutable, so we cannot accidentally change their values. To change them, we would need to use <code>var</code> instead of <code>val</code>. The same goes for the list I used in this snippet – it is immutable, so we cannot accidentally change its content. To create a mutable list, we would need to use <code>mutableListOf</code> and type it as<code> MutableList&lt;Int&gt;</code>. This strong distinction between mutable and immutable types is a great way to avoid accidental changes, which are often the source of bugs in Python programs.</p>



<p>There are other advantages of Kotlin over Python that are similarly apparent in the above example. Python&#8217;s default arguments are static, so changing them influences all future calls. This is a well-known source of very sneaky bugs in Python programs. Kotlin&#8217;s default arguments are evaluated at each call, so they are safer.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Kotlin</strong></h4>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">fun test(list: MutableList&lt;Int> = mutableListOf()) {
  list.add(1)
  println(list)
}
test() // prints [1]
test() // prints [1]
test() // prints [1]</pre>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Python</h4>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="python" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">def test(list=[]):
  list.append(1)
  print(list)

test()  # prints [1]
test()  # prints [1, 1]
test()  # prints [1, 1, 1]</pre>



<p>Let&#8217;s talk about classes. Both languages support classes, inheritance, and interfaces. To compare them, let&#8217;s look at a simple data class in both languages:</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Kotlin</strong></h4>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">data class Post(
  val id: Int,
  val content: String,
  val publicationDate: LocalDate,
  val author: String? = null
)
val post = Post(1, "Hello, Kotlin!", LocalDate.of(2024, 6, 1))
println(post) // prints Post(id=1, content=Hello, Kotlin!, publicationDate=2024-06-01, author=null)</pre>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Python</h4>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="python" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">@dataclass
class Post:
  id: int
  content: str
  publication_date: date
  author: Optional[str] = None
    
post = Post(1, "Hello, Python!", datetime.date(2024, 6, 1))
print(post)  # prints Post(id=1, content='Hello, Python!', publication_date=datetime.date(2024, 6, 1), author=null)</pre>



<p>Kotlin has built-in support for data classes, which automatically allows such objects to be compared by value, destructured, and copied. Python requires an additional decorator to achieve similar functionality. This class is truly immutable in Kotlin, and thanks to static typing, it requires minimal memory. Outside of that, both implementations are very similar. Kotlin has built-in support for nullability, which in Python is expressed with the <code>Optional</code> type from the <code>typing</code> package.</p>



<p>Now, let&#8217;s define a repository interface and its implementation in both languages. In Kotlin, we can use Spring Data with coroutine support, while in Python, we can use SQLAlchemy with async support. Notice that in Kotlin, there are two kinds of properties: Those defined inside a bracket are constructor parameters, while those defined within braces are class properties. So in <code>SqlitePostRepository</code>, <code>crud</code> is expected to be passed in the constructor. The framework we use will provide an instance of <code>PostCrudRepository</code>, which is generated automatically by Spring Data.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Kotlin</strong></h4>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">interface PostRepository {
  suspend fun getPost(id: Int): Post?
  suspend fun getPosts(): List&lt;Post>
  suspend fun savePost(content: String, author: String): Post
}

@Service
class SqlitePostRepository(
  private val crud: PostCrudRepository
) : PostRepository {
  override suspend fun getPost(id: Int): Post? = crud.findById(id)

  override suspend fun getPosts(): List&lt;Post> = crud.findAll().toList()

  override suspend fun savePost(content: String, author: String): Post =
      crud.save(Post(content = content, author = author))
}

@Repository
interface PostCrudRepository : CoroutineCrudRepository&lt;Post, Int>

@Entity
data class Post(
  @Id @GeneratedValue val id: Int? = null,
  val content: String,
  val publicationDate: LocalDate = LocalDate.now(),
  val author: String
)</pre>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Python</h4>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="python" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">class PostRepository(ABC):
  @abstractmethod
  async def get_post(self, post_id: int) -> Optional[Post]:
      pass

  @abstractmethod
  async def get_posts(self) -> List[Post]:
      pass

  @abstractmethod
  async def save_post(self, content: str, author: str) -> Post:
      pass
    
class SqlitePostRepository(PostRepository):
  def __init__(self, session: AsyncSession):
      self.session = session

  async def get_post(self, post_id: int) -> Optional[Post]:
      return await self.session.get(Post, post_id)  

  async def get_posts(self) -> List[Post]:
      result = await self.session.execute(select(Post))
      return result.scalars().all()

  async def save_post(self, content: str, author: str) -> Post:
      post = Post(content=content, author=author)
      self.session.add(post)
      await self.session.commit()
      await self.session.refresh(post)
      return post

class Post(Base):
  __tablename__ = "posts"
  id: Mapped[int] = Column(Integer, primary_key=True, index=True)
  content: Mapped[str] = Column(String)
  publication_date: Mapped[date] = Column(Date, default=date.today)
  author: Mapped[str] = Column(String)</pre>



<p>Those implementations are very similar in many ways, and the key differences between them result from choices made by the frameworks, not the languages themselves. Python, due to its dynamic nature, encourages the use of untyped objects or dictionaries; however, such practices are generally discouraged in modern times. Both languages provide numerous tools for libraries to design effective APIs. On the JVM, these languages often depend on annotation processing, whereas in Python, decorators are more common. Kotlin leverages a mature and well-developed Spring Boot ecosystem, but it also offers lightweight alternatives such as Ktor or Micronaut. Python has Flask and FastAPI as popular lightweight frameworks, and Django as a more heavyweight framework.</p>



<p>In a backend application, we also need to implement services, which are classes that implement business logic. They often do some collection or string processing. Kotlin provides a comprehensive standard library with numerous useful functions for processing collections and strings. All those functions are named and called in a very consistent way. In Python, we can make nearly all transformations available in Kotlin, but to do so, we need to use many different kinds of constructs. In the code below, I needed to use top-level functions, methods on lists, collection comprehensions, or even classes from the <code>collections</code> package. Those constructs are not very consistent, some of them are not very convenient, and are not easily discoverable. You can also see that complicated notation for defining lambda expressions in Python harms collection processing APIs. Collection and string processing in Kotlin is much more pleasant and productive.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Kotlin</strong></h4>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">class PostService(
  private val repository: PostRepository
) {
  suspend fun getPostsByAuthor(author: String): List&lt;Post> =
      repository.getPosts()
          .filter { it.author == author }
          .sortedByDescending { it.publicationDate }

  suspend fun getAuthorsWithPostCount(): Map&lt;String?, Int> =
      repository.getPosts()
          .groupingBy { it.author }
          .eachCount()

  suspend fun getAuthorsReport(): String =
      getAuthorsWithPostCount()
          .toList()
          .sortedByDescending { (_, count) -> count }
          .joinToString(separator = "n") { (author, count) ->
              val author = author ?: "Unknown"
              "$author: $count posts"
          }
          .let { "Authors Report:n$it" }
}</pre>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Python</h4>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="python" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">class PostService:
  def __init__(self, repository: "PostRepository") -> None:
      self.repository = repository

  async def get_posts_by_author(self, author: str) -> List[Post]:
      posts = await self.repository.get_posts()
      filtered = [post for post in posts if post.author == author]
      sorted_posts = sorted(
          filtered,
          key=lambda p: p.publication_date,
          reverse=True
      )
      return sorted_posts

  async def get_authors_with_post_count(self) -> Dict[Optional[str], int]:
      posts = await self.repository.get_posts()
      counts = Counter(p.author for p in posts)
      return dict(counts)

  async def get_authors_report(self) -> str:
      counts = await self.get_authors_with_post_count()
      items = sorted(counts.items(), key=lambda kv: kv[1], reverse=True)
      lines = [
          f"{(author if author is not None else 'Unknown')}: {count} posts"
          for author, count in items
      ]
      return "Authors Report:n" + "n".join(lines)</pre>



<p>Before we finish our comparison, let’s complete our example backend application by defining a controller that exposes our service through HTTP. Until now, I have used Spring Boot, which is the most popular framework for Kotlin backend development. This is how it can be used to define a controller:</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Kotlin</strong></h4>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">@Controller
@RequestMapping("/posts")
class PostController(
   private val service: PostService
) {
   @GetMapping("/{id}")
   suspend fun getPost(@PathVariable id: Int): ResponseEntity&lt;Post> {
       val post = service.getPost(id)
       return if (post != null) {
           ResponseEntity.ok(post)
       } else {
           ResponseEntity.notFound().build()
       }
   }

   @GetMapping
   suspend fun getPostsByAuthor(@RequestParam author: String): List&lt;Post> =
       service.getPostsByAuthor(author)

   @GetMapping("/authors/report")
   suspend fun getAuthorsReport(): String =
       service.getAuthorsReport()
}</pre>



<p>However, we noticed that many Python developers prefer a lighter and simpler framework, and their preferred choice for such functionality is Ktor. Ktor allows users to define a working application in just a couple of lines of code. This is a complete Ktor Server application that implements a simple in-memory text storage (it requires no other configuration or dependencies except Ktor itself):</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Kotlin</strong></h4>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">fun main() = embeddedServer(Netty, port = 8080) {
   routing {
       var value = ""
       get("/text") {
           call.respondText(value)
       }
       post("/text") {
           value = call.receiveText()
           call.respond(HttpStatusCode.OK)
       }
   }
}.start(wait = true)
</pre>



<p>I hope that this comparison helped you see both the key similarities and differences between Python and Kotlin. As we’ve seen, Kotlin has many features that are very intuitive for Python developers. At the same time, Kotlin offers many improvements over Python, especially in terms of safety. It has a powerful static type system that prevents many common bugs, built-in support for immutability, and a very rich and consistent standard library.</p>



<p>To summarize, I believe it’s fair to say that both languages are very similar in many ways, but Kotlin brings a number of improvements – some small, some big. In addition, Kotlin offers some unique features that are not present in Python, the biggest one probably being a concurrency model based on coroutines.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">kotlinx.coroutines vs. Python asyncio</h2>



<p>The most modern approach to concurrency in Kotlin and Python is based on coroutines. In Python, the most popular library for this purpose is <code>asyncio</code>, while in Kotlin, there is the Kotlin <code>kotlinx.coroutines</code> library. Both libraries can start lightweight asynchronous tasks and await their completion. However, there are some important differences between them.</p>



<p>Let&#8217;s start with the hallmark feature of <code>kotlinx.coroutines</code>: first-class support for structured concurrency. Let&#8217;s say that you implement a service like SkyScanner, which searches for the best flight offers. Now, let&#8217;s suppose a user makes a search, which results in a request or the opening of a WebSocket connection to our service. Our service needs to query multiple airlines to return the best offers. Let&#8217;s then suppose that this user left our page soon after searching. All those requests to airlines are now useless and likely very costly, because we have a limited number of ports available to make requests. However, implementing explicit cancellation of all those requests is very hard. Structured concurrency solves that problem. With kotlinx.coroutines, every coroutine started by a coroutine is its child, and when the parent coroutine is cancelled, all its children are cancelled too. This way, our cancellation is automatic and reliable.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img style="width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/image-7.png" alt="" class="wp-image-647589"/><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Once the user leaves the screen, all processes and ports get cancelled. For the above graphic, I used the free icons <a href="https://www.flaticon.com/free-icon/close-eyes_18543033" data-type="link" data-id="https://www.flaticon.com/free-icon/close-eyes_18543033" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Close eyes by Iconic Panda</a> and <a href="https://www.flaticon.com/free-icon/landing-page_8901502" data-type="link" data-id="https://www.flaticon.com/free-icon/landing-page_8901502" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Landing page by Design Circle</a></figcaption></figure>



<p>However, structured concurrency goes even further. If getting a resource requires loading two other resources asynchronously, an exception in one of those two resources will cancel the other one too. This way, kotlinx.coroutines ensures that we use our resources in the most efficient way. In Python, <code>asyncio</code> introduced <code>TaskGroup</code> in version 3.11, which offers some support for structured concurrency, but it is far from what kotlinx.coroutines offer, and it requires explicit usage.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Kotlin</strong></h4>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">suspend fun fetchUser(): UserData = coroutineScope {
  // fetchUserDetails is cancelled if fetchPosts fails
  val userDetails = async { api.fetchUserDetails() }
  // fetchPosts is cancelled if fetchUserDetails fails
  val posts = async { api.fetchPosts() }
  UserData(userDetails.await(), posts.await())
}</pre>



<p>The second important difference is thread management. In Python, <code>asyncio</code> runs all tasks on a single thread. Notice that this is not utilizing the power of multiple CPU cores, and it is not suitable for CPU-intensive tasks. Using kotlinx.coroutines, coroutines can typically run on a thread pool (by default as big as the number of CPU cores). This way, coroutines better utilize the power of modern hardware. Of course, coroutines can also run on a single thread if needed, which is quite common in client applications.</p>



<p>Another big advantage of coroutines is their testing capabilities. kotlinx.coroutines provides built-in support for testing asynchronous code over a predetermined simulated timeframe, removing the need to wait while the code is tested in real time. This way, we can test asynchronous code in a deterministic way, without any flakiness. We can also easily simulate all kinds of scenarios, like different delays from dependent services. In Python, testing asynchronous code is possible using third-party libraries, but this method is not as powerful and convenient as with coroutines.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Kotlin</strong></h4>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">@Test
fun `should fetch data asynchronously`() = runTest {
  val api = mockk&lt;Api> {
      coEvery { fetchUserDetails() } coAnswers {
          delay(1000)
          UserDetails("John Doe")
      }
      coEvery { fetchPosts() } coAnswers {
          delay(1000)
          listOf(Post("Hello, world!"))
      }
  }
  val useCase = FetchUserDataUseCase(api)
  val userData = useCase.fetchUser()
  assertEquals("John Doe", userData.user.name)
  assertEquals("Hello, world!", userData.posts.single().title)
  assertEquals(1000, currentTime)
}</pre>



<p>Finally, kotlinx.coroutines offer powerful support for reactive streams through the <code>Flow</code> type. It is perfect for representing websockets or streams of events. <code>Flow</code> processing can be easily transformed using operators consistent with collection processing. It also supports backpressure, which is essential for building robust systems. Python has <code>async generators</code>, which can be used to represent streams of data, but they are not as powerful and convenient as <code>Flow</code>.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Kotlin</strong></h4>



<pre class="EnlighterJSRAW" data-enlighter-language="kotlin" data-enlighter-theme="" data-enlighter-highlight="" data-enlighter-linenumbers="" data-enlighter-lineoffset="" data-enlighter-title="" data-enlighter-group="">fun notificationStatusFlow(): Flow&lt;NotificationStatus> =
  notificationProvider.observeNotificationUpdate()
      .distinctUntilChanged()
      .scan(NotificationStatus()) { status, update ->
          status.applyNotification(update)
      }
      .combine(
          userStateProvider.userStateFlow()
      ) { status, user ->
          statusFactory.produce(status, user)
      }</pre>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Performance comparison</h2>



<p>One of the key benefits of switching from Python to Kotlin is performance. Python applications can be fast when they use optimized native libraries, but Python itself is not the fastest language. As a statically typed language, Kotlin can be compiled to optimized bytecode that runs on the JVM platform, which is a highly optimized runtime. In consequence, Kotlin applications are typically faster than Python applications.</p>



<p>Kotlin applications also use fewer resources. One reason for this is Kotlin’s more efficient memory management (a consequence of static typing). Another reason is structured concurrency, which ensures that resources are cancelled when they are no longer needed.&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Interoperability</h2>



<p>Kotlin is fully interoperable with Java. This means that Kotlin applications can use everything from the rich Java ecosystem. Everything that can be used in Java can easily be used in Kotlin as well (see <a href="https://kotlinlang.org/docs/mixing-java-kotlin-intellij.html" target="_blank" data-type="link" data-id="https://kotlinlang.org/docs/mixing-java-kotlin-intellij.html" rel="noreferrer noopener">interoperability guide</a>).&nbsp;</p>



<p>It is also possible to bridge between Kotlin and Python using libraries like JPype or Py4J. Nowadays, some libraries support further interoperability, like <a href="https://github.com/guimauvedigital/zodable" target="_blank" data-type="link" data-id="https://github.com/guimauvedigital/zodable" rel="noreferrer noopener">zodable</a>, which allows generating Zod schemas from Kotlin data classes.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Summary</h2>



<p>I love Kotlin and I love Python. I’ve used both languages extensively throughout my career. In the past, Python had many clear advantages over Kotlin, such as a richer ecosystem, more libraries, and scripting capabilities. In some domains, like artificial intelligence, I still find Python to be a better choice. However, for backend development, Kotlin is clearly the better option today. It offers similar conciseness and ease of use as Python, but it is faster, safer, and scales better. If you consider switching from Python to Kotlin for your backend development, it is a transition worth making.</p>



<style>
  /*.enlighter-l-kotlin { background: #fff !important; }*/
  /* Let Gutenberg Columns handle layout; no floats */
  /*.EnlighterJSRAW.float-left,
  .EnlighterJSRAW.float-right { float: none !important; }*/
</style>
<style>.enlighter-l-kotlin {
    background: #fff !important;
}
body .is-layout-flex {
    align-items: flex-start;
    display: grid;
    grid-template-columns: repeat(2, 1fr);
}
body .is-layout-flex>div {
    height: 100%;
}
body .is-layout-flex>div>div {
    height: 100%;
}

@media (max-width: 1024px){
	body .is-layout-flex {
		display: block;
	}
}
</style>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Koog 0.5.0 Is Out: Smarter Tools, Persistent Agents, and Simplified Strategy Design</title>
		<link>https://blog.jetbrains.com/ai/2025/10/koog-0-5-0-is-out-smarter-tools-persistent-agents-and-simplified-strategy-design/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Daniela Bentrup]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 07:19:48 +0000</pubDate>
		<featuredImage>https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/JB-social-BlogFeatured-1280x720-1-6.png</featuredImage>		<product ><![CDATA[kotlin]]></product>
		<category><![CDATA[news]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ai]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ai-agents]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://blog.jetbrains.com/?post_type=ai&#038;p=651225</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[We recently released Koog 0.5.0, introducing full Agent2Agent (A2A) protocol support, which makes it easier than ever to build systems of interconnected AI agents in Kotlin. But A2A is just the beginning. Koog 0.5.0 brings a host of improvements that make agents more persistent, tools smarter, and strategy design more intuitive. Let’s dive into the [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>We recently released<a href="https://github.com/JetBrains/koog/releases/tag/0.5.0" target="_blank" rel="noopener"> Koog 0.5.0</a>, introducing full <a href="https://blog.jetbrains.com/ai/2025/10/koog-a2a-building-connected-ai-agents-in-kotlin/">Agent2Agent (A2A) protocol support</a>, which makes it easier than ever to build systems of interconnected AI agents in Kotlin.</p>



<p>But A2A is just the beginning. Koog 0.5.0 brings a host of improvements that make agents more persistent, tools smarter, and strategy design more intuitive. Let’s dive into the highlights.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">💡 Non-graph API for strategies</h2>



<p>Koog 0.5.0 introduces a <a href="https://github.com/JetBrains/koog/pull/560" target="_blank" rel="noopener">non-graph API</a> for defining agent strategies. You can now create and modify agent strategies directly in Kotlin, without working with graphs. The new non-graph API keeps most of Koog’s core features, including state management and history compression, so you can prototype custom strategies faster.&nbsp;</p>



<p>You can now streamline your development cycle. Start simple with the out-of-the-box AIAgent using the default strategy. Then, experiment with the non-graph API to quickly test and find the best configuration for your task through straightforward code. Once you’re ready, scale it into a graph workflow to take full advantage of persistence for maximum reliability, as well as nested event tracing for deeper insights to build and test strategies more efficiently.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">🔁 Agent persistence and checkpointing improvements</h2>



<p>Complex AI workflows often depend on <a href="https://github.com/JetBrains/koog/pull/856" target="_blank" rel="noopener">persistence</a> – the ability to save and restore state without losing context or causing unintended side effects. Since we introduced persistence in Koog 0.4.0, we’ve <a href="https://github.com/JetBrains/koog/pull/856" target="_blank" rel="noopener">continued to build on it</a> to make agent state management much more reliable and flexible.</p>



<p>The new RollbackToolRegistry enables agents to undo side effects from tool calls when checkpointing, ensuring that rollbacks don’t leave your environment in an inconsistent state.</p>



<p>You can now also toggle between full state-machine persistence and message history persistence, giving you control over how much of the agent’s internal state to preserve.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">⚒️ Tool API enhancements</h2>



<p>Tools are the backbone of Koog’s agent capabilities. This release refines the <a href="https://github.com/JetBrains/koog/pull/791" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Tool API</a> to make tool development and integration smoother.</p>



<p>Tool descriptors are now automatically generated for class-based tools across all platforms. With this update, defining tools on multiplatform works just as smoothly as on the JVM, removing redundant setup and keeping your Tool API definitions concise and consistent.</p>



<p>With improvements to subgraphWithTask and subgraphWithVerification, finishTools is no longer required, and neither is the SubgraphResult type. You can now specify any input type, output type (including primitive types), task, tools, and models, and everything works automatically. There’s no more boilerplate – Koog infers and generates it all for you.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">👋 Introducing AIAgentService</h2>



<p>Managing multiple agents is now easier with the new AIAgentService. It allows you to run and manage multiple AI agents as single-use, state-managed services.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">⚖️ New components and smarter interactions</h2>



<p>Koog 0.5.0 also introduces new components that enhance reasoning and control in agent systems.&nbsp;</p>



<p><a href="https://github.com/JetBrains/koog/pull/866" target="_blank" rel="noopener">LLM as a judge</a> is a new component that uses large language models to evaluate outputs or guide decision-making processes.</p>



<p>In version 0.5.0, we’ve added a <a href="https://github.com/JetBrains/koog/pull/829" target="_blank" rel="noopener">strategy</a> for iterative tool calling with structured outputs. This makes it much easier to obtain typed results from any agent without having to write custom code.&nbsp;</p>



<p><a href="https://github.com/JetBrains/koog/pull/747" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Streaming now supports tool calls</a>, allowing the use of tools while receiving results from an LLM on the fly. With this update, front-end integrated agents can now stream partial outputs to the user interface while still invoking tools as needed.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Wrapping up</h2>



<p>Koog 0.5.0 isn’t just about connecting agents – it’s about empowering them to be smarter, more persistent, and easier to design. Whether you’re experimenting with lightweight strategies, managing long-lived agent sessions, or creating sophisticated toolchains, this release brings significant improvements across the board.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">✨ Try Koog 0.5.0</h2>



<p>If you’re building agents that need to be more connected, persistent, and easier to design, Koog 0.5.0 is the right choice. Explore the <a href="https://docs.koog.ai/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">docs</a>, build systems of multiple AI agents, and experiment faster while still benefiting from Koog’s advanced features.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">🤝 Your contributions make a difference</h2>



<p>We’d like to take this opportunity to extend a huge thank-you to the entire community! Your feedback, issue reports, and pull requests have been invaluable for the development of Koog!</p>



<p>A special shoutout to this release’s top contributors:</p>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/dosier" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Stan</a> – refactored the streaming API to support tool calls.</li>



<li><a href="https://github.com/siarhei-luskanau" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Siarhei Luskanau</a> – added the iOS target and enabled web support for demo-compose-app.</li>



<li><a href="https://github.com/ptitjes" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Didier Villevalois</a> – added an option to dynamically adjust context window sizes for Ollama.</li>



<li><a href="https://github.com/rubencagnie" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ruben Cagnie</a> – implemented support for the tool-calling strategy in structured output.</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Build a Kotlin Multiplatform Project and Win a Trip to KotlinConf 2026</title>
		<link>https://blog.jetbrains.com/kotlin/2025/10/kotlin-multiplatform-contest-2026/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ksenia Shneyveys]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 13:29:03 +0000</pubDate>
		<featuredImage>https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Blog-Featured-1280x720-1-3.png</featuredImage>		<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[news]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[contest]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://blog.jetbrains.com/?post_type=kotlin&#038;p=647355</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This year’s Kotlin Multiplatform Contest for students and recent graduates is open. Build a project using KMP, and it could take you to KotlinConf 2026 in Munich, Germany! Whether you are already exploring Kotlin Multiplatform or just curious about how far you can take shared Kotlin code, seize the chance to challenge yourself, stand out, [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>This year’s <a href="https://jb.gg/f7vo0v" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Kotlin Multiplatform Contest</a> for students and recent graduates is open. Build a project using KMP, and it could take you to KotlinConf 2026 in Munich, Germany!</p>



<p>Whether you are already exploring Kotlin Multiplatform or just curious about how far you can take shared Kotlin code, seize the chance to challenge yourself, stand out, and be part of the Kotlin community’s biggest event.</p>



<p align="center"><a class="ek-link jb-download-button" title="Join the contest" href="https://jb.gg/f7vo0v" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Join the contest</a></p>



<p>Kotlin Multiplatform lets you create apps for Android, iOS, desktop, web, and server – all from a single codebase. We’ll support you in a <a href="https://slack-chats.kotlinlang.org/c/kotlin-multiplatform-contest" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">dedicated Slack channel</a> where you can ask questions, share progress, and meet fellow participants.</p>



<p>This year, you can explore Kotlin for AI-powered apps and optionally add intelligent features to your projects. Check out our <a href="https://kotlinlang.org/docs/kotlin-ai-apps-development-overview.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Kotlin AI examples</a> to see how.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Prizes</h2>



<ul>
<li>The creators of the top three projects will win a trip to KotlinConf 2026 in Munich, Germany, taking place May 21–22, 2026. This will include travel, accommodation, exclusive swag, and a spotlight on the KotlinConf, Kotlin, and Kotlin Foundation social media and public channels, as well as at the event itself.</li>



<li>All authors of valid entries will receive Kotlin souvenirs and a warm welcome to the community.</li>



<li>All prizes are proudly sponsored by the <a href="https://kotlinfoundation.org" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Kotlin Foundation</a>.</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Dates</h2>



<p>Contest opens: September 15, 2025</p>



<p>Submission deadline: January 12, 2026</p>



<p>Winners announced: January 22, 2026</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">How to enter</h2>



<ol>
<li>Join the <a href="https://slack-chats.kotlinlang.org/c/kotlin-multiplatform-contest" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">#kotlin-multiplatform-contest</a> channel on the Kotlinlang Slack workspace.<br>Stay up to date, ask questions, and get support from the community and Kotlin experts.</li>



<li><a href="https://kotlinconf.com/contest-rules/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Review the rules</a> and eligibility criteria. Make sure your submission meets the eligibility and technical requirements.</li>



<li>Build your project using Kotlin Multiplatform.</li>



<li>Submit your entry:
<ul>
<li>Upload your project to GitHub, including a detailed README with installation instructions and feature descriptions for all supported platforms.</li>



<li>Consider including a short screencast (three to five minutes long) demonstrating your project’s main features in action. This will help the jury quickly understand your project and evaluate its functionality and creative merit.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>



<p align="center"><a class="ek-link jb-download-button" title="Submit your project" href="https://jb.gg/z1tir1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Submit your project</a></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Resources</h2>



<p><a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/help/kotlin-multiplatform-dev/get-started.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Kotlin Multiplatform official documentation</a></p>



<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLlFc5cFwUnmyL2O0OaTYPfmOwODlLIeX9" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Kotlin Multiplatform Hits</a> – YouTube playlist</p>



<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5_W5YKPShZ4" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Compose Multiplatform</a> – video tutorial</p>



<p><a href="https://github.com/joreilly/PeopleInSpace" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">PeopleInSpace</a> – sample KMP projects</p>



<p><a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/help/kotlin-multiplatform-dev/multiplatform-samples.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">More samples of multiplatform projects</a></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Previous years’ winners</h2>



<p>Meet the developers who impressed us in previous years with their creativity and skill. Check out <a href="https://youtube.com/playlist?list=PLlFc5cFwUnmzJm4IRyfainQpYhpZ9kvYP&amp;si=xPqo_NANLlVOE-zx" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">this video playlist</a> featuring interviews with the previous winners from 2024 and 2023.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="KMP Contest" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/videoseries?list=PLlFc5cFwUnmzJm4IRyfainQpYhpZ9kvYP" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Join the community</h2>



<p>Participating in the Kotlin Multiplatform Contest is a chance to learn and connect. Join the <a href="https://slack-chats.kotlinlang.org/c/kotlin-multiplatform-contest" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Slack channel</a> to meet other students and Kotlin experts.</p>



<p>Take the leap – show us what you can do!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Crafting Your KotlinConf Proposal: Expert Tips to  Help You Stand Out</title>
		<link>https://blog.jetbrains.com/kotlin/2025/10/crafting-your-kotlinconf-proposal-expert-tips/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Daria Voronina]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 16:26:27 +0000</pubDate>
		<featuredImage>https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Blog-Featured-1280x720-1-2.png</featuredImage>		<category><![CDATA[news]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[events]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[kotlinconf]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tips]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://blog.jetbrains.com/?post_type=kotlin&#038;p=647268</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Thinking about sharing your Kotlin expertise on the big stage? KotlinConf is the premier event for all things Kotlin, and getting a talk accepted for inclusion in the conference is a fantastic way to contribute to the community and elevate your profile. However, submitting a talk proposal, especially for the first time, can feel daunting. [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Thinking about sharing your Kotlin expertise on the big stage? <a href="https://kotlinconf.com/" target="_blank" data-type="link" data-id="https://kotlinconf.com/" rel="noreferrer noopener">KotlinConf</a> is the premier event for all things Kotlin, and getting a talk accepted for inclusion in the conference is a fantastic way to contribute to the community and elevate your profile. However, submitting a talk proposal, especially for the first time, can feel daunting. With so many brilliant minds around, how do you give your proposal the best shot at being accepted?</p>



<p>In this post, we’ll share some ways to make your submission stand out, combining best practices for conference proposals with insider advice from JetBrains speakers, KotlinConf program committee members, and experienced presenters.</p>



<p>The tips are tailored to KotlinConf in particular, but most of these ideas are applicable to any developer conference.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">1. Make sure your title is clear and compelling</h2>



<p>You never get a second chance to make a first impression, and your talk’s title is your earliest opportunity to capture attention. Reviewers and attendees alike may decide whether to read further based solely on those first few words.</p>


    <div class="about-author ">
        <div class="about-author__box">
            <div class="row">
                                                            <div class="about-author__box-img">
                            <img style="width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;" decoding="async" src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Untitled-design-2.png" alt="" loading="lazy">
                        </div>
                                        <div class="about-author__box-text">
                                                    <h4>Pamela Hill. Developer Advocate, KotlinConf Program Committee member, KotlinConf speaker</h4>
                                                <p><a href="https://x.com/pamelaahill" target="_blank">X</a>, <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/pamelaahill.bsky.social" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Bluesky</a>, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/pamelaahill/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">LinkedIn</a></p>
<p><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">A carefully-selected title can make all the difference! Audience members often lack the time or attention span to read more than the title when deciding whether to attend a talk. Prefer clarity over a catchy or fun title that doesn’t give a good idea of what the talk is about in a nutshell.</span></i></p>
                    </div>
                            </div>
        </div>
    </div>



<p>Choose a title that communicates your topic in plain terms, hints at the level, and makes the benefit to the audience obvious.</p>



<div style="background-color: #f1f6fe; margin-bottom: 2px; padding: 5px; margin-right: 0%; text-align: left; min-height: px;">
<p><i><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cTfHRUSDnS0" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><em>Your Voice Belongs Here: Creating Compelling KotlinConf Proposals</em></a></i> is a supportive and practical livestream for people from underrepresented groups in tech – whether you&#8217;re preparing for your first talk or have speaking experience and want to take the next step onto a bigger stage like KotlinConf. Join Pamela Hill and Cheuk Ting Ho, seasoned speakers, CFP writers, and friendly program committee members, as they share what makes a proposal stand out, how to shape your Kotlin journey into a strong submission, and what reviewers are really looking for. Watch the livestream recording.</p>
</div>
<p></p>



<p align="center"><a class="ek-link jb-download-button" title="Watch now" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cTfHRUSDnS0" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Watch now</a></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">2. Tell a story with your abstract – with the audience in mind</h2>



<p>Crafting a great talk is not just about presenting information – it’s also about storytelling. Think of your proposal as a promise to provide a valuable learning experience wrapped in a story that makes it engaging.</p>


    <div class="about-author ">
        <div class="about-author__box">
            <div class="row">
                                                            <div class="about-author__box-img">
                            <img style="width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;" decoding="async" src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/T0288D531-U014J262P1A-41f465128ee6-512.jpeg" alt="" loading="lazy">
                        </div>
                                        <div class="about-author__box-text">
                                                    <h4>Sebastian Sellmair. Software Developer, KotlinConf speaker</h4>
                                                <p><a href="https://x.com/Sellmair" target="_blank">X</a>, <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/sellmair.dev" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Bluesky</a>, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@s.sellmair" target="_blank" rel="noopener">YouTube</a></p>
<p><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Talking at KotlinConf is a great experience and a huge achievement for any Kotlin developer. While choosing a great title, having highly polished animations, and curating high-quality memes might enhance your talk, the most important thing is having a story worth telling. Do you have something novel and technically interesting to present? Can you break down a topic in a way that is engaging and truly fun? Can you inspire fellow developers?</span></i></p>
                    </div>
                            </div>
        </div>
    </div>



<p>Your abstract should explain what you’ll cover, what the attendees will gain, and why your talk matters. Reviewers don’t need a full script, but they do need a clear, detailed impression of your talk.</p>


    <div class="about-author ">
        <div class="about-author__box">
            <div class="row">
                                                            <div class="about-author__box-img">
                            <img style="width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;" decoding="async" src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/T0288D531-U05RAPGGJAK-8766042aed05-512.png" alt="" loading="lazy">
                        </div>
                                        <div class="about-author__box-text">
                                                    <h4>Márton Braun. Developer Advocate, KotlinConf Program Committee member, KotlinConf speaker</h4>
                                                <p><a href="https://x.com/zsmb13" target="_blank">X</a>, <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/zsmb.co" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Bluesky</a>, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/zsmb13/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">LinkedIn</a></p>
<p><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">While we don’t need a full script for your talk as the abstract, we’re also unlikely to accept a talk where the abstract is just a single sentence. Two or three paragraphs are usually enough to provide meaningful detail.</span></i></p>
                    </div>
                            </div>
        </div>
    </div>



<p>Think of your abstract as a preview, not a transcript – just enough detail to show the value and flow of your talk.</p>



<p align="center"><a class="ek-link jb-download-button" title="Submit your session" href="https://jb.gg/l1dymy" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Submit your session</a></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">3. Start with the problem and build anticipation</h2>



<p>When writing your proposal, set the stage by outlining the challenge or pain point your talk addresses. Create curiosity before giving the solution. This builds anticipation and helps the audience connect with your topic.</p>


    <div class="about-author ">
        <div class="about-author__box">
            <div class="row">
                                                            <div class="about-author__box-img">
                            <img style="width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;" decoding="async" src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/T0288D531-U03B9EX5MNY-68f44def26a8-512.jpeg" alt="" loading="lazy">
                        </div>
                                        <div class="about-author__box-text">
                                                    <h4>Jodie Burchell. Developer Advocate and Data Scientist</h4>
                                                <p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/jodieburchell/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">LinkedIn</a>, <a href="https://fosstodon.org/@t_redactyl" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Mastodon</a>, <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/t-redactyl.bsky.social" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Bluesky</a></p>
<p><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Hook your audience by telling them the problem you&#8217;re going to be solving. People love mystery books for a reason, and that&#8217;s because they build up a bit of suspense before they jump into the solution. A great proposal will do the same thing.</span></i></p>
                    </div>
                            </div>
        </div>
    </div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">4. Think like an attendee: What&#8217;s their takeaway?</h2>



<p>The best proposals start with the audience. Instead of asking, <em>“</em>What do I want to present?<em>”</em>, consider what the attendees will learn and why they will find it valuable.</p>


    <div class="about-author ">
        <div class="about-author__box">
            <div class="row">
                                                            <div class="about-author__box-img">
                            <img style="width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;" decoding="async" src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/1FqLye0HTHxz.jpeg" alt="" loading="lazy">
                        </div>
                                        <div class="about-author__box-text">
                                                    <h4>Svetlana Isakova. Team Lead in Kotlin Developer Advocacy, KotlinConf Program Committee member, KotlinConf speaker </h4>
                                                <p><a href="https://x.com/sveta_isakova" target="_blank">X</a></p>
<p><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">When submitting a talk, think like an attendee: Would you want to sit through this? What’s in it for the audience? That’s why we ask about key takeaways. What do you want people to learn, try, do, or feel inspired by?</span></i></p>
                    </div>
                            </div>
        </div>
    </div>



<p>Be precise with key takeaways. Avoid vague statements like “You’ll learn best practices.” Instead, be concrete and specific.</p>



<p>Here are a few examples from KotlinConf 2025 talks:</p>



<ul>
<li>“Learn how native dependencies interact, how they are loaded, and the unexpected complexities of the native world.” (<a href="https://youtu.be/n0LpCCv3VEY?si=UJ1zXMJx7FwSniWL" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><em>Dependencies and Kotlin/Native</em></a> | Tadeas Kriz).</li>
</ul>



<ul>
<li>“You&#8217;ll learn how to effectively use built-in tools, recognize problematic patterns, and implement proven optimization strategies.” (<a href="https://youtu.be/QTX5_JV4TVU?si=7kpUPi3wopjC7HLV" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><em>Taming Asynchronous Beasts: Debugging and Performance Tuning in a Coroutine World</em></a> | Marcin Moskała).</li>
</ul>



<ul>
<li>“We&#8217;ll learn how KMP provides a unified framework for code sharing and execution across various platforms to solve the challenge of different codebases targeting different runtimes.” (<a href="https://youtu.be/OuX5325yq_I?si=LpT4Cs3aF7mwRMy9" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><em>Kotlin Multiplatform&#8217;s Cross-Platform Brilliance at Norway&#8217;s 377-Year-Old National Postal Service</em></a> | Anshika Koul)</li>
</ul>



<p>Specific takeaways not only strengthen your proposal for reviewers but also make your talk more attractive to attendees when the schedule is published.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">5. Make it Kotlin-centric</h2>



<p>KotlinConf focuses on Kotlin itself and its ecosystem. Reviewers look for proposals that highlight Kotlin’s features, multiplatform capabilities, or language design, or relevant tools from the ecosystem.</p>


    <div class="about-author ">
        <div class="about-author__box">
            <div class="row">
                                                            <div class="about-author__box-img">
                            <img style="width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;" decoding="async" src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/T0288D531-U05RAPGGJAK-8766042aed05-512.png" alt="" loading="lazy">
                        </div>
                                        <div class="about-author__box-text">
                                                    <h4>Márton Braun. Developer Advocate, KotlinConf Program Committee member, KotlinConf speaker</h4>
                                                <p><a href="https://x.com/zsmb13" target="_blank">X</a>, <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/zsmb.co" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Bluesky</a>, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/zsmb13/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">LinkedIn</a></p>
<p><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Keep in mind that your talk should be related to Kotlin! For example, not every Android talk is necessarily a good fit for the KotlinConf audience. Or talks about Jetpack Compose often cover things that work the exact same way with Compose Multiplatform, and the latter is much more likely to be accepted at KotlinConf!</span></i></p>
                    </div>
                            </div>
        </div>
    </div>



<p>If your talk covers a popular theme, put your own unique spin on it. A case study, a personal experience, or a surprising insight can make your submission stand out.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">6. Showcase your speaking skills</h2>



<p>Even the most brilliant idea can fall short without effective delivery. The KotlinConf program committee wants to see that you can engage the audience.</p>


    <div class="about-author ">
        <div class="about-author__box">
            <div class="row">
                                                            <div class="about-author__box-img">
                            <img style="width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;" decoding="async" src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/1FqLye0HTHxz.jpeg" alt="" loading="lazy">
                        </div>
                                        <div class="about-author__box-text">
                                                    <h4>Svetlana Isakova. Team Lead in Kotlin Developer Advocacy, KotlinConf Program Committee member, KotlinConf speaker </h4>
                                                <p><a href="https://x.com/sveta_isakova" target="_blank">X</a></p>
<p><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Examples of your talks help us make better choices. If you’re a first-time speaker and don’t have recordings, no worries! You can simply record yourself (even just part of your proposed talk) on your laptop and share the link. We would really appreciate it.</span></i></p>
                    </div>
                            </div>
        </div>
    </div>



<p>The KotlinConf Call for Speakers form includes a <em>Recordings of previous talks</em> field, which is a fantastic opportunity to demonstrate your presentation style and energy. If you&#8217;re new to speaking, a short, self-recorded video can make a huge difference.</p>



<p>If you don’t have formal recordings, consider including links to blog posts, open-source projects, or short demo videos related to your topic.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">7. Polishing matters: Make your proposal shine</h2>



<p>A strong proposal isn’t just about content; presentation matters too. Typos, inconsistent formatting, or vague writing can work against you.</p>


    <div class="about-author ">
        <div class="about-author__box">
            <div class="row">
                                                            <div class="about-author__box-img">
                            <img style="width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;" decoding="async" src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/T0288D531-U05RAPGGJAK-8766042aed05-512.png" alt="" loading="lazy">
                        </div>
                                        <div class="about-author__box-text">
                                                    <h4>Márton Braun. Developer Advocate, KotlinConf Program Committee member, KotlinConf speaker</h4>
                                                <p><a href="https://x.com/zsmb13" target="_blank">X</a>, <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/zsmb.co" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Bluesky</a>, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/zsmb13/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">LinkedIn</a></p>
<p><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Your submission should show that you’ve put some thought and energy into preparing it. Check your submission for formatting issues and typos, and please don’t submit abstracts that were generated by LLMs.</span></i></p>
                    </div>
                            </div>
        </div>
    </div>



<p>Reviewers want to see that you’ve taken care in preparing your proposal. A polished submission suggests you’ll bring the same care to your talk.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">8. Consider different formats and feel free to submit more than one talk</h2>



<p>If your topic doesn’t quite fit a full-length slot, consider proposing a lightning talk instead.</p>


    <div class="about-author ">
        <div class="about-author__box">
            <div class="row">
                                                            <div class="about-author__box-img">
                            <img style="width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;" decoding="async" src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/T0288D531-U05RAPGGJAK-8766042aed05-512.png" alt="" loading="lazy">
                        </div>
                                        <div class="about-author__box-text">
                                                    <h4>Márton Braun. Developer Advocate, KotlinConf Program Committee member, KotlinConf speaker</h4>
                                                <p><a href="https://x.com/zsmb13" target="_blank">X</a>, <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/zsmb.co" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Bluesky</a>, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/zsmb13/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">LinkedIn</a></p>
<p><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Don’t forget that we also accept lightning talks! If you feel like your content would have to be padded to fill a regular session, it might be more enjoyable as a lightning talk.</span></i></p>
                    </div>
                            </div>
        </div>
    </div>



<p>And here’s another strategic tip: Submitting multiple proposals increases your chances of being selected.</p>


    <div class="about-author ">
        <div class="about-author__box">
            <div class="row">
                                                            <div class="about-author__box-img">
                            <img style="width:100% !important; height:auto !important; max-width:100% !important;" decoding="async" src="https://blog.jetbrains.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Untitled-design-2.png" alt="" loading="lazy">
                        </div>
                                        <div class="about-author__box-text">
                                                    <h4>Pamela Hill. Developer Advocate, KotlinConf Program Committee member, KotlinConf speaker</h4>
                                                <p><a href="https://x.com/pamelaahill" target="_blank">X</a>, <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/pamelaahill.bsky.social" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Bluesky</a>, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/pamelaahill/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">LinkedIn</a></p>
<p><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Submit more than one talk! It gives you more chances to join in on the KotlinConf fun.</span></i></p>
                    </div>
                            </div>
        </div>
    </div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">9. Don’t be afraid to get creative</h2>



<p>There&#8217;s always room for talks that are purely fun or explore unexpected aspects of Kotlin. If you have an amazing side project or discovered something truly surprising about the language, don&#8217;t hesitate to submit it!</p>



<p>The KotlinConf&#8217;26 Call for Speakers is opem! Share your Kotlin expertise with the world – server-side, web, desktop, mobile, AI/ML, and more! Submit your proposal and get a chance to speak at the year&#8217;s biggest Kotlin event!</p>



<p align="center"><a class="ek-link jb-download-button" title="Submit your session" href="https://jb.gg/l1dymy" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Submit your session</a></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Conclusion</h2>



<p>Getting a talk accepted to a prestigious conference like KotlinConf is a significant achievement. It’s an opportunity to share your insights, experiences, or even fun discoveries with the Kotlin community. However, the competition is stiff, and each year, many good proposals don’t make the cut.</p>



<p>Don’t get discouraged if your submission isn’t accepted. Keep refining your ideas, practice your presentation skills, and continue to engage with the Kotlin community. Every submission is a learning experience and valuable practice. With preparation and care, the next KotlinConf stage could be yours.</p>



<p>Good luck preparing your submission for KotlinConf&#8217;26!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
