<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Ubuntu blog</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/feed</link><description>Ubuntu blog feed</description><atom:link href="https://ubuntu.com//blog/feed" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>Python Feedgen</generator><lastBuildDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 12:06:21 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Open design: the opportunity design students didn’t know they were missing</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/open-design-the-opportunity-design-students-didnt-know-they-were-missing</link><description>&lt;p&gt;What if you could work on real-world projects, shape cutting-edge technology, collaborate with developers across the world, make a meaningful impact with your design skills, and grow your portfolio… all without applying for an internship or waiting for graduation? That’s what we aim to do with open design: an opportunity for universities and students of [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="372" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 660px) 660px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_660/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2e37%2Fimage.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2e37%2Fimage.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2e37%2Fimage.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2e37%2Fimage.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_660/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2e37%2Fimage.png 660w" width="660"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if you could work on real-world projects, shape cutting-edge technology, collaborate with developers across the world, make a meaningful impact with your design skills, and grow your portfolio… all without applying for an internship or waiting for graduation?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s what we aim to do with open design: an opportunity for universities and students of any design discipline. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;What is open design, and why does it matter?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we go further, let’s talk about what open design is. Many open source tools are built by developers, for developers, without design in mind. When open source software powers &lt;a href="https://static.carahsoft.com/concrete/files/1617/1597/8665/2024_Open_Source_Security_and_Risk_Analysis_Report_WRAPPED.pdf"&gt;90% of the digital world&lt;/a&gt; (PDF), it leaves everyday users feeling overwhelmed or left out. Open design wants to bridge that gap. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We aim to introduce human-centred thinking into open source development, enhancing these tools to be more intuitive, inclusive, and user-friendly. Most open source projects focus on code contributions, neglecting design contributions. That leaves a vast number of projects without a design system, accessibility audits, or onboarding documentation. That’s where designers come in, helping shape better user experiences and more welcoming communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open design is about more than just aesthetics. Open design helps to make technology work for people; that’s exactly what open source needs. Learn more about open design on our &lt;a href="https://canonical.design/open-design"&gt;webpage&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We want to raise awareness for the projects,  the problems that currently exist, and how we can fix them together,  and encourage universities and students to become advocates of open design. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We want universities to connect their students to real-world, meaningful design opportunities in a field that is currently lacking the creativity of designers. Our goal is to help and motivate students to bring their design skills into open source projects and become advocates, to make open design accessible, practical, and empowering! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;How Canonical helps universities access open design&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We want to help universities help students to access:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Real-world experiences:&lt;/strong&gt; Students apply their design skills to global projects to create valuable, demonstrable outcomes, beyond hypothetical briefs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Interdisciplinary growth:&lt;/strong&gt; Empower students to gain collaborative experience with developers, and navigate real tech workflows&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accessible opportunities:&lt;/strong&gt; No interviews, no barriers; just impact, experience, and learning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have provided universities with talks and project briefs, enabling them to prepare students to utilise their expertise and design a brighter future for open source. If you’re a department leader, instructor, or coordinator, &lt;a href="https://canonical.design/open-design/get-started-for-designers"&gt;exploring open source and open design&lt;/a&gt; will help you to give your students unique access to industry-aligned experiences, while embedding values of collaboration, open contribution, and inclusive design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Why should students care?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re a student in UX, UI, interaction, service, visual, HCI design, or &lt;strong&gt;any other field with design influence&lt;/strong&gt;, you’ve been told how important it is to build your portfolio, gain hands-on experience, and collaborate with cross-functional teams. Open design is your opportunity to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best part is, you don’t have to write a single line of code to make a difference! Open source projects are looking for:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;UX/UI improvements&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Accessibility and heuristic audits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;User research and persona development&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;User flows and wireframes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Information architecture reviews&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Design documentation and feedback systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re in a design course, you already have, or are developing, the skills that open-source projects need. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open design is an opportunity to develop by collaborating across disciplines, navigating ambiguity, and advocating for users: skills employers value. With open design, you’ll gain confidence in presenting ideas, working with international teams, and handling feedback in a real-world setting, growing in ways that classroom projects and internships often don’t offer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re aiming for a tech-focused design career, open design is one of the most impactful and distinctive ways to stand out!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;How can you start?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting started is easier than you think, even if GitHub looks scary at first. Here’s how:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Learn the basics of GitHub&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve made a &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/rIN3Tr1xRIw?si=WqMUIKZ3RrbGwUh2"&gt;video guide to understanding GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, and curated a list of other &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1sy-KSbA3WATYD20lWXOcRLIGxLOTJjZKDUhpNn-shZA/edit?tab=t.0#heading=h.cdj6wh5znx6k"&gt;videos&lt;/a&gt; to get to grips with GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start="2"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Find a project on &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://contribute.design/for-designers"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;contribute.design&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s like a job board for design contributions. These projects are waiting for you. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start="3"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Understand the project’s needs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most projects on &lt;a href="https://contribute.design/for-designers"&gt;contribute.design&lt;/a&gt; list what they’re looking for in .design file or DESIGN.md guidelines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start="4"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pick an issue, or propose your own&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Navigate to the Issues tab of the project repo, where you can filter for issues labelled for design. You can also use this tab to propose any issues you discover in the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start="5"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contribute, collaborate, grow&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start adding your ideas, questions, and solutions to issues. You’ll be collaborating, communicating, and making meaningful contributions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can explore more projects through the &lt;a href="https://github.com/explore"&gt;GitHub Explore&lt;/a&gt; page, but not every project will have a design process in place; that’s where your skills are especially valuable. If you don’t see design issues, treat the project as a blank canvas. Suggest checklists, organise a design system, or improve documentation. The power is in your hands!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reach out to maintainers, join community discussions, and don’t hesitate to introduce design-focused thinking. Your initiative can spark meaningful change and help open source become more user-friendly, one project at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;View every project as an opportunity; you don’t need an invitation to contribute, just curiosity, creativity, and the willingness to collaborate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Interested? &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re looking for universities and departments interested in introducing open design to their students. Whether that’s through a talk, module project briefs, or anything else you’d like to see, we’re excited to find ways to work together and bring open design to campus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you a program director, a design department, a student group, or an interested student? Let’s talk!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reach out at &lt;a href="mailto:opendesign@canonical.com"&gt;opendesign@canonical.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Miguel Divo (Miguel Divo)</author><category>Design</category><category>open design</category><category>University</category><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 09:39:51 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Anbox Cloud 1.28.0 is now available!</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/anbox-cloud-1-28-0-is-now-available</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Enhanced Android device simulation, smarter diagnostics, and OIDC-enforced authentication The Anbox Cloud team has been working around the clock to release Anbox Cloud 1.28.0! We’re very proud of this release that adds robust authentication, improved diagnostic tools, and expanded simulation options, making Anbox Cloud even more secure, flexible, and developer-friendly for running large-scale Android workloads. [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;Enhanced Android device simulation, smarter diagnostics, and OIDC-enforced authentication&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Anbox Cloud team has been working around the clock to release Anbox Cloud 1.28.0! We’re very proud of this release that adds robust authentication, improved diagnostic tools, and expanded simulation options, making Anbox Cloud even more secure, flexible, and developer-friendly for running large-scale Android workloads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s go over the most significant changes in this new version.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Strengthened authentication and authorization&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our OpenID Connect (OIDC)-based authentication and authorization framework is now stable with Anbox Cloud 1.28.0. This new framework provides a standardized approach for controlling access across web and command-line clients. Operators can now assign permissions through entitlements with fine-grained control, define authorization groups, and create and manage identities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Configuring user permissions, understanding the idea of identities and groups, and looking through the entire list of available entitlements are all thoroughly covered in the &lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/anbox-cloud/howto/anbox/auth/#howto-auth"&gt;new guides&lt;/a&gt; that come with this release. This represents a significant advancement in the direction of a more uniform and standards-based access model for all Anbox Cloud deployments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Simulated SMS support&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is one of our most exciting new features: developers testing telephony-enabled applications in Anbox Cloud can now simulate incoming SMS messages using the Anbox runtime HTTP API. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This new functionality allows messages to trigger notifications the same way they would on a physical device, generating more realistic end-to-end scenarios. A &lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/anbox-cloud/howto/android/simulate-incoming-sms/#howto-simulate-incoming-sms"&gt;new how-to guide&lt;/a&gt; in our documentation provides detailed instructions on how to enable and use this feature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Protection against accidental deletions&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because we know accidents happen (especially in production environments…), in order to reduce operational risk, this release introduces the ability to protect instances from accidental deletion. This option can be enabled directly in the dashboard either when creating a new instance or later from the Instance details page under the Security section. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once this protection option is turned on, the instance cannot be deleted, even during bulk delete operations, until the configuration is reset. This simple safeguard helps operators preserve important data and prevents costly mistakes in busy environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Improved ADB share management&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working with ADB (the Android Debug Bridge) has also become more flexible. Anbox Cloud now allows up to five ADB shares to be managed directly from the dashboard. For those who prefer the command line, the new amc connect command provides an alternative to the existing anbox-connect tool. Together, these improvements make it easier for developers to manage and maintain multiple debugging or testing sessions at once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;New diagnostic facility for troubleshooting&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With version 1.28.0, we’re introducing a new diagnostic facility in the dashboard. This tool is designed to simplify troubleshooting for both the instances and the streaming sessions themselves. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This feature helps collect relevant diagnostic data automatically, thereby reducing the work needed to identify and resolve issues. It also makes collaboration with our Canonical support teams more efficient, as users can now provide consistent and accurate diagnostic information in a structured, standard format.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Sensor support in the Streaming SDK&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s another hotly anticipated feature: the Anbox Streaming SDK gains expanded sensor support in this release. Our SDK now includes gyroscope, accelerometer and orientation sensors, allowing developers to test applications more interactively. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sensor support is disabled by default but can be easily enabled in the streaming client configuration. This addition opens up new possibilities for interactive use cases, such as gaming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Upgrade now and stay tuned!&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We think that Anbox Cloud 1.28.0 is our best release to date, and we are pleased to keep providing a feature-rich, scalable, and safe solution for managing Android workloads on a large scale. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This latest version makes it easier than ever for developers and operators to create and test Android apps by introducing more precise device simulation, improved troubleshooting tools, and stricter access controls, as we’ve explained above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try it now and stay tuned for further developments in our upcoming releases. For detailed instructions on how to upgrade your existing deployment, please refer to the &lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/anbox-cloud/en/latest/howto/update/upgrade-anbox/#howto-upgrade-anbox-cloud"&gt;official documentation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Further reading&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/anbox-cloud/#"&gt;Official documentation&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/anbox-cloud/howto/install-appliance/install-on-github/"&gt;Anbox Cloud Appliance&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://canonical.com/anbox-cloud"&gt;Learn more about Anbox Cloud or contact our team to discuss your use case&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Android is a trademark of Google LLC. Anbox Cloud uses assets available through the Android Open Source Project.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Bertrand Boisseau (Bertrand Boisseau)</author><category>Anbox</category><category>anbox cloud</category><category>Anbox Cloud Appliance</category><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>83% of organizations see value in adopting open source, but report major gaps in security and governance</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/state-of-global-open-source-2025</link><description>&lt;p&gt;A new Linux Foundation report reveals how organizations worldwide are adopting, using, and perceiving open source software. The Linux Foundation’s latest report, The state of global open source, has just been released in collaboration with Canonical. The report follows the Linux Foundation’s European spotlight report, released earlier this year, and confirms that many of the [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;A new Linux Foundation report reveals how organizations worldwide are adopting, using, and perceiving open source software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Linux Foundation’s latest &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/engage/world-of-open-source-global-2025"&gt;report&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;The state of global open source&lt;/em&gt;, has just been released in collaboration with Canonical. The report follows &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/blog/open-source-advantage-europe"&gt;the Linux Foundation’s European spotlight report&lt;/a&gt;, released earlier this year, and confirms that many of the trends the European spotlight report unveiled are true on a global scale. In particular, the global spotlight report confirms the role of open source software as the foundation of business-critical systems worldwide, and indicates a continued increase in adoption. However, organizations continue to lack the governance, security testing, and strategic maturity required to manage open source strategically and securely. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The report suggests that most organizations expect enterprise-grade performance from open source software, but under-invest in the required governance frameworks, security practices, and community engagement. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/engage/world-of-open-source-global-2025"&gt;&lt;button class="p-button--positive"&gt;Download the report&lt;/button&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;83% of organizations acknowledge open source is valuable to their future&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the report, the trend of increasing open source adoption in the enterprise is set to continue, as 83% of enterprises consider open source software adoption valuable to their future. Likewise, the report reveals the centrality of open source software to the modern enterprise. Globally, enterprises have adopted open source software throughout their technical stacks: 55% have adopted open source operating systems, whilst 49% have adopted open source cloud and container technologies, and 46% open source web and application development. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The widespread confidence that open source will play a pivotal role in many organizations’ futures is closely connected to a growing understanding of the benefits of open source software adoption.   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;86% report open source software improves productivity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This report confirms a shift in enterprises’ strategic mindset around open source: 82% of respondents considered open source as an asset that enables innovation. Historically, open source software was often reserved for specific projects or use cases, like setting up web servers – with wider organizational use being viewed with some scepticism. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open source is now a “must-have.” Why is this the case? Here’s what the respondents had to say: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;86% stated that open source improves productivity &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;79% reported improved software quality as a result of open source&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;78% highlighted improved security&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="701" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1180px) 1180px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1180/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F9d4b%2FGraph-Linux-Foundation-2025-World-of-Open-Source-Global-Report.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F9d4b%2FGraph-Linux-Foundation-2025-World-of-Open-Source-Global-Report.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F9d4b%2FGraph-Linux-Foundation-2025-World-of-Open-Source-Global-Report.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F9d4b%2FGraph-Linux-Foundation-2025-World-of-Open-Source-Global-Report.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F9d4b%2FGraph-Linux-Foundation-2025-World-of-Open-Source-Global-Report.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F9d4b%2FGraph-Linux-Foundation-2025-World-of-Open-Source-Global-Report.png 1920w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1180/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F9d4b%2FGraph-Linux-Foundation-2025-World-of-Open-Source-Global-Report.png 1180w" width="1180"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compared to the benefits seen by organizations using open source software in 2024, 46% reported increased business value from open source over the past year. The growing interest in and use of open source technologies is particularly clear for certain technologies, like AI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;AI technologies benefit most from being open source&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The growing value of open source can partly be attributed to the influence of AI. Since 2024, there has been an increase in the adoption of open source AI and machine learning (ML) applications from 35% to 40% – a rise of 5%. Globally, AI and ML were perceived to be the technology most benefiting from being open source. Code visibility ensures organizations can more easily audit their AI systems, which makes compliance simpler, provides more transparency into how the AI model functions, and enables companies to run the AI on their own infrastructure – ensuring sensitive data never leaves the organization’s control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With growing adoption of AI and ML come new cybersecurity risks and requirements. However, the report indicates that organizations currently lack mature governance structures for their open source estates, creating additional complications to adopting AI and ML securely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Lack of mature governance: only 34% of organizations have defined a clear open source strategy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite increasing adoption of open source technologies, many organizations still lack a mature governance strategy for their open source software. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The number of organizations that have defined a clear open source strategy has grown by just 2% in the last year, to a total of 34%. That means that nearly two-thirds of organizations rely instead on informal strategies of governance of their open source estates, primarily due to budget constraints, shifting priorities and new strategic requirements. For example, when evaluating open source components for adoption:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;44% of organizations check the activity level of the project community&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;31% use automated security testing tools&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;28% manually review the source code&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;36% evaluate the direct dependencies of the open source component&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With less than half of organizations taking these important formal strategies before adoption, the report indicates that this “creates significant risk exposure and limits organizations’ ability to capture the full strategic value of open source participation,” signalling that this is a concern that organizations must take seriously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, organizations demonstrate a lack of consensus around which security features and assurances matter to them when adopting open source components, with no single certification or assurance mechanism achieving adoption by more than a quarter of open source solutions. Almost a third of organizations (28%) don’t know which assurances would make them more likely to trust an open source solution. This opens them up to serious security risks, like supply chain attacks.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result, enterprises are increasingly turning to paid support options for their open source estates. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;54% view paid support as essential for mission-critical workloads&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than half of respondents consider paid support for their open source essential. As open source technologies have become critical to business infrastructure, expectations for open source software support are beginning to mirror that of commercial software standards: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;71% of organizations expect response times of less than 12 hours from support providers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;47% expect rapid security patching for open source software in production environments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;53% expect long term support guarantees for their open source software. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Acquiring paid support for open source software makes this level of support achievable, which organizations broadly accept. On a granular level, the industries with the highest proportion that consider paid support essential are those that process sensitive or valuable data, such as manufacturing (97%) followed by financial services (96%), IT (91%) and government (92%). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Conclusion and recommendations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Linux Foundation’s &lt;em&gt;The state of global open source&lt;/em&gt; reveals that enterprises are relying on open source software and perceiving its benefits. However, increasing engagement with open source communities, more structured governance of open source estates, and structured security evaluations of open source elements before adoption will help organizations to strengthen the resilience of their open source infrastructure. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="p-cta-block"&gt;
&lt;a class="p-button--positive" href="https://ubuntu.com/engage/world-of-open-source-global-2025"&gt;Download the report&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://canonical.com/open-source-adoption"&gt;Adopt open source in your enterprise with Canonical ›&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Canonical (Canonical)</author><pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 16:10:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Everything you need to know about FIPS 140-3 on Ubuntu | Videos </title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/everything-you-need-to-know-about-fips-140-3-on-ubuntu-videos</link><description>&lt;p&gt;We get a lot of questions about FIPS 140-3, and so we decided to put together this comprehensive collection of video resources to answer the most burning ones we’ve had so far. &lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;FIPS 140 is a highly demanding security standard that’s mandatory for almost all high-security and federal environments. It can be hard to get right and may be a daunting part of the journey for those trying to meet compliance requirements like FedRAMP or CMMC. We get &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt; of questions about FIPS 140-3, and so we decided to put together this comprehensive collection of video resources to answer the most burning ones we’ve had so far. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this collection, you’ll be able to get answers to the most frequently asked FIPS questions, including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to enable FIPS 140-3 on Ubuntu 22.04&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to check if you’re operating in FIPS mode&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to enable FIPS on public clouds: AWS, Azure, GCP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Which modules and hardware have been FIPS 140-3 certified for Ubuntu &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Which FIPS-enabled Docker containers are available in Iron Bank &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the most common issues when enabling FIPS 140-3 &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;How to enable FIPS on Ubuntu?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"&gt;&lt;div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper"&gt;
&lt;iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="304" loading="lazy" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/KcbKMMHC-KU?list=PLwFSk464RMxkQhlIXi-HdQrq4-ZjTJewL" title="How to enable FIPS 140-3 on Ubuntu" width="540"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ll start with the most common question: how do you enable FIPS on Ubuntu? The basic prerequisite is an Ubuntu Pro subscription, which is available either free for personal use or with a 30-day free trial for enterprise users. After subscribing, you’ll get access to a dashboard where you can find a token that you can attach to an Ubuntu instance and get access to the FIPS certified modules. All you need to do is open your terminal and enter the following commands: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo pro attach &amp;lt;token&amp;gt;

sudo pro enable fips-updates

sudo reboot&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should see output like the following, indicating that the FIPS packages have been installed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;Installing FIPS Updates packages

FIPS Updates enabled

A reboot is required to complete install.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enabling FIPS should be performed during a system maintenance window since this operation makes changes to underlying SSL-related libraries and requires a reboot into the FIPS-certified kernel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;How to check if you’re operating in FIPS mode&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"&gt;&lt;div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper"&gt;
&lt;iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="304" loading="lazy" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/W9ZJXHEeSNQ?list=PLwFSk464RMxkQhlIXi-HdQrq4-ZjTJewL" title="How to check if you're operating in FIPS mode" width="540"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After enabling FIPS mode, it is good to verify that it is activated. Luckily it’s very straightforward to verify that FIPS mode is enabled. Just run this command in the terminal:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;cat /proc/sys/crypto/fips_enabled&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The output that indicates that FIPS mode is enabled is “&lt;strong&gt;1&lt;/strong&gt;”. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;How to enable FIPS on public clouds&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"&gt;&lt;div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper"&gt;
&lt;iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="304" loading="lazy" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Zd4ucUhaGWU?list=PLwFSk464RMxkQhlIXi-HdQrq4-ZjTJewL" title="Enabling FIPS on public clouds" width="540"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is very easy to enable FIPS in public clouds. In contrast to on-prem usage, Ubuntu images for public clouds already have FIPS enabled. Decide on the Ubuntu version you’d like to run, visit the relevant marketplace for your public cloud provider (for example: &lt;a href="https://aws.amazon.com/marketplace/pp/prodview-o5noqh44k3uxm"&gt;AWS&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://azuremarketplace.microsoft.com/en-us/marketplace/apps/canonical.0001-com-ubuntu-pro-jammy-fips?tab=Overview"&gt;Azure&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href="https://console.cloud.google.com/compute/instancesAdd?imageId=4467206581577450407&amp;amp;imageProjectId=ubuntu-os-pro-cloud&amp;amp;pli=1"&gt;GCP&lt;/a&gt;), and search for the relevant image. Here is an example of how it would look:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img decoding="async" height="344" loading="lazy" src="blob:https://admin.insights.ubuntu.com/cf988ecc-4ade-4921-95b7-696661161e00" width="624"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Which modules and hardware have been FIPS 140-3 certified &lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"&gt;&lt;div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper"&gt;
&lt;iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="304" loading="lazy" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/tG2Sfjr2sRk?list=PLwFSk464RMxkQhlIXi-HdQrq4-ZjTJewL" title="FIPS certified modules and hardware for Ubuntu" width="540"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes it can be tricky to figure out exactly which modules and hardware have been FIPS 140-3 certified. This video goes into extensive detail outlining the modules and components you’ll be able to make full use of with FIPS 140-3 certified Ubuntu. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To give a brief overview, the following certified cryptographic modules are available with Ubuntu 22.04 LTS:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;OpenSSL v3.0.5&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Libgcrypt v1.9.4&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;GnuTLS v3.7.3&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Linux kernel v5.15.0&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;StrongSwan v5.9.5&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These modules have been developed and tested on a range of hardware platforms:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Intel/AMD x86_64&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ARM64&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IBM z15&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;FIPS-enabled containers available in Iron Bank &lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"&gt;&lt;div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper"&gt;
&lt;iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="304" loading="lazy" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/hwdoRlKjnkA?list=PLwFSk464RMxkQhlIXi-HdQrq4-ZjTJewL" title="FIPS enabled containers" width="540"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical’s container images are trusted and pre-approved for high-security use cases. Hardened Ubuntu images are already certified and available in the U.S. Department of Defense’s Iron Bank, the official repository of security-hardened containers for government systems. You can find the code to build your own image &lt;a href="https://ironbank.dso.mil/repomap/details;registry1Path=canonical%252Fubuntu-pro-cis-fips-stig"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, or get the actual container that passed all the automated compliance checks &lt;a href="https://ironbank.dso.mil/repomap/details;registry1Path=canonical%252Fubuntu-pro-cis-fips-stig"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Note, you would need to first register to get access to the platform. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;img decoding="async" height="461.0802935662009" src="blob:https://admin.insights.ubuntu.com/fbdbf290-bbcc-4b61-96f6-fa8cd45c6655" width="624"/&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical has also &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/engage/secure-federal-cloud-native-stack-k8s"&gt;recently added FIPS and STIG-compliance to Canonical Kubernetes.&lt;/a&gt; Built on Ubuntu Pro hosts, Canonical Kubernetes now includes FIPS 140-3 validated crypto modules out of the box and can be hardened for DISA-STIG. This means you can deploy secure, compliant clusters built on Ubuntu, making it much easier to meet FedRAMP and other federal compliance requirements right from your Kubernetes base.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Common issues when enabling FIPS 140-3 &lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"&gt;&lt;div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper"&gt;
&lt;iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="304" loading="lazy" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/OwGBfrdMFlw?list=PLwFSk464RMxkQhlIXi-HdQrq4-ZjTJewL" title="Common issues when enabling FIPS" width="540"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compliance always comes with challenges, but when we know the issues, we can help. The video above explains how to solve the most common issues that teams run into when enabling FIPS 140-3, including: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;WiFi SSID should be 16 characters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;32-bit crypto library versions must be removed, if present&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Full-disk encryption requires PBKDF2
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sudo cryptsetup –pbkdf=pbkdf2 luksAddKey &amp;lt;partition&amp;gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some applications might not expect disallowed operations to fail – we will endeavor to provide fixes where possible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’d like to raise a bug/issue with FIPS compliance on Ubuntu, you can do it on Launchpad. &lt;a href="https://bugs.launchpad.net/bugs/bugtrackers/openssl-rt"&gt;Here is an example of OpenSSL bugs&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Summary &lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We hope this blog has been useful for you to learn more about FIPS 140-3 on Ubuntu. You can&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/pro/subscribe"&gt; easily get FIPS 140-3 compliance with an Ubuntu Pro subscription, which is &lt;/a&gt;free for personal use and offers a&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/pro/subscribe"&gt; free trial&lt;/a&gt; for enterprise-focused projects. Additionally, an &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/pro"&gt;Ubuntu Pro subscription&lt;/a&gt; is not limited to only FIPS 140-3: the subscription also includes access to our hardening automation tools such as &lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/security/compliance/usg/"&gt;Ubuntu Security Guide&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/security/esm"&gt;expanded security maintenance&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/landscape"&gt;Ubuntu fleet management&lt;/a&gt;, and more. And if you’re looking for assistance with more complex enterprise use cases, you can simply &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/security/fips#get-in-touch"&gt;contact us&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;More reading &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/security/fips"&gt;Learn more about FIPS on Ubuntu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/security/"&gt;Ubuntu security documentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/engage/security-compliance-US-public-sector-FIPS-DISASTIG"&gt;Ubuntu Compliance Guide for the US Public Sector&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/security/security-standards"&gt;All security standards offered on Ubuntu &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Case Study: &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/case-study/lucid-aws-fedramp-compliance-case-study"&gt;How Lucid Software became FedRAMP compliant in less than 6 months&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Henry Coggill (Henry Coggill)</author><category>CMMC</category><category>DISA STIG</category><category>FedRAMP</category><category>FIPS</category><category>FIPS certification</category><category>Hardening</category><category>Ubuntu Pro</category><pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 18:23:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A CISO’s preview of open source and cybersecurity trends in 2026 and beyond</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/a-cisos-preview-of-open-source-and-cybersecurity-trends-in-2026-and-beyond</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Where is open source going next? What’s in store for open source in the coming years, particularly in relation to security? Here’s a CISO&amp;#8217;s reflection on the state of open source, and the trends that you can expect to have an impact going into 2026. &lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;Open source has come a long way. Recently I was watching a &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lt9TAQLT0PM&amp;amp;t=31s"&gt;keynote address by our founder, Mark Shuttleworth&lt;/a&gt;, in which he discussed his vision for Ubuntu to provide quality support and security maintenance across the broad open source ecosystem, and it made me reflect on how far the open source software (OSS) community has come. Indeed, when looking at today’s interoperable open source landscape, the fragmented, disconnected landscape of the past seems like another planet. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But where is open source going next? What’s in store for open source in the coming years, particularly in relation to security? Here’s my reflection on the state of open source, and the trends that I expect to have an impact going into 2026. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;So, what is the state of open source in 2025?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open source has become a ubiquitous part of software development – just look at the numbers. The average app today contains three times as many open source files as it did just four years ago, to the point where &lt;a href="https://www.blackduck.com/resources/analyst-reports/open-source-security-risk-analysis.html"&gt;97% of all applications contain OSS&lt;/a&gt;. At the same time, research commissioned by Canonical and IDC revealed that seven out of ten organizations &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/engage/2025-state-of-software-supply-chain"&gt;consider open source to be “extremely important”&lt;/a&gt; for running their mission-critical workloads. In fact, a &lt;a href="https://www.hbs.edu/faculty/Pages/item.aspx?num=65230#:~:text=We%20find%20that%20firms%20would%20need%20to,created%20by%20only%205%25%20of%20OSS%20developers."&gt;Harvard study&lt;/a&gt; found that if OSS didn’t exist, the global expenditure on software would be 3.5 times higher. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Put simply, the modern software landscape and market depends upon open source. Open source is popular because it is transformative for businesses, blending cost-effectiveness with access to sophisticated software. For instance, one company &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/engage/oneuptime-cost-savings-case-study?_gl=1*16vyo7l*_gcl_au*OTAwNzM2NjA0LjE3Mzk5Njk3NjU."&gt;reduced their cloud total cost of ownership (TCO) by 76%&lt;/a&gt; – saving approximately $370,000 – simply by transitioning to open source cloud infrastructure from Canonical. Previously unthinkable deployments, such as carrier-grade private 5G mobile networks, are now entirely achievable with open source tools, as &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/blog/telco-bringing-automation-to-open-source-5g-software-at-ubuntu-summit-2024"&gt;we demonstrated last year in the Netherlands&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s astonishing to think that just 20 years ago, most software companies explicitly forbid the use of &lt;strong&gt;any&lt;/strong&gt; OSS in their contracts and terms of service. Open standards and interoperability – now synonymous with open source – were far from mainstream, and as a result, companies were forced into an uncomfortable decision: use the one expensive product that works, or spend months building and integrating everything from scratch. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s a lot of change in just 20 years: an entire ecosystem turned on its head. That’s why I think it’s important to pay critical attention to what’s going around us, to spot trends that could be just as revolutionary (or disastrous), and work around them so that we can keep growing in the next 20 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that I’ve covered the current state of play, let’s dive into the potential tech revolutions – or challenges – in-waiting. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Future open source cybersecurity trends and their impact on cybersecurity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Open source adoption will continue its strong rise&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The decision to move away from the constraints of proprietary systems is grounded in promise: as &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/engage/2025-state-of-software-supply-chain"&gt;research by Canonical and IDC shows&lt;/a&gt;, businesses everywhere are using open source to keep down costs, fully own their infrastructure, and open up their systems to innovation. Ensuring that this promise is reflected in reality requires a proactive, forward-thinking approach. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your ability to adopt and adapt to the latest innovations in open source software will be vital. Two things are needed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A clear plan for adopting open source&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A way to manage this open source software supply chain post-adoption&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without a clear plan, you don’t know where you’re going; and without a management system, you’ll be recreating the difficult, fragmented environment open source was 20 years ago. However, I believe that the ever wider adoption of open source will lead to interoperability and simplified supply chains becoming the norm in the software landscape – essentially, that open source software will reshape the software landscape in line with its values. People want open source software that’s quick to install, easy to learn and use, and effortless to deploy and manage. If you’re looking for a place to begin exploring how you can approach adopting open source into your project or organization, I highly recommend visiting &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/open-source-adoption"&gt;our new dedicated webpage to helping you do exactly that.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;A new age of digital sovereignty&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tumultuous geopolitical and cyberthreat landscape of 2025 has sparked a new movement towards independence and ownership in mainstream circles. Long story short, companies don’t want to be left in the cold and dark if something happens with their overseas software or services provider – with the appeal of open source software being the control and freedom it offers to users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most notably, we’ve seen a major increase in interest, from businesses and governments, in open source, and repatriated products and infrastructure. For example, communal, municipal, and government authorities in nations like Germany and Denmark have expressed strong interest in moving away from proprietary systems in favour of open source alternatives. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This doesn’t mean proprietary tools will vanish. But it does mean that the pressure will increase on software providers to give peace of mind to end users and consumers that whatever system they use will remain online and functioning – even if new terms of service, sanctions, politics, or laws present unforeseen hurdles. Product features will still be important, but things like documentation, interoperability, system-agnostic design, training for users and system admins, and clear handover processes will be a new ‘normal’ in software offerings. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Organizations must balance complexity with visibility&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The developer landscape in 2025 has no shortage of tools, libraries, and solutions. If you want to build an app or service, you could build it from scratch, get portions of the solution from open source, or use already-built solutions. The challenge today is creating systems that give you a full view of these tools, and which allow them to be used securely and sustainably in the long term, without major costs. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Security is hard. There is no one-size-fits-all solution, which introduces the challenge of complexity. Developers have a lot of shiny toys to choose from, and keeping them all securely managed within a usable, minimally complex environment will be a real challenge. Indeed, securing your ever-growing stack won’t be easy. All this new tech doesn’t just mean maximized performance and efficiency: it also means a bigger attack surface and new attack vectors born of the intricate interdependencies between systems. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is made harder by wider organizational  habits. Canonical and IDC’s research shows that in general, organizations prize stability over constant updates: over 50% do not automatically upgrade to the newest versions of software when available. Instead, they wait until new features are needed or the program of free updates stops. They also draw these updates from various places: 57% draw from upstream source repositories, such as Github or Gitlab, and 51% draw from ecosystem packages, like pip or npm. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This approach presents clear problems: if you draw packages from multiple different sources and only apply them when you’re forced to update, it leads to more manual work and less certainty that you’re meeting increasingly strict cybersecurity standards in today’s market. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Organizations still have some work to do in order to meet the challenge of complexity. Our research with IDC shows that 70% of organizations mandate vulnerability patching within 24 hours of identification for “high” and “critical” container vulnerabilities – however, just 41% of respondents are “very confident” or “completely confident” in their organization’s ability to execute this policy. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember that innovation isn’t just driven by “the good guys”: bad actors are also working to develop new attack methods and techniques, as AI becomes increasingly powerful and AI tools become more connected and widespread.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;… especially as we enter the post vibe-coding era&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve all heard about and read about vibe coding, which is when a software engineer uses AI to generate and debug code. The hype wave of AI has led to fast adoption of generative AI tools as  incredible productivity magnifiers. While the allure of faster go-to-market times and improved cost-effectiveness is undeniable, the widespread adoption of AI tools in primary codebases, especially in environments with busy developers stretching across multiple projects, is creating significant security issues. The rapid, often less scrutinized generation of code through these tools can introduce vulnerabilities and amplify existing security challenges in complex software supply chains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the next few years, I predict the rise of a new  category of cyberincidents stemming from vibecoded feature additions. Organizations everywhere will need a clear policy on use of these tools, and robust checks and quality assurance processes to ensure that the vibecoded additions don’t ignore instructions, or hallucinate package names and inadvertently execute malicious code inside production environments. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Regulation is coming, and making things harder&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve seen a wave of regulation sweep across the US, EU, and UK in the last 4 years. As open source is adopted at the biggest levels of software, it will inherit the steep, strict demands that come with operating in a prestigious global playing field. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/engage/2025-state-of-software-supply-chain"&gt;Our research with IDC&lt;/a&gt; gives a clearer view into the challenges and frustrations that organizations are experiencing with regulations and compliance:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;37% of organizations are struggling to understand how regulations apply to specific systems, technologies, and software components.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;34% are battling with how to enforce compliance standards across software systems in a consistent manner.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;29% find it hard to source the resources and expertise needed to centrally manage software compliance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class="wp-block-buttons is-layout-flex wp-block-buttons-is-layout-flex"&gt;
&lt;div class="wp-block-button"&gt;&lt;a class="wp-block-button__link wp-element-button" href="https://ubuntu.com/engage/2025-state-of-software-supply-chain" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"&gt;Download the full IDC research report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As more regulation is rolled out and tightened up, these challenges will only become harder. Simply hitting the check box of compliance or hardening needed for enterprise eligibility isn’t the point any more – security teams have their work cut out in establishing a clear, transparent track record of your software’s trust lifecycle, and embed this transparency into your development practices. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means more work for people like me whose job it is to keep open source robust and trusted. But it’s undeniably the right path. After all, we don’t just want solutions that work – we want solutions that reflect, support, and continue the legacy of openness and contribution that allowed them to exist in the first place. And we want Canonical to be a leader in transparency and accountability, and institute practices that demonstrate the trustworthiness and compliance-readiness of our software and services. &lt;a href="https://trust.canonical.com/"&gt;We recently published our Trust Center&lt;/a&gt; – a web portal with all our certifications and compliance efforts – in order to demonstrate that when it comes to that hard work of regulations, we’re doing it right. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="wp-block-buttons is-layout-flex wp-block-buttons-is-layout-flex"&gt;
&lt;div class="wp-block-button"&gt;&lt;a class="wp-block-button__link wp-element-button" href="https://trust.canonical.com/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"&gt;Visit the Canonical Trust Center&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Wrapping up&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short: the future will be characterized by even more adoption of open source, increased regulation, a surge in AI-driven attack vectors, and a critical need for organizations to implement robust security policies and practices. Businesses must prioritize security without compromising stability, manage their open source supply chains effectively, and adapt to a landscape where transparency and compliance are paramount.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No matter the upcoming challenges to security in open source, I’m truly excited about this next phase.  The openness we spent decades building has created a truly remarkable landscape of interoperability, where you can combine and integrate almost any technology into a functioning model. I’ve seen first hand how open source has changed everything in the software landscape, and I know how much more revolutionary it could be in the coming years. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Black Duck, 2025 “Open Source Security and Risk Analysis 2025. Accessed at:  &lt;a href="https://www.blackduck.com/resources/analyst-reports/open-source-security-risk-analysis.html"&gt;https://www.blackduck.com/resources/analyst-reports/open-source-security-risk-analysis.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hoffmann, Manuel, Frank Nagle, and Yanuo Zhou. “The Value of Open Source Software.” Harvard Business School Working Paper, No. 24-038, January 2024.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/engage/2025-state-of-software-supply-chain"&gt;The state of software supply chains: Security challenges, opportunities and the path to resilience with open source software&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/blog/telco-bringing-automation-to-open-source-5g-software-at-ubuntu-summit-2024"&gt;https://ubuntu.com/blog/telco-bringing-automation-to-open-source-5g-software-at-ubuntu-summit-2024&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;More reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://canonical.com/blog/what-is-application-security-appsec"&gt;What is Application Security (AppSec)?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://canonical.com/blog/a-cisos-guide-to-application-security-best-practices"&gt;A CISO’s guide to Application Security best practices&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://canonical.com/blog/how-to-implement-zero-trust-into-third-party-idps"&gt;Extra Factor Authentication: how to create zero trust IAM with third-party IdPs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://canonical.com/blog/the-cyber-resilience-act-what-it-means-for-open-source"&gt;The Cyber Resilience Act: What it means for open source &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://canonical.com/open-source-adoption"&gt;Webpage: open source adoption&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/engage/iot-compliance-in-the-global-market-a-guide-for-iot-device-manufacturers"&gt;Whitepaper: a guide to global IoT compliance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/engage/vulnerability-management"&gt;Whitepaper: a guide to open source vulnerability management&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Stephanie Domas (Stephanie Domas)</author><category>Open source</category><pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Canonical Kubernetes officially included in Sylva 1.5</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/canonical-kubernetes-officially-included-in-sylva-1-5</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Sylva 1.5 becomes the first release to include Kubernetes 1.32, bringing the latest open source cloud-native capabilities to the European telecommunications industry. With the launch of Sylva 1.5, Canonical Kubernetes is now officially part of the project’s reference architecture. This follows its earlier availability as a technology preview in Sylva 1.4. What is the Sylva [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;Sylva 1.5 becomes the first release to include Kubernetes 1.32, bringing the latest open source cloud-native capabilities to the European telecommunications industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the launch of Sylva 1.5, &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/kubernetes"&gt;Canonical Kubernetes&lt;/a&gt; is now officially part of the project’s reference architecture. This follows its earlier availability as a technology preview in Sylva 1.4.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;What is the Sylva project?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://sylvaproject.org/"&gt;Sylva&lt;/a&gt; project is backed by Europe’s largest telecom operators and vendors, including Nokia and Ericsson, and is designed to deliver an open, telco-friendly cloud-native framework. By focusing on interoperability, performance, and automation, Sylva addresses the unique requirements of telecommunications providers building Kubernetes telco platforms for their IT, 5G core, O-RAN, and edge services. Canonical is thrilled to be included as part of the Sylva project, supporting the important work of creating an open source cloud-native reference architecture capable of hosting the mission-critical workloads of the telco industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Canonical’s contribution to the Kubernetes telco ecosystem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical Kubernetes brings unique advantages to Sylva’s mission of reducing fragmentation and simplifying operations across telecom networks. One of its defining features is up to 12 years of long-term support (LTS). For operators running critical workloads, this ensures stability, ongoing security updates, and compliance with industry standards over a much longer lifecycle than other Kubernetes distributions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical Kubernetes also provides the flexibility needed for large-scale Kubernetes telco deployments, from core networks to the far edge. Operators benefit from a distribution designed to be both lightweight and maintained with security in mind, while remaining capable of handling advanced workloads such as 5G core, O-RAN, and AI-driven services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="wp-block-quote"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guillaume Nevicato, Sylva Technical Steering Committee co-chair and Orange Telco Cloud Product Manager, recognized the importance of this contribution:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;cite&gt;Canonical is a major open-source player that has achieved the integration of their Canonical Kubernetes distribution into Sylva. They fully embrace Sylva’s full-stack automation, including cluster lifecycle management, storage, networking, observability, GreenDashboard, and security enhancements. This represents a significant step forward in Sylva’s adoption.&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Accelerating the validation of Kubernetes telco workloads&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A critical part of Sylva’s role is validating network functions against its reference framework, ensuring that cloud-native network functions (CNFs) and virtualized network functions (VNFs) perform reliably across any Sylva-compliant infrastructure. Following its technical preview in the previous Sylva release, Canonical Kubernetes is now included with 1.32 LTS in Sylva 1.5. This allows it to enter the validation process with the Sylva Validation Workgroup, covering key telecom workloads such as 5G Core, O-RAN, and distributed edge services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For operators, this means they can deploy Kubernetes telco workloads with confidence, knowing that interoperability and performance have already been tested. Vendors also benefit, since a single certification process ensures compatibility across multiple Sylva-aligned platforms, reducing time to market for new services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Looking ahead: future opportunities for integration&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical is now exploring how its broader infrastructure portfolio, including technologies like &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/openstack"&gt;Canonical OpenStack,&lt;/a&gt; a featureful, highly customizable cloud, and &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/maas"&gt;MAAS&lt;/a&gt;, bare-metal server automation software, could complement Sylva’s approach in the future. These solutions could help create a more unified environment for both virtualized and cloud-native network functions, enhancing the flexibility of Kubernetes telco deployments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Sylva evolves, Canonical will continue engaging with operators, vendors, and the wider community to identify opportunities where its open source software can add value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Building the future of Kubernetes in telco&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inclusion of Canonical Kubernetes in Sylva represents a milestone in the adoption of open source telco cloud infrastructure. Operators now have access to a validated, commercially supported Kubernetes telco distribution that combines long-term stability, security, and interoperability with the innovation of cloud-native technologies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Kubernetes at the foundation, operators can accelerate the rollout of next-generation network functions and services, while benefiting from the reliability and flexibility that only open-source collaboration can deliver.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Next steps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you building your telco cloud strategy? Learn how Canonical Kubernetes can give you a stable, validated, and open foundation for 5G, O-RAN, and edge workloads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Explore &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/solutions/telco"&gt;Canonical telco solutions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find out how to &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/solutions/telco/5g-core"&gt;Transform your 5G infrastructure with Canonical&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn how &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/case-study/nova-telecommunications"&gt;Nova Telecommunications is building its next-gen telco cloud with Canonical&lt;/a&gt; in the case study&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read our in-depth white paper on how to &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/engage/kubernetes-for-telco-performance"&gt;unlock the full potential of Kubernetes for telco performance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://canonical.com/solutions/telco#get-in-touch"&gt;Get in touch with Canonical’s telco team&lt;/a&gt; to discuss how we can help design and support your Kubernetes telco deployments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Benjamin Ryzman (Benjamin Ryzman)</author><category>5g</category><category>5G core network</category><category>canonical kubernetes</category><category>Sylva</category><category>Telco</category><pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 17:37:05 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Canonical expands total coverage for Ubuntu LTS releases to 15 years with Legacy add-on</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/canonical-expands-total-coverage-for-ubuntu-lts-releases-to-15-years-with-legacy-add-on</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu Pro now supports LTS releases for up to 15 years through the Legacy add-on. More security, more stability, and greater control over upgrade timelines for enterprises.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Expansion ensures business continuity without forcing major upgrades&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, Canonical announced the expansion of the Legacy add-on for Ubuntu Pro, extending total coverage for Ubuntu LTS releases to 15 years. Starting with Ubuntu 14.04 LTS (Trusty Tahr), this extension brings the full benefits of Ubuntu Pro – including continuous security patching, compliance tooling and support for your OS – to long-lived production systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In highly regulated or hardware-dependent industries, upgrades threaten to disrupt tightly controlled security and compliance. For many organizations, maintaining production systems for more than a decade is complex, but remains a more sensible option than a full upgrade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s why, in 2024, we first &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/blog/canonical-expands-long-term-support-to-12-years-starting-with-ubuntu-14-04-lts"&gt;introduced the Legacy add-on&lt;/a&gt; for Ubuntu Pro, starting with Ubuntu 14.04 LTS (Trusty Tahr). The Legacy add-on increased the total maintenance window for Ubuntu LTS releases to 12 years: five years of standard security maintenance, five years of Expanded Security Maintenance (ESM), and two years of additional coverage with the Legacy add-on – with optional support throughout. Due to the positive reception and growing interest in longer lifecycle coverage, we’re excited to now extend the Legacy add-on to 5 years, bringing a 15-year security maintenance and support window to Ubuntu LTS releases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;A 15-year lifecycle for stability&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout this 15-year window, Ubuntu Pro provides continuous security maintenance across the entire Ubuntu base, kernel, and key open source components. Canonical’s security team actively scans, triages, and backports critical, high, and select medium CVEs to all maintained LTS releases, ensuring security without forcing disruptive major upgrades that break compatibility or require re-certification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Break/fix support remains an optional add-on. When production issues arise, you can get access to our Support team through this service and troubleshoot with experts who contribute to Ubuntu every day, who’ve seen similar problems before and know how to resolve them quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scope of the Legacy add-on itself is unchanged, but the commitment is longer, giving users additional years to manage transition timelines and maintain compliance. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This updated coverage applies from Ubuntu 14.04 LTS onward. With this extension, Ubuntu 14.04 LTS is now supported until April 2029, a full 15 years after its debut.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="511" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1071px) 1071px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1071/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F75eb%2Fimage.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F75eb%2Fimage.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F75eb%2Fimage.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F75eb%2Fimage.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F75eb%2Fimage.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F75eb%2Fimage.png 1920w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1071/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F75eb%2Fimage.png 1071w" width="1071"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By committing to a 15-year lifecycle, Canonical gives users:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Realistic timelines for planning and executing major migrations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Continuous security and compliance coverage for long-lived systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flexibility to modernize infrastructure strategically rather than reactively&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Infrastructure is complicated, and upgrades carry real costs and risks. This expansion acknowledges those realities and gives you the support duration your deployments actually require.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;A simple path to extended coverage&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Current Ubuntu Pro subscriptions will continue uninterrupted. No re-enrollment, no reinstallation, no surprise migration projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Legacy add-on is available after the first 10 years of coverage (standard security maintenance plus ESM, and optional break/bug fix support), priced at a 50% premium over standard Ubuntu Pro. This applies whether you’re approaching that milestone with 16.04 LTS or already using the Legacy add-on with 14.04 LTS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To activate coverage beyond ESM, &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/contact-us/form?product=pro"&gt;contact Canonical Sales&lt;/a&gt; or reach out to your account manager.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more information about the Legacy add-on, visit our &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/pro"&gt;Ubuntu Pro page&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn more:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/pro"&gt;Ubuntu Pro &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/support"&gt;Canonical Support&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://canonical.com/case-study/sbi-bits"&gt;Read how SBI BITS ensures business continuity with Canonical’s support&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Canonical (Canonical)</author><category>LTS</category><category>Support</category><category>Ubuntu Pro</category><pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 09:11:04 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Canonical releases FIPS-enabled Kubernetes</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/canonical-releases-fips-enabled-kubernetes</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Today at KubeCon North America, Canonical, the publisher of Ubuntu, released support to enable FIPS mode in its Kubernetes distribution, providing everything needed to create and manage a scalable cluster suitable for high-security and Federal deployments.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Deploy a FedRAMP-ready Kubernetes cluster and application suite, with FIPS 140-3 crypto and DISA-STIG hardening&lt;/em&gt;,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today at KubeCon North America, Canonical, the publisher of Ubuntu, released support to enable FIPS mode in its Kubernetes distribution, providing everything needed to create and manage a scalable cluster suitable for high-security or Federal deployments. As of version 1.34, Canonical Kubernetes is available with a built-in FIPS 140-3 capability that uses certified cryptographic modules. Your deployment with this FIPS capability can be easily hardened to DISA-STIG standards using comprehensive documentation when deployed as a snap package. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;KubeCon attendees in Atlanta can learn more about FIPS-enabled Canonical Kubernetes at booth 821. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;What is Canonical Kubernetes?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical Kubernetes is a performant, lightweight, and securely designed CNCF-conformant distribution of Kubernetes. It provides everything needed for a fully functioning cluster, including a container runtime, a CNI, DNS services, an ingress gateway, metrics server, and more. New versions of Canonical Kubernetes ship within a week of the upstream release, and Long Term Support (LTS) versions (which are released every 2 years) are fully supported and security maintained by Canonical for up to 12 years. Long Term Support for Ubuntu and FIPS-enabled Canonical Kubernetes is offered through an &lt;a href="http://ubuntu.com/pro"&gt;Ubuntu Pro subscription.&lt;/a&gt; Canonical’s FIPS 140-3 compliant Kubernetes is also available as part of the NVIDIA AI Factory for Government reference design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Gain stability with the option to upgrade for new features&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical is the first software provider to offer 12 years of support for Kubernetes, which is far beyond the support window offered by upstream CNCF and other vendors. Upstream Kubernetes is typically maintained and &lt;a href="https://kubernetes.io/releases/patch-releases/#support-period"&gt;supported for about 14 months&lt;/a&gt; by the Kubernetes community, with 3 releases per year. In comparison, Canonical  maintains an LTS release every 2 years, in line with the Ubuntu LTS release cadence. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traditionally, Kubernetes clusters must be &lt;a href="https://kubernetes.io/releases/version-skew-policy/"&gt;upgraded one version at a time&lt;/a&gt;. However, Canonical’s “interim” versions will be supported for 1 year past the next LTS release, allowing  customers to upgrade within 1 year of the next LTS release, without downtime, all while knowing their cluster is fully covered by security maintenance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Get reliable security maintenance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each component of the Kubernetes stack is backed by Canonical’s CVE patching service. Our dedicated security team triages all relevant vulnerabilities and backports upstream fixes to the currently supported software versions, ensuring a completely stable base without breaking existing deployments. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Comply with FedRAMP requirements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical has been publishing FIPS-certified cryptographic modules for Ubuntu since 2016. These modules are vital for customers across the Federal sector and for on-premises and public clouds, powering a wide range of FedRAMP deployments. With the availability of Canonical Kubernetes and its built-in FIPS 140-3 mode using certified cryptographic modules, customers will have a faster and more direct route to meet their FedRAMP requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FIPS 140-3 functionality requires Kubernetes to be deployed on top of a FIPS-enabled Ubuntu LTS host Operating System. Canonical Kubernetes enables Kubernetes DISA-STIG, and allows you to deploy onto a host OS hardened to DISA-STIG guidelines using the Ubuntu Security Guide (USG) tool. What’s more, applicable STIG controls can be applied to enable hardened containers, along with embedded FIPS cryptographic libraries. Ubuntu STIG hardening has been extensively tested and deployed across the Federal landscape, making it a proven route to meeting FedRAMP security standards. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FIPS modules and STIG hardening are available with an &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/pro"&gt;Ubuntu Pro&lt;/a&gt; subscription. Ubuntu Pro subscriptions apply on a per-machine basis, which means that any containerized application running on a Pro-enabled host machine is also included within Pro when the Pro token is enabled. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Visit us at our booth 821 at &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://events.linuxfoundation.org/kubecon-cloudnativecon-north-america/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;KubeCon North America&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt; on November 11-13, 2025 for an in-person conversation about how Canonical Kubernetes powers FedRAMP compliant deployments.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;About Canonical&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical, the publisher of Ubuntu, provides open source security, support ,and services. Our portfolio covers critical systems, from the smallest devices to the largest clouds, from the kernel to containers, from databases to AI. With customers that include top tech brands, emerging startups, governments and home users, Canonical delivers trusted open source for everyone. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn more at &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/"&gt;https://canonical.com/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Further Reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/engage/secure-federal-cloud-native-stack-k8s"&gt;Register for an expert webinar discussing FIPS and STIG compliant Canonical Kubernetes &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/canonical-kubernetes/latest/"&gt;Canonical Kubernetes Documentation&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/blog/canonical-delivers-kubernetes-platform-and-open-source-security-with-nvidia-enterprise-ai-factory-validated-design"&gt;Canonical delivers Kubernetes platform and open-source security with NVIDIA Enterprise AI Factory validated design &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/canonical-kubernetes/latest/snap/howto/install/disa-stig/"&gt;DISA-STIG for Canonical Kubernetes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Canonical (Canonical)</author><category>canonical kubernetes</category><category>DISA STIG</category><category>FIPS</category><category>FIPS certification</category><category>Hardening</category><category>kubernetes</category><category>Ubuntu Pro</category><pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 14:45:33 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Canonical announces optimized Ubuntu images for Google Cloud’s Axion N4A Virtual Machines</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/canonical-announces-optimized-ubuntu-images-for-google-clouds-axion-n4a-virtual-machines</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Today Canonical, the publishers of Ubuntu, and Google Cloud announced the immediate availability of optimized Ubuntu images for the new Axion-based N4A virtual machines (VMs) on Google Compute Engine.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;This new release brings the stability and security of Ubuntu to Axion-based N4A virtual machines on Google Compute Engine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;November 6, 2025 – Today Canonical, the publishers of Ubuntu, and Google Cloud announced the immediate availability of optimized Ubuntu images for the new Axion-based N4A virtual machines (VMs) on Google Compute Engine. This collaboration brings the stability, security, and expansive ecosystem of Ubuntu, the world’s most popular cloud operating system, to Google Cloud’s most cost-effective N-series offering, enabling enterprises to maximize the total cost of ownership (TCO) for a wide range of general-purpose workloads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new N4A VMs are powered by Google’s custom-designed Axion ARM-based CPUs and offer up to 105% better price performance and 80% better performance-per-watt than comparable, current-generation x86-based VMs. By integrating optimized Ubuntu images at launch, Canonical helps ensure developers and operators can immediately take advantage of this breakthrough efficiency for demanding workloads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical has long supported ARM infrastructure, helping to ensure that Ubuntu provides a consistent, reliable, and secure experience across heterogeneous computing environments. Our deep experience in solving the challenges of mixed x86 and ARM deployments allows us to bring a robust and fully optimized operating system to the N4A series from day one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The availability of optimized Ubuntu on N4A ensures developers can use the familiar packages and libraries of the latest Long-Term Support (LTS) releases, guaranteeing longevity and simplifying migration. This is crucial for businesses looking to adopt N4A’s cost savings without compromising on operational consistency across Google Cloud’s Compute Engine, Google Kubernetes Engine (GKE), and other services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Seamless integration and reliability from Day One&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These optimized Ubuntu images are backed by rigorous testing to help ensure enterprise-grade stability and compatibility with Google Cloud’s core features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical and Google Cloud have executed thorough validation across the entire image lifecycle, confirming that Ubuntu on N4A performs exceptionally well with Google Cloud services and VMs. This extensive testing includes validation of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Secure Boot integrity:&lt;/strong&gt; Full compatibility and successful execution of google-secure-boot, ensuring the highest levels of system integrity from the moment of launch.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Initialization and configuration:&lt;/strong&gt; Robust confirmation of the cloud-init configuration process, including network, user, and password authentication (cloud-init-password-auth-test), guaranteeing reliable deployment and user setup.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lifecycle management:&lt;/strong&gt; Successful execution of startup and shutdown scripts (google-startup, google-shutdown-script, and their URL-based variants), critical for automated maintenance and application orchestration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Compute Engine feature compatibility:&lt;/strong&gt; Validation of core Google Cloud functionality, including accurate disk resizing (google-disk-size), and general system integration (google-general), helping to ensure that Ubuntu images behave predictably within the Compute Engine environment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This comprehensive testing suite allows customers to deploy Ubuntu on N4A with total confidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Getting started&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get started, simply select the N4A machine type and choose your preferred Ubuntu image when creating a VM in Google Cloud Compute Engine, or when configuring node settings in GKE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The optimized images are available now in the public preview regions for N4A (us-central1, us-east4, europe-west3, and europe-west4).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;About Canonical &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical, the publisher of Ubuntu, provides open source security, support and services. Our portfolio covers critical systems, from the smallest devices to the largest clouds, from the kernel to containers, from databases to AI. With customers that include top tech brands, emerging startups, governments and home users, Canonical delivers trusted open source for everyone. Learn more at&lt;a href="https://canonical.com/"&gt; https://canonical.com/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Read more&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/security/certifications/docs/usg"&gt;The Ubuntu Security Guide documentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://ubuntu.com/gcp"&gt;Ubuntu on Google Cloud&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Hugo Huang (Hugo Huang)</author><category>ARM</category><category>Axion</category><category>Google Cloud</category><category>Ubuntu</category><pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 22:08:10 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Generating accessible color palettes for design systems … inspired by APCA!</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/generating-color-palettes-for-design-systems-inspired-by-apca</link><description>&lt;p&gt;This is the first of two blog posts about how we created the color palette for a new design system at Canonical. In this post I share my journey into perceptually uniform color spaces and perceptual contrast algorithms.&amp;nbsp; If you&amp;#8217;re already familiar with these concepts, skip to this section (or visit the Github repository) to [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;This is the first of two blog posts about how we created the color palette for a new design system at Canonical. In this post I share my journey into perceptually uniform color spaces and perceptual contrast algorithms. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re already familiar with these concepts, &lt;a href="#inspired-by-apca"&gt;skip to this&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;section&lt;/a&gt; (or &lt;a href="https://github.com/dgtlntv/perceptual-contrast-palette"&gt;visit the Github repository&lt;/a&gt;) to see how I reverse-engineered the Accessible Perceptual Contrast Algorithm (APCA) to generate perceptually contrasting color palettes. In the next post, I will share why we didn’t choose this solution and what we chose instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;How humans perceive color&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was nerd sniped by a colleague with this article by Matthew Ström, “&lt;a href="https://matthewstrom.com/writing/how-to-pick-the-least-wrong-colors/"&gt;How to pick the least wrong colors&lt;/a&gt;” about using &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Color_appearance_model"&gt;perceptually uniform color spaces&lt;/a&gt; to pick data visualization colors. At that point, I hadn’t known about perceptually uniform color spaces like &lt;a href="https://bottosson.github.io/posts/oklab/"&gt;Oklab and Oklch&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="768" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1920px) 1920px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_webp,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F8edf%2Frgb-cube.webp" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_webp,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F8edf%2Frgb-cube.webp 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_webp,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F8edf%2Frgb-cube.webp 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_webp,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F8edf%2Frgb-cube.webp 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_webp,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F8edf%2Frgb-cube.webp 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_webp,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F8edf%2Frgb-cube.webp 1920w" width="1920"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Normal” color spaces, such as RGB, are structured in such a way that machines can easily process colors. Therefore, RGB has very inhuman characteristics. If you imagine the color space as a geometric shape, for example, RGB would be a cube. The naive assumption would be that colors we perceive as similar are close to each other in this cube, right? However, this is not the case. Surprisingly, human color perception does not correspond to a perfect cube. Who would have thought?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="768" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1920px) 1920px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_webp,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Ff44a%2Foklch-3d-shape.webp" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_webp,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Ff44a%2Foklch-3d-shape.webp 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_webp,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Ff44a%2Foklch-3d-shape.webp 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_webp,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Ff44a%2Foklch-3d-shape.webp 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_webp,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Ff44a%2Foklch-3d-shape.webp 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_webp,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Ff44a%2Foklch-3d-shape.webp 1920w" width="1920"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perceptually uniform color spaces support human perception, not computers. While RGB’s are consistent in how a color displays on a monitor, PUCs are consistent with how we actually see the color. As a result, their 3D shapes are not perfect geometric shapes, such as the one from Oklch (pictured above). Shocker!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This property of perceptually uniform color spaces, which aligns more closely with actual human color perception, holds enormous potential for UI design and the wider design spectrum. For example, it’s much easier to create color palettes in which the brightness of different colors appears more uniform in the same “gradation”. This potential fascinated me, so I took a deeper dive into perceptually uniform color spaces and &lt;a href="https://www.handprint.com/HP/WCL/color1.html"&gt;human perception of colors and contrasts in general&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;How humans perceive contrast&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the things I learned during my research was the shortcomings of the contrast algorithm currently recommended in the &lt;a href="https://www.w3.org/WAI/WCAG21/Understanding/contrast-minimum.html"&gt;WCAG guidelines&lt;/a&gt;, a recommendation based on the &lt;a href="https://cdn.standards.iteh.ai/samples/16875/4e1bf8a0a2d34083a45e301f1e30884c/ISO-9241-3-1992.pdf"&gt;ISO-9241-3&lt;/a&gt; standard. The author of APCA, myndex, does an excellent job of documenting the &lt;a href="https://github.com/Myndex/SAPC-APCA/discussions/30"&gt;shortcomings of WCAG&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essentially, WCAG produces both false positives and false negatives when it evaluates contrast between two colors. Meaning, WCAG approvals aren’t necessarily accessible because some combinations with high contrast fail and some with low contrast pass. APCA is a contrast algorithm that is more closely aligned with human contrast perception and is therefore much better at evaluating contrast than WCAG.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="740" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 588px) 588px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_webp,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_588/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fe6c3%2Fapca-vs-wcag.webp" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_webp,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fe6c3%2Fapca-vs-wcag.webp 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_webp,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fe6c3%2Fapca-vs-wcag.webp 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_webp,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fe6c3%2Fapca-vs-wcag.webp 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_webp,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_588/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fe6c3%2Fapca-vs-wcag.webp 588w" width="588"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At that time, I also was going to start creating a new color palette for Canonical’s design system. So I expanded my research to include how different color spaces and contrast algorithms can be used to create color palettes. In this context, I also read another article by Matthew Ström on color generation, titled “&lt;a href="https://matthewstrom.com/writing/generating-color-palettes/"&gt;How to Generate Color Palettes for Design Systems&lt;/a&gt;.” This article was one of the most important sources of inspiration for my further work and this blog post; In particular, Ström’s principle of using contrasts to determine color gradations, which made me wonder whether it could be developed further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Generating color palettes for design systems…&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To support my work creating a new color palette for Canonical’s design system, I also researched how color spaces and contrast algorithms can be used to make color palettes. In his article Ström explores combining contrast algorithms and perceptually uniform color spaces to generate color palettes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contrast is one of the most important aspects of working with color in user interfaces (and other media). There must be sufficient contrast between two colors so that people can distinguish between them. Ström believes that contrast should determine the gradation between colors in a palette. Applied to Ström’s palette, this means that every pair of colors with a distance of 500 will have the WCAG mandated contrast ratio of 4.5:1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="768" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1920px) 1920px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_webp,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F53b7%2Fapca-vs-wcag-algorithm.webp" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_webp,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F53b7%2Fapca-vs-wcag-algorithm.webp 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_webp,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F53b7%2Fapca-vs-wcag-algorithm.webp 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_webp,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F53b7%2Fapca-vs-wcag-algorithm.webp 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_webp,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F53b7%2Fapca-vs-wcag-algorithm.webp 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_webp,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F53b7%2Fapca-vs-wcag-algorithm.webp 1920w" width="1920"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a color palette where the contrast between two shades is consistent, it’s easy to choose accessible color pairs. Choose any two shades in the palette that are a certain distance apart, and you’ve got an accessible color pair. You no longer need to manually check all color combinations in your user interface. In an internal survey of designers at Canonical, we found that selecting accessible color pairs is an important concern for designers. Therefore, a color palette in which it is easy to select accessible color pairs seemed ideal for us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="inspired-by-apca"&gt;… inspired by APCA!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew Ström used the WCAG algorithm in his blog post to good effect, but as mentioned earlier, the WCAG contrast algorithm has its drawbacks. I was curious to see if it would be possible to follow the same principle (basing color palette gradation on contrast) but replace the WCAG algorithm with a perceptual contrast algorithm; in fact, even Ström mentioned in his article that it would be an interesting experiment. I found the idea of trying it with perceptual contrast exciting and began to investigate its feasibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So began my journey to create a color palette inspired by APCA contrast algorithm principles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="1854" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1224px) 1224px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1224/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2b63%2Fapca-math.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2b63%2Fapca-math.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2b63%2Fapca-math.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2b63%2Fapca-math.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2b63%2Fapca-math.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2b63%2Fapca-math.png 1920w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1224/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2b63%2Fapca-math.png 1224w" width="1224"/&gt;&lt;figcaption class="wp-element-caption"&gt;The APCA formula&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I had to create a reverse perceptual contrast algorithm. APCA takes two colors and outputs a number between -108 and 106 (where 0 is low contrast and the extreme values are high contrast) to indicate how contrasting the color pair is. Reversing the algorithm means restructuring it so that we can specify a color and a desired contrast ratio to the algorithm, and it returns a color that meets those criteria. Due to its complexity, reversing a perceptual contrast algorithm was much harder than reversing the WCAG algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I knew that the &lt;a href="https://github.com/Myndex/apca-w3"&gt;apca-w3 package&lt;/a&gt; already had a “reverse APCA” function. Originally, I thought I would have to go beyond the capabilities of this function (it can only perform the reversal with grayscale colors). As a side project during a climbing trip with friends, I therefore tried to sketch out the reversal of the APCA algorithm on a napkin myself (with the help of a physicist friend, as I’m not that good at math myself).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="1280" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1984px) 1984px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1984/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F96f7%2Fnapkin.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F96f7%2Fnapkin.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F96f7%2Fnapkin.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F96f7%2Fnapkin.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F96f7%2Fnapkin.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F96f7%2Fnapkin.png 1920w" width="1984"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of the APCA algorithm’s complexity stems from the fact that there are four possible cases and the equation looks different depending on the case. The four cases we need to consider for our inverse algorithm are the polarity (is the text lighter than the background) and which of the two variables we want to solve for (text or background).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So for the inverse algorithm, we need to consider four cases:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Case 1:&lt;/strong&gt; Light text on a dark background, solving for text&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Case 2:&lt;/strong&gt; Dark text on light background, solving for text&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Case 3:&lt;/strong&gt; Light text on dark background, solving for background&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Case 4:&lt;/strong&gt; Dark text on light background, solving for background&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will show my process for the first case. The process for the other cases is basically the same, but different substitutions and signs must be used depending on the case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="1742" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1020px) 1020px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1020/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fe20d%2Freversal.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fe20d%2Freversal.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fe20d%2Freversal.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fe20d%2Freversal.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fe20d%2Freversal.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fe20d%2Freversal.png 1920w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1020/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fe20d%2Freversal.png 1020w" width="1020"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Repeating the same process for the other cases we get the following 4 equations for our 4 cases:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="780" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 895px) 895px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_895/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fa47d%2Fall-cases.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fa47d%2Fall-cases.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fa47d%2Fall-cases.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fa47d%2Fall-cases.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fa47d%2Fall-cases.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_895/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fa47d%2Fall-cases.png 895w" width="895"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, in APCA, all input Y values must be clamped, and the Y value returned as the output of the inverse function must be unclamped. The two functions for clamping and unclamping Y are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="1024" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1260px) 1260px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1260/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fb34a%2Funclamp.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fb34a%2Funclamp.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fb34a%2Funclamp.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fb34a%2Funclamp.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fb34a%2Funclamp.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fb34a%2Funclamp.png 1920w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1260/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fb34a%2Funclamp.png 1260w" width="1260"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After completing all the scary calculations, I was ready to translate it all into code. In doing so, I realized that I had only determined the required Y component (in the XYZ color space) of a color with the correct contrast value distance, but not a full color. So, the formula is essentially capable of determining a grayscale color that has the correct contrast distance to the input color – exactly what the existing reverse APCA function can do 😅.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I took another look at Ström’s article and realized that the Y component was actually all I needed to generate the palettes. So I could have just used the function available in the apca-w3 package… So if you are considering a similar project, you can save yourself (and your physicist friends) the napkin calculations and either use the existing &lt;code&gt;reverseAPCA()&lt;/code&gt; function in the apca-w3 package or my code below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still thought it was a good learning experience to reverse it myself, and since apca-w3 is not completely open source (it doesn’t have a standard open source license), I also thought it would be nice to have an implementation of the reverse algorithm with a truly open source license. I’m not sure if what I did is compatible with the &lt;a href="https://git.apcacontrast.com/documentation/LICENSE.html"&gt;APCA trademark license&lt;/a&gt;, so I’ll refrain from claiming that my result is APCA-compliant. The code for my inverse perceptual contrast finder, inspired by APCA algorithm principles, is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script src="https://ubuntu.com/static/js/dist/prism.js?v=a763671"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;pre class="language-javascript" style="max-height: 600px; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;code class="language-javascript"&gt;/**
 * Constants used in perceptual contrast calculations
 * Inspired by the formula found at https://github.com/Myndex/apca-w3/blob/c012257167d822f91bc417120bdb82e1b854b4a4/src/apca-w3.js#L146
 */

const PERCEPTUAL_CONTRAST_CONSTANTS: {
    BLACK_THRESHOLD: number
    BLACK_CLAMP: number
    OFFSET: number
    SCALE: number
    MAGIC_OFFSET_IN: number
    MAGIC_OFFSET_OUT: number
    MAGIC_FACTOR: number
    MAGIC_EXPONENT: number
    MACIG_FACTOR_INVERSE: number
} = {
    BLACK_THRESHOLD: 0.022,
    BLACK_CLAMP: 1.414,
    OFFSET: 0.027,
    SCALE: 1.14,
    MAGIC_OFFSET_IN: 0.0387393816571401,
    MAGIC_OFFSET_OUT: 0.312865795870758,
    MAGIC_FACTOR: 1.9468554433171,
    MAGIC_EXPONENT: 0.283343396420869 / 1.414,
    MACIG_FACTOR_INVERSE: 1 / 1.9468554433171,
}

/**
 * Removes clamping from near-black colors to restore original values
 * Inspired by the formula found at: https://github.com/Myndex/apca-w3/blob/c012257167d822f91bc417120bdb82e1b854b4a4/src/apca-w3.js#L403
 * @param y - The clamped luminance value to be unclamped
 * @returns The unclamped luminance value
 */
function unclampY(y: number): number {
    return y &amp;gt; PERCEPTUAL_CONTRAST_CONSTANTS.BLACK_THRESHOLD
        ? y
        : Math.pow(
              (y + PERCEPTUAL_CONTRAST_CONSTANTS.MAGIC_OFFSET_IN) *
                  PERCEPTUAL_CONTRAST_CONSTANTS.MAGIC_FACTOR,
              PERCEPTUAL_CONTRAST_CONSTANTS.MAGIC_EXPONENT
          ) *
              PERCEPTUAL_CONTRAST_CONSTANTS.MACIG_FACTOR_INVERSE -
              PERCEPTUAL_CONTRAST_CONSTANTS.MAGIC_OFFSET_OUT
}

/**
 * Applies clamping to near-black colors to prevent contrast calculation issues
 * Inspired by the formula found at: https://github.com/Myndex/apca-w3/blob/c012257167d822f91bc417120bdb82e1b854b4a4/src/apca-w3.js#L381
 * @param y - The luminance value to be clamped
 * @returns The clamped luminance value
 */
function clampY(y: number): number {
    return y &amp;gt;= PERCEPTUAL_CONTRAST_CONSTANTS.BLACK_THRESHOLD
        ? y
        : y +
              Math.pow(
                  PERCEPTUAL_CONTRAST_CONSTANTS.BLACK_THRESHOLD - y,
                  PERCEPTUAL_CONTRAST_CONSTANTS.BLACK_CLAMP
              )
}

/**
 * Reverses perceptual contrast calculations to find a matching luminance
 * Inspired by the formula found at: https://github.com/Myndex/apca-w3/blob/c012257167d822f91bc417120bdb82e1b854b4a4/images/APCAw3_0.1.17_APCA0.0.98G.svg
 * @param contrast - Target contrast value (between 5 and 106.04066)
 * @param y - Known luminance value (between 0 and 1)
 * @param bgIsDarker - Whether the background is darker than the text
 * @param lookingFor - What we're solving for: "txt" (text color) or "bg" (background color)
 * @returns The calculated luminance value, or false if no valid solution exists
 */
export function reversePerceptualContrast(
    contrast: number = 75, // Default contrast of 75
    y: number = 1, // Default luminance of 1
    bgIsDarker: boolean = false, // Default assumes background is lighter
    lookingFor: "txt" | "bg" = "txt" // Default solves for text color
): number | false {
    contrast = Math.abs(contrast)
    let output: number | undefined

    if (!(y &amp;gt; 0 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; y &amp;lt;= 1)) {
        console.log("y is not a valid value (y &amp;gt; 0 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; y &amp;lt;= 1)")
        return false
    }

    if (!(contrast &amp;gt;= 5 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; contrast &amp;lt;= 106.04066)) {
        console.log(
            "contrast is not a valid value (contrast &amp;gt;= 5 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; contrast &amp;lt;= 106.04066)"
        )
        return false
    }

    // Apply clamping to input luminance
    y = clampY(y)

    // Calculate output luminance based on what we're looking for and background darkness
    // You could do these calculations here more DRY, but I find that it is easier to
    // understand the derivation from the original calculation with the if statements.

    if (lookingFor === "txt") {
        if (bgIsDarker) {
            // For light text on dark background
            output =
                (y ** 0.65 -
                    (-contrast / 100 - PERCEPTUAL_CONTRAST_CONSTANTS.OFFSET) *
                        (1 / PERCEPTUAL_CONTRAST_CONSTANTS.SCALE)) **
                (1 / 0.62)
        } else if (!bgIsDarker) {
            // For dark text on light background
            output =
                (y ** 0.56 -
                    (contrast / 100 + PERCEPTUAL_CONTRAST_CONSTANTS.OFFSET) *
                        (1 / PERCEPTUAL_CONTRAST_CONSTANTS.SCALE)) **
                (1 / 0.57)
        }
    } else if (lookingFor === "bg") {
        if (bgIsDarker) {
            // For dark background with light text
            output =
                (y ** 0.62 +
                    (-contrast / 100 - PERCEPTUAL_CONTRAST_CONSTANTS.OFFSET) *
                        (1 / PERCEPTUAL_CONTRAST_CONSTANTS.SCALE)) **
                (1 / 0.65)
        } else if (!bgIsDarker) {
            // For light background with dark text
            output =
                (y ** 0.57 +
                    (contrast / 100 + PERCEPTUAL_CONTRAST_CONSTANTS.OFFSET) *
                        (1 / PERCEPTUAL_CONTRAST_CONSTANTS.SCALE)) **
                (1 / 0.56)
        }
    }

    // Unclamp the output value if valid
    if (output !== undefined &amp;amp;&amp;amp; !isNaN(output)) {
        output = unclampY(output)
    }

    // Validate final output
    if (
        output === undefined ||
        isNaN(output) ||
        !(output &amp;gt; 0 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; output &amp;lt;= 1)
    ) {
        console.log("A color with the specifications does not exist")
        return false
    } else {
        return output
    }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After performing the perceptual contrast inversion, all I had to do was combine my code for reverse perceptual contrast with Ström's code:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script src="https://ubuntu.com/static/js/dist/prism.js?v=a763671"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;pre class="language-javascript" style="max-height: 600px; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;code class="language-javascript"&gt;import Color from "colorjs.io"

/**
 * Converts OKHSl color to sRGB array
 * @param {OkHSL} hsl - Array containing [hue, saturation, lightness]
 *   hue: number (0-360) - The hue angle in degrees
 *   saturation: number (0-1) - The saturation value
 *   lightness: number (0-1) - The lightness value
 * @returns {[number, number, number]} sRGB array [r, g, b] in 0-255 range
 */
export function okhslToSrgb(
    hsl: [number, number, number],
): [number, number, number] {
    // Create new color in OKHSl space
    let c = new Color("okhsl", hsl)
    // Convert to sRGB color space
    c = c.to("srgb")

    return [c.srgb[0] * 255, c.srgb[1] * 255, c.srgb[2] * 255]
}

/**
 * Converts Y (luminance) value to OKHSL lightness
 * Inspired by the formula found at https://github.com/Myndex/apca-w3/blob/c012257167d822f91bc417120bdb82e1b854b4a4/src/apca-w3.js#L418
 * @param {number} y - Linear luminance value (0-1)
 * @returns {number} OKHSL lightness value (0-1)
 */
export function yToOkhslLightness(y: number): number {
    const srgbComponent = y ** (1 / 2.4)
    const c = new Color("srgb", [srgbComponent, srgbComponent, srgbComponent])
    return c.okhsl[2]
}

/**
 * Color scale object with hex color values keyed by scale number
 */
interface ColorScale {
    [step: number]: [number, number, number]
}

/**
 * Compensates for the Bezold-Brücke effect where colors appear more purplish in shadows
 * and more yellowish in highlights by shifting the hue up to 5 degrees
 * Derived from https://mattstromawn.com/writing/generating-color-palettes/#putting-it-all-together%3A-all-the-code-you-need
 * Copyright (c) 2025 Matthew Ström-Awn
 * Licensed under MIT. See LICENSE file.
 * @param step - Scale step value (0-1000)
 * @param baseHue - Starting hue in degrees (0-360)
 * @returns Adjusted hue value
 * @throws If parameters are invalid
 */
function computeHue(step: number, baseHue: number): number {
    // Normalize step from 0-1000 range to 0-1
    const normalizedStep = step / 1000

    // Validate normalizedStep is between 0 and 1
    if (normalizedStep &amp;lt; 0 || normalizedStep &amp;gt; 1) {
        throw new Error("step must produce a normalized value between 0 and 1")
    }

    // Validate baseHue is between 0 and 360
    if (baseHue &amp;lt; 0 || baseHue &amp;gt; 360) {
        throw new Error("baseHue must be a number between 0 and 360")
    }

    if (baseHue === 0) {
        return baseHue
    }

    return baseHue + 5 * (1 - normalizedStep)
}

/**
 * Creates a parabolic function for chroma/saturation that peaks at middle values
 * This ensures colors are most vibrant in the middle of the scale while being
 * more subtle at the extremes
 * Derived from https://mattstromawn.com/writing/generating-color-palettes/#putting-it-all-together%3A-all-the-code-you-need
 * Copyright (c) 2025 Matthew Ström-Awn
 * Licensed under MIT. See LICENSE file.
 * @param step - Scale step value (0-1000)
 * @param minChroma - Minimum chroma/saturation value (0-1)
 * @param maxChroma - Maximum chroma/saturation value (0-1)
 * @returns Calculated chroma value
 * @throws If parameters are invalid
 */
function computeChroma(
    step: number,
    minChroma: number,
    maxChroma: number,
): number {
    const normalizedStep = step / 1000

    // Validate normalizedStep is between 0 and 1
    if (normalizedStep &amp;lt; 0 || normalizedStep &amp;gt; 1) {
        throw new Error("step must produce a normalized value between 0 and 1")
    }

    // Validate chroma values are between 0 and 1 and properly ordered
    if (minChroma &amp;lt; 0 || minChroma &amp;gt; 1 || maxChroma &amp;lt; 0 || maxChroma &amp;gt; 1) {
        throw new Error("Chroma values must be numbers between 0 and 1")
    }
    if (minChroma &amp;gt; maxChroma) {
        throw new Error("minChroma must be less than or equal to maxChroma")
    }

    const chromaDifference = maxChroma - minChroma
    return (
        -4 * chromaDifference * Math.pow(normalizedStep, 2) +
        4 * chromaDifference * normalizedStep +
        minChroma
    )
}

/**
 * Computes OKHSL lightness from a target contrast step using perceptual contrast
 * Derived from https://mattstromawn.com/writing/generating-color-palettes/#putting-it-all-together%3A-all-the-code-you-need
 * Copyright (c) 2025 Matthew Ström-Awn
 * Licensed under MIT. See LICENSE file.
 * @param step - Scale step value (0-1000)
 * @returns OKHSL lightness value (0-1)
 * @throws If target luminance cannot be calculated
 */
function computeLightness(step: number): number {
    // Clip values below minimum threshold to full lightness (white)
    if (step &amp;lt; 50) {
        return 1
    }

    // Rescale 50-999 to perceptual contrast's 5-106.04066 range
    const perceptualContrast = 5 + ((step - 50) * (106.04066 - 5)) / (1000 - 50)

    const targetLuminance = reversePerceptualContrast(
        perceptualContrast,
        1,
        false,
        "txt",
    )

    if (targetLuminance === false) {
        throw new Error(
            `Problem calculating the target luminance for step ${step}`,
        )
    }

    return yToOkhslLightness(targetLuminance)
}

/**
 * Options for generating a color scale
 */
export interface GenerateColorScaleOptions {
    /** Base hue in degrees (0-360) */
    baseHue: number
    /** Minimum chroma/saturation (0-1) */
    minChroma: number
    /** Maximum chroma/saturation (0-1) */
    maxChroma: number
    /** Array of scale values to generate (integer values between 0-1000) */
    steps: number[]
}

/**
 * Generates a complete color scale with accessible contrast levels
 * @param options - Configuration object for color scale generation
 * @returns Scale object with color srgb values keyed by scale number
 */
export function generateColorScale(
    options: GenerateColorScaleOptions,
): ColorScale {
    const { baseHue, minChroma, maxChroma, steps } = options

    if (baseHue &amp;lt; 0 || baseHue &amp;gt; 360) {
        throw new Error("baseHue must be a number between 0 and 360")
    }

    if (minChroma &amp;lt; 0 || minChroma &amp;gt; 1 || maxChroma &amp;lt; 0 || maxChroma &amp;gt; 1) {
        throw new Error("Chroma values must be numbers between 0 and 1")
    }

    if (minChroma &amp;gt; maxChroma) {
        throw new Error("minChroma must be less than or equal to maxChroma")
    }

    if (
        steps.some((step) =&amp;gt; step &amp;lt; 0 || step &amp;gt; 1000 || !Number.isInteger(step))
    ) {
        throw new Error("All steps must be integers between 0 and 1000")
    }

    // Generate the color scale using map and reduce
    return steps.reduce&lt;colorscale&gt;((scale, step) =&amp;gt; {
        const h = computeHue(step, baseHue)
        const s = computeChroma(step, minChroma, maxChroma)
        const l = computeLightness(step)

        const srgb = okhslToSrgb([h, s, l])

        return { ...scale, [step]: srgb }
    }, {})
}
&lt;/colorscale&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And just like that, we can generate a color palette with predictable perceptual contrast based shades:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Shade&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="padding-left:18px;"&gt;Gray&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="padding-left:18px;"&gt;Blue&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="padding-left:18px;"&gt;Green&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="padding-left:18px;"&gt;Red&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="padding-left:18px;"&gt;Yellow&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#fff;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#fff&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#fff;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#fff&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#fff;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#fff&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#fff;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#fff&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#fff;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#fff&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#e9e9e9;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#e9e9e9&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#e4eaf4;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#e4eaf4&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#dfeee1;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#dfeee1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#f4e6e4;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#f4e6e4&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#f2e8dc;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#f2e8dc&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;20&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#d7d7d7;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#d7d7d7&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#c7d9f5;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#c7d9f5&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#a9eab2;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#a9eab2&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#f5ccc7;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#f5ccc7&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#f3d1a9;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#f3d1a9&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;30&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#c4c4c4;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#c4c4c4&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#a5c6fa;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#a5c6fa&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#66e37e;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#66e37e&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#faaea5;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#faaea5&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#f7b666;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#f7b666&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;40&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#b1b1b1;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#b1b1b1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#81b2fe;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#81b2fe&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#32d25b;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#32d25b&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#fd8c81;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#fd8c81&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#f09c1b;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#f09c1b&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;50&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#9c9c9c;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#9c9c9c&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#5a9cff;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#5a9cff&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#00bd43;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#00bd43&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#ff5f58;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#ff5f58&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#d88900;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#d88900&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;60&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#878787;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#878787&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#3083f8;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#3083f8&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#2ba142;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#2ba142&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#f32c34;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#f32c34&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#bb7608;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#bb7608&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;70&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#707070;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#707070&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#2a6ecb;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#2a6ecb&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#3b8343;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#3b8343&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#c13938;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#c13938&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#9a6317;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#9a6317&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;80&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#585858;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#585858&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#2e5892;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#2e5892&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#38643a;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#38643a&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#8c3a37;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#8c3a37&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#754f23;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#754f23&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;90&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#3c3c3c;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#3c3c3c&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#2c3d56;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#2c3d56&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#2f422f;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#2f422f&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#543230;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#543230&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#4b3926;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#4b3926&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;100&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#000;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#000&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#000;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#000&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#000;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#000&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#000;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#000&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex;align-items:center;white-space:nowrap;"&gt;
&lt;span style="display:inline-block;width:16px;height:16px;background:#000;border:1px solid #ccc;margin-right:4px;flex-shrink:0;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;#000&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find the entire code in a &lt;a href="https://github.com/dgtlntv/perceptual-contrast-palette"&gt;Github repository&lt;/a&gt;. I mentioned that I did all this work in preparation for developing a new color palette for Canonical's design system. But in the end, we decided (for good reasons) to go with the WCAG-based approach, which I will write about in my next blog post. So stay tuned 🙂&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Maximilian Blazek (Maximilian Blazek)</author><category>Design</category><pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 12:49:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Web Engineering: Celebrating Our Third Annual Hack Week</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/web-engineering-celebrating-our-third-annual-hack-week</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The Web Engineering team is thrilled to announce the successful conclusion of our third annual Hack Week! Over the past three years, this initiative has become a cornerstone of our collaborative spirit and commitment to innovation. With 126 significant contributions to date, Hack Week provides a dedicated space for our engineers to tackle challenging problems, [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;The Web Engineering team is thrilled to announce the successful conclusion of our third annual Hack Week! Over the past three years, this initiative has become a cornerstone of our collaborative spirit and commitment to innovation. With 126 significant contributions to date, Hack Week provides a dedicated space for our engineers to tackle challenging problems, refine existing systems, and push the boundaries of what’s possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key goals of these events is allowing us to talk with confidence about the true open source nature of our work. We get the opportunity to addressing issues we’ve identified upstream in projects that we use to benefit ourselves and others. By dedicating time to these fixes, we not only improve the stability and performance of our foundational technologies but also empower our team to gain a deeper understanding of complex systems and our dependency tree. The direct engagement with these challenges allows us to truly experience the difficulties firsthand, fostering a unique learning environment. These invaluable learnings are then taken back to our daily projects, where we reflect on the insights gained and implement improvements that benefit all our ongoing work. We are proud of the dedication displayed by everyone involved, and we look forward to continuing this initiative into the future with impactful contributions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year we focused on providing accessibility contributions to our internal corporate message application called &lt;a href="https://mattermost.com/"&gt;Mattermost&lt;/a&gt;. All contributions are listed below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-table"&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/Murtaza-Ax/Color-Converter/pull/1"&gt;Murtaza-Ax/Color-Converter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/mattermost/mattermost/pull/34132"&gt;Mattermost #34132&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/mattermost/mattermost/issues/34128"&gt;Mattermost ##34128&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/biomejs/biome/pull/7749"&gt;Biome #7749&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/mattermost/mattermost/issues/26961"&gt;Mattermost #26961&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/mattermost/mattermost/pull/34141"&gt;Mattermost #34141&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/mattermost/mattermost/pull/34142"&gt;Mattermost #34142&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/psycopg/psycopg/pull/1184"&gt;Psycopg #1184&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/upptime/uptime-monitor/pull/269"&gt;Upptime#269&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/heroui-inc/heroui/issues/5810"&gt;HeroUI #5810&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/heroui-inc/heroui/pull/5811"&gt;HeroUI #5811&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/mattermost/mattermost/issues/34153"&gt;Mattermost #34153&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/mattermost/mattermost/pull/34154"&gt;Mattermost #34154&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/TheAlgorithms/JavaScript/pull/1842"&gt;TheAlgorithms/JavaScript #1842&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/google/adk-web/pull/161"&gt;adk-web #161&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/heroui-inc/heroui/issues/5814"&gt;HeroUI #5814&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/heroui-inc/heroui/pull/5813"&gt;HeroUI #5813&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/TryGhost/Ghost/pull/25183"&gt;Ghost #25183&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/heroui-inc/heroui/issues/5818"&gt;HeroUI #5818&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/heroui-inc/heroui/pull/5819"&gt;HeroUI #5819&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/TryGhost/Ghost/pull/25195"&gt;Ghost #25195&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/upptime/uptime-monitor/pull/271"&gt;Upptime#271&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/edlerd/scrabble/pull/3"&gt;Scrabble #3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/mattermost/mattermost/pull/34196"&gt;Mattermost #34196&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/RDjarbeng/countdown/pull/155"&gt;Countdown #155&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/TryGhost/Ghost/pull/25197"&gt;Ghost #25197&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open source encourages compatibility with standards, making locking users in more difficult. This is why we love the freedom open source offers. Open source software allows for sharing knowledge, gaining knowledge, and practising. It promotes transparency in data collection and software systems. Freedom, therefore, is the gift that keeps on giving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please have a look at &lt;a href="https://github.com/canonical/"&gt;our open-source projects&lt;/a&gt; and reach out to us via the issues if anything is unclear.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Anthony Dillon (Anthony Dillon)</author><category>engineering</category><category>Open source</category><category>web</category><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 11:22:28 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Azure VM utils now included in Ubuntu: boosting cloud workloads</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/ubuntu-azure-vm-utils-included</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu images on Microsoft Azure have recently started shipping with the open source package azure-vm-utils included by default. This change provides essential utilities and udev rules to optimize the Linux experience on Azure, resulting in more reliable disks, smoother networking on accelerated setups, and fewer tweaks to get things running.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu images on Microsoft Azure have recently started shipping with the open source package &lt;a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/virtual-machines/linux/azure-virtual-machine-utilities"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;azure-vm-utils&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; included by default. Azure VM utils is a package that provides essential utilities and udev rules to optimize the Linux experience on Azure. This change results in more reliable disks, smoother networking on accelerated setups, and fewer tweaks to get things running. Here’s what you need to know:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What’s changing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Smoother storage on modern Azure VMs&lt;/strong&gt;: Ubuntu now provides consistent device naming across SCSI and NVMe, reducing post-reboot surprises and easing automation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Better handling of accelerated networking&lt;/strong&gt;: environments using MANA or Mellanox benefit from safer defaults that avoid double-managing passthrough interfaces.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Less image customization&lt;/strong&gt;: the utility and rules that many platform teams previously added now ship in the image, removing one more custom step from your pipelines.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why it matters&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fewer post-boot surprises&lt;/strong&gt;: predictable device names keep fstab, cloud-init and provisioning scripts stable across VM families and reboots.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Smoother NVMe adoption&lt;/strong&gt;: newer VM families lean NVMe-first for performance; built-in rules make that transition painless while keeping SCSI setups working.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Less to maintain: &lt;/strong&gt;the stock image now handles Azure disk naming and accelerated NICs (MANA/Mellanox), so teams can drop custom udev/Netplan snippets and avoid fstab surprises after reboots.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to Get It&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For New VMs&lt;/strong&gt;: No action is needed. The package is included by default in new Ubuntu images.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For Existing VMs&lt;/strong&gt;: You can install the package directly from the Ubuntu archive, where it’s available for all current LTS and interim releases: sudo apt update &amp;amp;&amp;amp; sudo apt install azure-vm-utils&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quick ways to verify&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;azure-nvme-id --version           # tool present&lt;br/&gt;find /dev/disk/azure -type l      # predictable Azure disk links&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Jehudi (Jehudi)</author><category>Microsoft Azure</category><pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 15:02:15 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>