<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Ubuntu blog</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/feed</link><description>Ubuntu blog feed</description><atom:link href="https://ubuntu.com//blog/feed" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>Python Feedgen</generator><lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 12:04:46 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>NVIDIA DGX Spark: The developer’s personal AI supercomputer built on an Ubuntu base</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/nvidia-dgx-spark-ubuntu-base</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The history of computing is a story of incredible change, but not every revolution happens at the same speed. It took decades to downsize the mainframe, invent the microprocessor, and bring computing into personal devices. Today, we are witnessing a new era: the move from massive, centralized AI clusters to powerful, on-device AI PCs. And [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;The history of computing is a story of incredible change, but not every revolution happens at the same speed. It took decades to downsize the mainframe, invent the microprocessor, and bring computing into personal devices. Today, we are witnessing a new era: the move from massive, centralized AI clusters to powerful, on-device AI PCs. And it’s happening at an explosive pace. This article explores why the second revolution is so much faster, and how years of advancements in the Ubuntu ecosystem have helped facilitate this shift.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;NVIDIA DGX Spark: huge AI models running locally&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="wp-block-image"&gt;
&lt;figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"&gt;&lt;img alt="" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 680px) 680px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_680/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F714b%2F1758132002210.jpeg" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F714b%2F1758132002210.jpeg 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F714b%2F1758132002210.jpeg 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F714b%2F1758132002210.jpeg 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_680/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F714b%2F1758132002210.jpeg 680w" width="680"/&gt;&lt;figcaption class="wp-element-caption"&gt;Credit: &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/nvidia-ai_sparksomethingbig-activity-7383656061058269184-Y-Mx?utm_source=share&amp;amp;utm_medium=member_desktop&amp;amp;rcm=ACoAADEwr_sBw6omXnnXyXfg-_rYjVqBRvsnjmk"&gt;NVIDIA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As consumers demand more AI capabilities at their fingertips, a move from massive, centralized GPU clusters to on-device AI is currently happening, at a fast pace. NVIDIA has just announced the availability of DGX Spark for AI developers. The system is designed from the ground up to build and run AI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.nvidia.com/en-us/products/workstations/dgx-spark/"&gt;NVIDIA DGX Spark &lt;/a&gt;brings enormous computing power to the hands of developers. It delivers 1 petaFLOP of AI performance in a power-efficient, compact design. With 128 GB of unified system memory, the Blackwell GPU and the Grace CPU with 20 ARM cores, it can handle AI models of up to 200B parameters. Using &lt;a href="https://www.nvidia.com/en-us/networking/ethernet-adapters/"&gt;NVIDIA ConnectX &lt;/a&gt;networking, two DGX Spark systems can be connected to work on even larger models up to 405B parameters. This setup provides a robust platform for prototyping, fine-tuning, and inferencing large models locally DGX Spark provides a full stack solution for AI developers including the NVIDIA AI software stack to accelerate AI workloads and support an incredible third-party developer ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Ubuntu as a base for DGX OS&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The NVIDIA DGX Spark operating system, DGX OS, is based on Ubuntu. DGX OS makes use of Ubuntu’s established ecosystem and trusted repositories to accelerate development. The Ubuntu ecosystem brings years of open-source maturity in the software stack, especially the software stack around the CUDA runtime and CUDA development tools. Canonical helps ensure a secure computing environment by maintaining consistent updates, patching thousands of open-source packages and addressing CVEs in a timely manner. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu brings three fundamental pillars to enrich the developer experience in the DGX OS:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;1. Ubuntu uses the same kernel for Ubuntu Server and Ubuntu Desktop&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because Ubuntu Server and Ubuntu Desktop share the same core kernel, they are not separate operating systems. This unified foundation allows developers to install server packages on the desktop and vice-versa. As a result, Ubuntu desktop benefits from years of mature development in the CUDA ecosystem on Ubuntu servers.  AI workloads running on massive cloud clusters can use the exact same software stack on DGX OS, creating a consistent and stable development environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;2. Arm support in Ubuntu&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical has supported Arm processors since 2011, establishing Ubuntu as a scalable platform for AI on both servers and devices. This long-standing and consistent support for the 64-bit Armv8 architecture ensures NVIDIA DGX Spark, which features an ARM-based Grace CPU, is fully supported from its launch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;3. Mature package distribution and supply chain security&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DGX OS leverages Ubuntu’s mature package management and resilient software supply chain to be a production-ready platform. It inherits trusted repositories, ensuring software is validated. Additionally, Canonical’s Expanded Security Maintenance (ESM), available through Ubuntu Pro, provides timely security patches for open source packages, which are critical for AI and data science workloads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By building DGX OS on Ubuntu, NVIDIA could leverage the same software that runs on cloud servers for a compact desktop device. This was possible due to Ubuntu’s mature support for Arm processors and its securely-designed software supply chain, which created a stable, production-ready platform and significantly sped up development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;A unified developer experience&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The NVIDIA AI platform software architecture makes it possible for DGX Spark users to easily move their models from their desktop to DGX Cloud or any accelerated cloud or data center infrastructure, making it easier to prototype, fine-tune, and iterate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To give developers a familiar experience, NVIDIA DGX Spark mirrors the same software architecture that powers industrial-strength AI factories. It comes preconfigured with the latest NVIDIA AI software stack, along with developer program access to NVIDIA NIM™ and NVIDIA Blueprints. This means developers can hit the ground running using leading open source AI models and common tools such as PyTorch, Jupyter, and Ollama to prototype, fine-tune, and inference on NVIDIA DGX Spark and easily deploy in the data center or cloud. With DGX Spark, developers benefit from a familiar environment and a streamlined setup experience via a setup wizard that ensures fast onboarding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Looking ahead&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The introduction of NVIDIA DGX Spark marks an exciting milestone in desktop AI computing. As AI continues to transform industries and drive innovation, tools like DGX Spark will play a crucial role in democratizing access to powerful AI development resources. At Canonical, we’re excited to continue our collaboration with NVIDIA, supporting the AI community with robust, open-source solutions that power the next generation of AI breakthroughs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;a aria-label=" (opens in a new tab)" class="p-button--small p-button--positive" href="https://ubuntu.com/nvidia" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"&gt;Learn more about Canonical’s work with NVIDIA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Further reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://canonical.com/partners/silicon"&gt;&lt;u&gt;Discover our silicon partner program&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Canonical (Canonical)</author><pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 14:30:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Canonical releases Ubuntu 25.10 Questing Quokka</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/canonical-releases-ubuntu-25-10-questing-quokka</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The latest interim release of Ubuntu comes with compatibility enhancements at the silicon level, accessibility upgrades and a robust security posture that sets the stage for the next LTS. October 9, 2025 Today Canonical announced the release of Ubuntu 25.10, codenamed &amp;#8220;Questing Quokka,” available to download and install from ubuntu.com/download.  Alongside GNOME 49 and new [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;h4 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;The latest interim release of Ubuntu comes with compatibility enhancements at the silicon level, accessibility upgrades and a robust security posture that sets the stage for the next LTS.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="1080" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1920px) 1920px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2e6a%2FQuesting_Quokka_Wallpaper_Color_1920x1080.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2e6a%2FQuesting_Quokka_Wallpaper_Color_1920x1080.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2e6a%2FQuesting_Quokka_Wallpaper_Color_1920x1080.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2e6a%2FQuesting_Quokka_Wallpaper_Color_1920x1080.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2e6a%2FQuesting_Quokka_Wallpaper_Color_1920x1080.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2e6a%2FQuesting_Quokka_Wallpaper_Color_1920x1080.png 1920w" width="1920"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;October 9, 2025&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today Canonical announced the release of Ubuntu 25.10, codenamed “Questing Quokka,” available to download and install from &lt;a href="http://ubuntu.com/download"&gt;ubuntu.com/download&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alongside GNOME 49 and new default applications such as the Ptyxis terminal emulator and the Loupe image viewer, Ubuntu 25.10 introduces notable platform upgrades, from improved Bluetooth audio handling to expanded support for confidential computing features. Ubuntu 25.10 is the first to benefit from memory-safe implementations of “coreutils” and “sudo-rs,” as well as improvements in TPM-backed full disk encryption and support for nested virtualization on Arm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="p-pull-quote--small"&gt;
&lt;p class="p-pull-quote__quote"&gt;Ubuntu 25.10 is a statement of intent for the next Ubuntu LTS in 2026. Canonical continues to deliver a resilient, performant Linux operating system trusted by individuals and enterprises alike, from makers and developers to Fortune 500 companies, across hardware from IoT devices to modern datacenters. I’m particularly pleased with the progress on memory-safe utilities, and the enhancements to our TPM-backed full disk encryption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;span class="p-pull-quote__citation"&gt;Jon Seager, VP of Ubuntu Engineering at Canonical&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This Ubuntu release is also the first to coincide with a new format of the &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/summit"&gt;Ubuntu Summit&lt;/a&gt;, where viewers around the world can learn about the latest developments in Ubuntu and open source.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="p-cta-block"&gt;
&lt;a class="p-button--positive" href="https://ubuntu.com/download"&gt;Download Ubuntu 25.10 for free&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://discourse.ubuntu.com/t/register-for-ubuntu-summit-25-10/65270"&gt;Register for Ubuntu Summit ›&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;GNOME 49 and accessibility enhancements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="796" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1282px) 1282px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1282/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fb00a%2FUbuntu-25.10-desktop-screenshot.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fb00a%2FUbuntu-25.10-desktop-screenshot.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fb00a%2FUbuntu-25.10-desktop-screenshot.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fb00a%2FUbuntu-25.10-desktop-screenshot.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fb00a%2FUbuntu-25.10-desktop-screenshot.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fb00a%2FUbuntu-25.10-desktop-screenshot.png 1920w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1282/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fb00a%2FUbuntu-25.10-desktop-screenshot.png 1282w" width="1282"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu 25.10 features &lt;a href="https://release.gnome.org/49/"&gt;GNOME 49&lt;/a&gt;. This update introduces media and power controls on the lock screen, improved accessibility and HDR brightness settings. Users will also find two new applications: Loupe, a modern image viewer, and Ptyxis, a new terminal emulator. These additions are part of a broader effort to modernize Ubuntu’s application set. Selecting the “install restricted extras” option in the installer will now enable support for more Bluetooth codecs (AAC) and enable hardware accelerated screen recording in GNOME, further improving performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In line with the European Accessibility Act (EAA), Canonical continues its long-standing effort to make Linux easy for everyone to use. Ubuntu’s App Center and Settings panels come with better support for high contrast mode, keyboard navigation, and screen reading. The login screen also introduces a more prominent accessibility menu, making assistive technologies easier to access from the start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Next-generation toolchains bolster the developer experience&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu 25.10 ships with OpenJDK 25, the latest version of Java, and the latest upstream versions for Python (3.14 RC3), Golang (1.25), and GCC (15). Rust 1.85 will be the default, and 1.88 is also available. A preview of the new &lt;a href="https://ziglang.org/"&gt;Zig language&lt;/a&gt; compiler is available in this release for &lt;code&gt;amd64&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;arm64&lt;/code&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, this release includes a preview of .NET 10, which is the upcoming .NET LTS due for release in November. &lt;br/&gt;Canonical continues to improve the .NET developer experience on Ubuntu with an enhanced  &lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/snapcraft/stable/common/craft-parts/reference/plugins/dotnet_v2_plugin/"&gt;.NET Snapcraft plugin&lt;/a&gt; to improve support for monorepo setups, delivering better developer experience with MSBuild through custom flag attributes. In addition, the popular tools from Powershell on Windows are now available in Ubuntu on &lt;code&gt;arm64&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;ppc64el&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;s390x&lt;/code&gt; platforms through the Powershell snap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Rust-based implementations of &lt;code&gt;sudo&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;coreutils&lt;/code&gt; for improved memory safety&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical is committed to increase the resilience of critical system software in Ubuntu by &lt;a href="https://discourse.ubuntu.com/t/carefully-but-purposefully-oxidising-ubuntu/56995"&gt;adopting modern implementations&lt;/a&gt; of key components like &lt;code&gt;sudo&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;coreutils&lt;/code&gt;. As part of this initiative, Ubuntu 25.10 &lt;a href="https://discourse.ubuntu.com/t/adopting-sudo-rs-by-default-in-ubuntu-25-10/60583"&gt;uses &lt;code&gt;sudo-rs&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a new Rust implementation of the &lt;code&gt;sudo&lt;/code&gt; tool. While the Rust-based &lt;code&gt;sudo&lt;/code&gt; is the default in this new release, the traditional &lt;code&gt;sudo&lt;/code&gt; tool &lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/server/how-to/security/user-management/#sudo-rs"&gt;is still available&lt;/a&gt; for users who need it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The introduction of a memory-safe sudo delivers many benefits compared to the traditional implementation. For users, a reduced attack surface in the sudo tool will improve Ubuntu’s overall security posture. Canonical welcomes users to test the tool and provide feedback ahead of its inclusion in the upcoming Ubuntu 26.04 LTS. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“At Trifecta Tech Foundation, we aim to make essential building blocks like sudo more secure and robust for everyone,” said Erik Jonkers, Chair at Trifecta Tech Foundation. “Seeing sudo-rs landing in Ubuntu is a huge achievement we’re very excited about. We applaud Canonical for pushing for memory safety and thank them for the collaboration over the past months to get sudo-rs ready for the 25.10 release. We’re confident that by working together and taking in feedback, we can make this a seamless shift that will improve security for Ubuntu’s users.”&lt;br/&gt;Similarly, Ubuntu 25.10 is the first major Linux distribution release to adopt &lt;a href="https://uutils.github.io/"&gt;&lt;code&gt;uutils&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;‘ implementation of &lt;a href="https://uutils.github.io/coreutils/"&gt;&lt;code&gt;coreutils&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is a ground up reimplementation of the traditional GNU coreutils package in Rust with like-for-like compatibility and memory safety as key goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Platform security improvements with TPM-backed FDE&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu 25.10 offers &lt;a href="https://discourse.ubuntu.com/t/tpm-fde-progress-for-ubuntu-25-10/65146/"&gt;experimental support&lt;/a&gt; for TPM-backed Full Disk Encryption (FDE), providing a way to ensure all content on the disk is encrypted and inaccessible at rest. A TPM, or Trusted Platform Module is a chip found in most modern computers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="1189" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1609px) 1609px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1609/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F4f25%2FTPM-backed-FDE-Ubuntu-25.10-Questing-Quokka.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F4f25%2FTPM-backed-FDE-Ubuntu-25.10-Questing-Quokka.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F4f25%2FTPM-backed-FDE-Ubuntu-25.10-Questing-Quokka.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F4f25%2FTPM-backed-FDE-Ubuntu-25.10-Questing-Quokka.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F4f25%2FTPM-backed-FDE-Ubuntu-25.10-Questing-Quokka.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F4f25%2FTPM-backed-FDE-Ubuntu-25.10-Questing-Quokka.png 1920w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1609/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F4f25%2FTPM-backed-FDE-Ubuntu-25.10-Questing-Quokka.png 1609w" width="1609"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TPM-backed FDE is a security method that uses the Trusted Platform Module to store cryptographic keys to encrypt the hard drive, making data unreadable without the correct key at boot time. New features include passphrase support and management, regeneration of the recovery key and better integration with firmware updates, alongside stabilization of the core components of the system to pave the way for the next Ubuntu LTS release. Security-focused users can test this FDE implementation in 25.10, but it’s not yet recommended for production environments. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following the initial inclusion of Network Time Security (NTS) in &lt;a href="https://discourse.ubuntu.com/t/ubuntu-server-gazette-issue-1-network-online-target-network-time-security-matrix-chat/56135"&gt;Ubuntu 25.04&lt;/a&gt;, Questing Quokka ships with NTS enabled by default. NTS enhances Network Time Protocol (NTP) security by providing a cryptographic layer of authentication for the time synchronization process. This increases resilience against man-in-the-middle attacks and similar types of security risks. NTS uses Transport Layer Security (TLS) to ensure that time data comes from a trusted source.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Linux kernel 6.17 delivers nested virtualization and enhanced confidential workloads&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In line with Canonical’s commitment to enable the latest features and hardware support, Ubuntu 25.10 ships with the latest Linux kernel, version 6.17. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu 25.10 brings early access to the nested virtualization feature on Arm, following its inclusion in the upstream Linux kernel. Nested virtualization allows cloud providers and developers to run hypervisors inside virtual machines, enabling advanced CI/CD pipelines, flexible testing environments, and stronger workload isolation. Ubuntu 25.10 introduces support of this technology on platforms like NVIDIA Grace and AmpereOne, paving the way for broader use and maturity of nested virtualization on Arm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="p-pull-quote--small"&gt;
&lt;p class="p-pull-quote__quote"&gt;As cloud infrastructure becomes more dynamic, the ability to run securely nested workloads is essential to scaling services efficiently while maintaining strong isolation and operational flexibility. With Ubuntu 25.10 enabling nested virtualization on Arm-based platforms both in the cloud and on-premises, developers and operators can advance development and deployment of this powerful capability. Together with Canonical, we’re accelerating the adoption of secure, scalable Arm-based cloud solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;span class="p-pull-quote__citation"&gt;Bhumik Patel, Director, Server Ecosystem Development, Infrastructure Business, Arm&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This latest interim release of Ubuntu also lays the foundation for native support of Intel TDX with Ubuntu 26.04 LTS as the host operating system. Intel TDX is a technology that creates hardware-isolated virtual machines for confidential computing, making it ideal to support data clean rooms and confidential AI workloads. Ubuntu 25.10 kernels will ship with Intel TDX host support, enabling enterprises to run and receive support for confidential computing on their data centers or private clouds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;New RVA23 profile for accelerated RISC-V adoption&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Ubuntu 25.10, Canonical is adopting the recently ratified RVA23 as the baseline profile for its RISC-V builds. RVA23 helps accelerate the growth of the RISC-V ecosystem ensuring compatibility across RISC-V implementations. This early move aligns Ubuntu with RVA23-class solutions reaching the market, and enables early rigorous testing, bug fixing and issue triage. This effort enables RVA23 readiness in Ubuntu 26.04 LTS and provides the RISC-V ecosystem with a predictable roadmap and target.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="p-pull-quote--small"&gt;
&lt;p class="p-pull-quote__quote"&gt;RISC-V International is excited to see Canonical adopting the RVA23 profile for Ubuntu. RVA23 was ratified to help accelerate widespread implementation of RISC-V among toolchains and operating systems, set the base for high performing modern application processors with support for vectors and hypervisors, and ensure binary compatibility at the application level. Our collaboration with Canonical strengthens the RISC-V software ecosystem and advances the adoption of RISC-V in enterprise applications from IoT to HPC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;span class="p-pull-quote__citation"&gt;Andrea Gallo, CEO of RISC-V International&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Readers can tune into the &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/summit"&gt;Ubuntu Summit&lt;/a&gt; on October 23-24 for a &lt;a href="https://discourse.ubuntu.com/t/risc-v-forward-to-the-future-moving-to-rva23/67249"&gt;behind-the-scenes look at RVA23 advancements&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Next steps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://discourse.ubuntu.com/t/questing-quokka-release-notes/59220"&gt;Read the release notes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://discourse.ubuntu.com/"&gt;Follow the Ubuntu engineering team on Discourse&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class="p-cta-block"&gt;
&lt;a class="p-button--positive" href="https://ubuntu.com/download"&gt;Download Ubuntu 25.10 for free&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://discourse.ubuntu.com/t/register-for-ubuntu-summit-25-10/65270"&gt;Register for Ubuntu Summit ›&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;About Canonical&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical, the publisher of Ubuntu, provides open source security, support and services. Our portfolio covers critical systems, from the smallest devices to the largest clouds, from the kernel to containers, from databases to AI. With customers that include top tech brands, emerging startups, governments and home users, Canonical delivers trusted open source for everyone. &lt;br/&gt;Learn more at &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/"&gt;canonical.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Canonical (Canonical)</author><category>Ubuntu 25.10</category><category>Ubuntu Desktop</category><category>Ubuntu Server</category><pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 09:48:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ubuntu worker nodes for OKE now in Limited Availability</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/ubuntu-worker-nodes-for-oracle-oke-now-in-limited-availability</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Oracle Kubernetes Engine now supports Ubuntu images for worker nodes natively, with no need for custom images 8 October 2025 – Today Canonical, the publisher of Ubuntu, announced that Ubuntu worker nodes for Oracle Kubernetes Engine (OKE) are now available in Limited Availability. This means that OKE now supports Ubuntu images for worker nodes natively, [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Oracle Kubernetes Engine now supports Ubuntu images for worker nodes natively, with no need for custom images&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;8 October 2025 – Today Canonical, the publisher of Ubuntu, announced that Ubuntu worker nodes for Oracle Kubernetes Engine (OKE) are now available in Limited Availability. This means that OKE now supports Ubuntu images for worker nodes natively, with no need for custom images. You can find more detail on how to start using these in &lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/oracle/oracle-explanation/ubuntu-on-oke-worker-nodes/"&gt;our documentation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While applications on Kubernetes run within containers, the underlying operating system and kernel of the worker node still plays a critical role in performance, security, and management. Ubuntu provides a stable, widely-supported and securely-designed host environment that can optimize resource utilization for your Kubernetes workloads. Ubuntu’s familiar tooling also simplifies debugging, maintenance, and integration with existing infrastructure across all the major public clouds, offering a consistent and reliable foundation for your containerized applications. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the availability of Ubuntu worker nodes on OKE, developers can now enjoy a consistent Ubuntu experience across worker nodes on the managed Kubernetes offerings of &lt;a href="https://cloud-images.ubuntu.com/docs/aws/eks/"&gt;Amazon AWS&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/blog/how-to-use-ubuntu-in-gke-on-nodes-and-in-containers"&gt;Google Cloud Platform&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://cloud.ibm.com/docs/containers?topic=containers-cs_versions#cs_versions_available"&gt;IBM Cloud&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/azure/azure-explanation/ubuntu-on-aks-worker-nodes/"&gt;Microsoft Azure&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/oracle/oracle-explanation/ubuntu-on-oke-worker-nodes/"&gt;Oracle OCI – all without having to build or deploy any custom images.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find details on the Ubuntu releases and Kubernetes versions available on OKE in the &lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/oracle/oracle-reference/ubuntu-availability-on-oke/"&gt;Ubuntu Availability documentation&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="706" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1222px) 1222px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1222/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F1cab%2Foke-info2.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F1cab%2Foke-info2.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F1cab%2Foke-info2.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F1cab%2Foke-info2.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F1cab%2Foke-info2.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F1cab%2Foke-info2.png 1920w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1222/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F1cab%2Foke-info2.png 1222w" width="1222"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;The latest step in our decade-long partnership&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu worker images for Oracle OKE users were &lt;a href="https://discourse.ubuntu.com/t/ubuntu-22-04-lts-oracle-kubernetes-engine-oke-1-29-1-released/47501"&gt;first released &lt;/a&gt;in August 2024. Today’s announcement is the latest step in our efforts to make Ubuntu more accessible across a greater diversity of platforms and environments, particularly for AI/ML use cases or to have a consistent experience across on-premise and other public cloud environments. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oracle and Canonical have been close partners since 2015, bringing  Ubuntu images onto Oracle Cloud Infrastructure (OCI). Today, all currently-supported Long-Term Support releases of Ubuntu are available on OCI as images for VM instances (see, for example, &lt;a href="https://docs.oracle.com/en-us/iaas/images/ubuntu-2404/index.htm"&gt;Ubuntu 24.04&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Get started with Ubuntu OKE nodes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are working with Oracle to make Ubuntu OKE node pools a fully-integrated experience. We have prepared specific guides on setting these up using the &lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/oracle/oracle-how-to/deploy-ubuntu-oke-nodes-using-console/"&gt;Oracle Cloud Console&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/oracle/oracle-how-to/deploy-ubuntu-oke-nodes-using-cli/"&gt;CLI&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/oracle/oracle-how-to/deploy-ubuntu-oke-nodes-using-terraform/"&gt;Terraform&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re interested in using Ubuntu OKE nodes,  please contact your Oracle account or support teams to express interest and explore access to this program. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’d like to share any feedback with us or the Oracle team, we’d love to hear your thoughts and experiences, which you can share with us on &lt;a href="https://discourse.ubuntu.com/t/ubuntu-worker-nodes-for-oracle-oke-are-now-in-limited-availability/69584"&gt;Discourse&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/oracle/oracle-explanation/ubuntu-on-oke-worker-nodes/"&gt;Ubuntu on OKE worker nodes documentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Aaron Whitehouse (Aaron Whitehouse)</author><category>kubernetes</category><category>Oracle Cloud</category><category>Public cloud</category><pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 16:31:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>OpenStack cloud – happy 15th anniversary!</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/openstack-cloud-happy-15th-anniversary</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Happy birthday, OpenStack! It’s astonishing how fast time flies – fifteen years already. Yet, here we are: OpenStack cloud still stands as a de facto standard for open source cloud infrastructure implementation. It powers thousands of organisations around the world, across telco, finserv, public sector, IT, research, manufacturing and more. With more than 45 millions [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;Happy birthday, OpenStack!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s astonishing how fast time flies – fifteen years already. Yet, here we are: &lt;a href="https://www.openstack.org/"&gt;OpenStack cloud&lt;/a&gt; still stands as a &lt;em&gt;de facto&lt;/em&gt; standard for open source cloud infrastructure implementation. It powers thousands of organisations around the world, across telco, finserv, public sector, IT, research, manufacturing and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With more than 45 millions of cores in production, OpenStack is undoubtedly one of the most successful open source projects ever. Thus, let’s take a moment to celebrate its anniversary together, review how we got here, and think about what the next 5 years are going to bring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;OpenStack cloud – the early days&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the OpenStack cloud project was launched in 2010, led by &lt;a href="https://www.nasa.gov/"&gt;NASA&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.rackspace.com/"&gt;Rackspace&lt;/a&gt;, it sought to solve a fundamental set of challenges: how to implement a standard, scalable, and interoperable cloud platform for compute, networking, and storage across modern datacenters. Proprietary stacks and vendor lock-in limited innovation; OpenStack’s goal was to deliver an open source, community-driven, and modular foundation for cloud computing at scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical recognized the promise of that vision early on. We committed to packaging OpenStack for Ubuntu, ensuring that operators could use the power of OpenStack cloud on top of the world’s leading Linux distro. Over time, we extended support for OpenStack under Ubuntu’s long-term support (LTS) releases, offering users the desired level of stability, and security updates, now available for up to 12 years under &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/blog/canonical-expands-long-term-support-to-12-years-starting-with-ubuntu-14-04-lts"&gt;Legacy Support&lt;/a&gt;. We also built an automation framework to simplify OpenStack’s deployment and operations, all while actively steering upstream development towards emerging use cases and market needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2014, Canonical formally launched its OpenStack cloud distribution – &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/openstack"&gt;Canonical OpenStack&lt;/a&gt;. That timing coincided with the early “technology trigger” phase of the hype cycle. Many were testing private cloud ideas, and Canonical OpenStack gained traction precisely because it lowered the operational barrier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="900" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1600px) 1600px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1600/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F6bca%2Fimage.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F6bca%2Fimage.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F6bca%2Fimage.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F6bca%2Fimage.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F6bca%2Fimage.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F6bca%2Fimage.png 1920w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1600/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F6bca%2Fimage.png 1600w" width="1600"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;15 years of growth and maturity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last decade and a half, OpenStack has evolved from a “cloud experiment” into a rock-solid, production-proven platform. It has been pushed to its limits in high-stakes sectors: from &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/engage/5G-with-open-source-infrastructure"&gt;telco NFV deployments&lt;/a&gt; to sophisticated &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/engage/ai-on-private-cloud"&gt;AI/ML workloads&lt;/a&gt; and mission-critical &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/engage/sicredi-openstack-case-study"&gt;enterprise cloud environments&lt;/a&gt;. What was once a cutting edge technology is now mature, stable, and trusted by CEOs worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In parallel, Canonical has maintained its commitments: over 5 million lines of code (and many thousands of commits, and code reviews) have flowed into the OpenStack project from Canonical since its initial release. Over the years, we became &lt;a href="https://www.stackalytics.io/?company=canonical&amp;amp;release=all&amp;amp;metric=loc"&gt;the second biggest contributor&lt;/a&gt; – and we’re still going strong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the distribution front, Canonical OpenStack has become a leading choice: more than 500 clouds run our distribution in production globally under &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/pro"&gt;Ubuntu Pro&lt;/a&gt;. Meanwhile, Ubuntu Server has emerged as the preferred OS for OpenStack cloud deployments. In the 2024 edition of the &lt;a href="https://www.openstack.org/analytics/"&gt;OpenStack User Survey&lt;/a&gt;, 54% of respondents reported they run their OpenStack cloud on top of Ubuntu Server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;OpenStack cloud: what’s next?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story of OpenStack is far from being over. With the project &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/blog/linux-foundation-openstack"&gt;now under the governance of the Linux Foundation&lt;/a&gt;, OpenStack is set to play an even greater role in shaping the future of cloud-native infrastructure. Moreover, emerging use cases such as digital sovereignty, AI, and confidential computing will be central to its next phase, and will steer directions for future development for sure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And Canonical remains committed to driving this story, and to the overall OpenStack’s success. Our primary focus remains on modernising its operational experience with cloud-native principles, simplifying its adoption, refining the code base, and ensuring that OpenStack remains accessible to all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These efforts converge in &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/engage/cloud-native-infrastructure"&gt;project Sunbeam&lt;/a&gt; – a reimagined OpenStack cloud that is composable yet opinionated by default, enterprise-grade yet simple to deploy, and capable of running anywhere, at any scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="959" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1600px) 1600px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1600/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F5706%2Fimage.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F5706%2Fimage.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F5706%2Fimage.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F5706%2Fimage.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F5706%2Fimage.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F5706%2Fimage.png 1920w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1600/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F5706%2Fimage.png 1600w" width="1600"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical is honoured to mark OpenStack’s 15th anniversary. We have been there from early days, through every architectural shift, every release, every challenge, and we are more optimistic now about its future than we have ever been before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To OpenStack – happy birthday! We hope that when you turn 18, we’ll be raising glasses of champagne together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To learn more about Canonical OpenStack and Sunbeam, visit the following resources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://canonical.com/openstack"&gt;Canonical OpenStack product page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://canonical-openstack.readthedocs-hosted.com/en/latest/"&gt;Canonical OpenStack documentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Tytus Kurek (Tytus Kurek)</author><category>Canonical</category><category>Community</category><category>OpenStack</category><category>Private cloud</category><pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 07:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The clock is ticking: Ubuntu Summit 25.10 is just around the corner</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/the-clock-is-ticking-ubuntu-summit-25-10-is-just-around-the-corner</link><description>&lt;p&gt;London has called, and the Ubuntu community has answered! This year, the Ubuntu Summit has the ambitious goal of extending its reach to everyone, no matter where they are in the world.&amp;nbsp; The event has not started yet, and we have been blown away by the excitement already! The desire to contribute to the community [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/blog/ubuntu-summit-25-10-is-coming-to-your-circle-of-friends-from-london"&gt;London has called&lt;/a&gt;, and the Ubuntu community has answered!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, the Ubuntu Summit has the ambitious goal of extending its reach to everyone, no matter where they are in the world.  The event has not started yet, and we have been blown away by the excitement already! The desire to contribute to the community with Ubuntu Extended events, remote participation, remote lightning talks and other incredible ideas has been humbling, and inspiring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, with the Summit just a heartbeat away, we want to make sure you have everything you need to be a part of this unforgettable experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="720" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1280px) 1280px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1280/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F8767%2F25.10.UbuntuSummit-X-1280x720-0-00-14-241.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F8767%2F25.10.UbuntuSummit-X-1280x720-0-00-14-241.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F8767%2F25.10.UbuntuSummit-X-1280x720-0-00-14-241.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F8767%2F25.10.UbuntuSummit-X-1280x720-0-00-14-241.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F8767%2F25.10.UbuntuSummit-X-1280x720-0-00-14-241.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F8767%2F25.10.UbuntuSummit-X-1280x720-0-00-14-241.png 1920w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1280/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F8767%2F25.10.UbuntuSummit-X-1280x720-0-00-14-241.png 1280w" width="1280"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Don’t miss out: register today! ✏️&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ubuntu Summit is now a fully remote event. No matter where you are, and how big your circle of friends is, we have a spot for you. Remote registrations are free for everyone. Join us onOctober 23 and 24, 2025, for two days packed with inspiring talks, and stay for the community! There will be exciting interviews, polls, giveaways, FOSS music, and much more. What are you waiting for? &lt;a href="https://discourse.ubuntu.com/t/register-for-ubuntu-summit-25-10/65270"&gt;Register for the Ubuntu Summit 25.10&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;A sneak peek at our amazing speakers 👀&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are incredibly excited to welcome a diverse and talented group of speakers to the Ubuntu Summit stage. Here’s just a glimpse of the people you’ll get to hear from:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Raffaello Bonghi (Nvidia)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eriol Fox (Superbloom) &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Victoria Brekenfeld and Carl Richell (System76)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scott Jenson (Mastodon)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Zhixhuan Wang (ByteDance)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And many more! &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Plan your Ubuntu Summit: The timetable is live 🗓️&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have a stellar lineup ready for you! From deep dives into system profiling, to the heights of autonomous flying 5g antennas, and playing videogames in space, there’s something for everyone. Head over to the &lt;a href="https://discourse.ubuntu.com/t/ubuntu-summit-25-10-timetable/65271"&gt;official timetable&lt;/a&gt; and start planning your personal Summit schedule!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Grow your circle of friends: host an Extended Event 📢&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting with this edition, the Ubuntu Summit is all about bringing the community together. If you are asking yourself how a remote event brings people together, you are in the right place, keep reading. You can host your own “Ubuntu Summit Extended” event! Gather your  local Ubuntu  Community, open source meetup, or group of friends to watch the livestream, share ideas, and celebrate the release of Ubuntu. &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSd0Tm3AVaHeC9g7Iadg_1up3f87Bc1iDSR4pMMcZls7Ok0bbw/viewform"&gt;Tell us about your Extended Event.&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu Summit 25.10 is a showcase for the innovative and the ambitious. Let’s demonstrate that the best technology is made in the open. We can’t wait to see you there on October 23 and 24!&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><author>ilvipero (ilvipero)</author><category>Ubuntu</category><category>Ubuntu Summit</category><category>ubuntu summit 25.10</category><pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 15:16:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Canonical achieves ISO 27001 certification</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/canonical-achieves-iso-27001-certification</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The certification demonstrates alignment with cybersecurity standards that will further safeguard open source products and services for use in the most demanding enterprise environments. Canonical is proud to announce it has achieved the ISO/IEC 27001 certification for its Information Security Management System (ISMS), following an extensive assessment by A-LIGN, a respected certification provider. This milestone [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;The certification demonstrates alignment with cybersecurity standards that will further safeguard open source products and services for use in the most demanding enterprise environments.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical is proud to announce it has achieved the ISO/IEC 27001 certification for its Information Security Management System (ISMS), following an extensive assessment by A-LIGN, a respected certification provider. This milestone highlights Canonical’s commitment to policies, processes and controls that support the confidentiality, integrity and availability of internal and customer data, supplier information, and the company’s corporate infrastructure environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="wp-block-quote"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;cite&gt;“Achieving the ISO 27001 certification is a testament to our team’s unwavering commitment to information security,” said Stephanie Domas, CISO at Canonical. “It validates that our processes meet the highest global standards, giving our customers and partners the confidence that their data is protected with the utmost care and rigor. This isn’t a one-time achievement, but a promise to continuously strengthen our security posture as a core part of our business.” &lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Robust information security for customers&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ISO/IEC 27001 is among the most widely recognized and internationally accepted information security standards. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Benefits to Canonical customers include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data security&lt;/strong&gt; – Customers can rely on established processes and best practices to safeguard data and handle incidents.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Regulatory compliance &lt;/strong&gt;– Customers can demonstrate that Canonical  is certified by an internationally recognized standard to help in their own regulatory compliance efforts. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Commitment to improvement&lt;/strong&gt; – One of the key requirements of ISO/IEC 27001 is continuous improvement. Maintaining the certification means Canonical will continue to improve its security and resilience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;An ongoing commitment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Achieving ISO 27001 certification is not a one-time event – it’s a continuous journey towards excellence. Canonical is  committed to maintaining a high standard of quality and correctness, aiming to continuously improve its  security posture by adapting to emerging threats and new regulatory requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The certification also complements Canonical’s certifications for &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/blog/canonical-iec-62443-4-1"&gt;IEC 62443-4-1&lt;/a&gt;, which governs  cybersecurity in Industrial Automation and Control Systems (IACS), and &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/blog/canonical-achieves-iso-21434-certification"&gt;ISO/SAE 21434&lt;/a&gt; for automotive cybersecurity standards. Enterprises relying on Canonical’s open source solutions can deploy them with confidence knowing they are backed by robust and long-term-supported, open source security processes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more information, consult the ISO certificate available in our &lt;a href="https://trust.canonical.com/"&gt;Trust Center&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Canonical (Canonical)</author><category>Compliance</category><category>Security</category><category>Security certifications and compliance</category><pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 15:05:07 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Fortifying security for Ubuntu on Azure with Metadata Security Protocol (MSP)</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/fortifying-security-ubuntu-azure-metadata-security-protocol-msp</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu now supports Azure’s Metadata Security Protocol (MSP), raising the baseline for VM security on Azure. MSP locks down IMDS and WireServer behind HMAC-signed, identity-aware requests enforced by the azure-proxy-agent (Canonical’s integration of Microsoft’s GPA) using eBPF interception and per-endpoint allowlists. It must be enabled from Azure (Portal/CLI). The package is ready for testing (including via -proposed) with SRUs planned for 24.04 LTS and 22.04 LTS. Start in Audit mode, then move to Enforce once behaviour is validated.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;We’re pleased to share a security enhancement for Ubuntu workloads on Microsoft Azure. In collaboration with Microsoft, Ubuntu now supports Azure’s Metadata Security Protocol (MSP)—a feature that hardens access to the Instance Metadata Service (IMDS) and WireServer. On Ubuntu, MSP is enabled by the azure-proxy-agent package, Canonical’s integration of &lt;a href="https://github.com/Azure/GuestProxyAgent."&gt;Microsoft’s Guest Proxy Agent (GPA)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Why MSP raises the baseline&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traditional metadata endpoints are default-open within a VM. That leaves room for confused-deputy/SSRF paths and sandbox escapes. MSP flips this to default-closed with strong controls at the metadata boundary:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strong authentication&lt;/strong&gt;. IMDS/WireServer accept only requests endorsed (HMAC-signed) by a trusted in-guest delegate (GPA/azure-proxy-agent). Unsigned traffic is rejected.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Identity-aware authorization&lt;/strong&gt;. The agent uses eBPF to intercept IMDS and WireServer requests and identify the originating process and user. It then checks an allowlist before endorsing the request (granular, per-endpoint RBAC).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Safe by default&lt;/strong&gt;. Even if guest firewall rules are misconfigured or bypassed, unauthenticated traffic still cannot reach the metadata services.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For architecture and Azure-side configuration, see &lt;a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/azure/virtual-machines/metadata-security-protocol/overview"&gt;Microsoft’s MSP documentation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;MSP must be enabled in Azure. Installing the Ubuntu package alone does not turn on MSP. Enable MSP for the VM/VMSS from the Azure side (Portal/CLI/template) so requests are validated and unsigned traffic is rejected.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Availability and roadmap&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The azure-proxy-agent package is available now for testing and is in the development series for Ubuntu 25.10 “Questing Quokka.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After we incorporate feedback and verify stability, we plan to deliver azure-proxy-agent to Ubuntu 25.04 (Plucky Puffin), Ubuntu 24.04 LTS (Noble Numbat) and Ubuntu 22.04 LTS (Jammy Jellyfish) through the Stable Release Updates (SRU) process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Early testing on LTS&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Ubuntu 24.04 LTS and 22.04 LTS, azure-proxy-agent is currently available in -proposed. If you’re comfortable testing SRU candidates, enable -proposed temporarily and pin only this package so you don’t upgrade unrelated components. Background on -proposed and SRUs: &lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/sru/en/latest/"&gt;Stable Release Updates&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generic, codename-aware snippet (works for Jammy/Noble/Plucky):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="wp-block-group is-layout-constrained wp-block-group-is-layout-constrained"&gt;&lt;div class="wp-block-group__inner-container"&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;# Resolve codename (prefers /etc/os-release; falls back to lsb_release)
CODENAME="$(. /etc/os-release 2&amp;gt;/dev/null; echo ${VERSION_CODENAME:-$(lsb_release -cs)})"

# Pin only azure-proxy-agent from &amp;lt;codename&amp;gt;-proposed
sudo tee /etc/apt/preferences.d/azure-proxy-agent &amp;lt;&amp;lt;EOF
Package: azure-proxy-agent
Pin: release n=${CODENAME}-proposed
Pin-Priority: 501
EOF

# Add -proposed for this codename, install, then remove it
sudo add-apt-repository "deb http://archive.ubuntu.com/ubuntu ${CODENAME}-proposed main universe"
sudo apt update
sudo apt install azure-proxy-agent
sudo add-apt-repository -r "deb http://archive.ubuntu.com/ubuntu ${CODENAME}-proposed main universe"&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Install on Ubuntu 25.10 (development series)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo apt update
sudo apt install azure-proxy-agent

&lt;em&gt;After installation, enable MSP on the VM/VMSS from Azure (Portal/CLI/template). Without enabling MSP, requests won’t be validated and protection won’t apply.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Evaluation best practices&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every environment is different. If you decide to try MSP, start in Audit to observe behavior, and move to Enforce when you’re satisfied. Many teams simply sanity-check normal workloads and—if relevant—try a basic allowlist. Beyond that, test whatever reflects your risk model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Share your feedback&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please share results (Ubuntu release, kernel, VM size, architecture; any observations) in our &lt;a href="https://discourse.ubuntu.com/t/ubuntu-on-azure-metadata-security-protocol-msp/68388"&gt;Discourse thread&lt;/a&gt;. Your input will help us complete SRU validation and promote azure-proxy-agent to -updates for LTS users.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Jehudi (Jehudi)</author><pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 17:59:55 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Beyond ‘whack-a-mole’ and insecticide</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/beyond-whack-a-mole-and-insecticide</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Designing a new, robust, sustainable, and truly holistic approach to cybersecurity Talk to any cybersecurity expert or IT security manager, and they’ll tell you they’re sick of alerts and issues. For a while now, the industry has slowly been realizing that there’s a better way to improve cybersecurity and resolve security issues in IT without [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Designing a new, robust, sustainable, and truly holistic approach to cybersecurity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Talk to any cybersecurity expert or IT security manager, and they’ll tell you they’re sick of alerts and issues. For a while now, the industry has slowly been realizing that there’s a better way to improve cybersecurity and resolve security issues in IT without taking on an issue-by-issue ‘whack-a-mole’ approach. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, I recently read &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/whack-a-mole-dead-mark-curphey-ssl8f/"&gt;an interesting article&lt;/a&gt; by the co-founder of Crash Override, Mark Curphey, regarding exactly this problem in cybersecurity. The piece highlights how our industry has long been stuck in an endless cycle of reactive threat-by-threat game of ‘whack-a-mole’ that spends all its time on emergencies and nearly no time on the systemic issues that create them – resulting in people who are “drowning in issues and alert fatigue”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;What’s wrong with cybersecurity ‘whack-a-mole’?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main problem with the issue-by-issue or CVE-by-CVE approach is that it’s inefficient, repetitive, and risky. After all, not all vulnerabilities are equal: some are severe and need instant action; others are minor but take major effort to patch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that’s without considering how tricky managing individual CVEs can be. Take for example &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/security/CVE-2025-32462"&gt;CVE-2025-32462&lt;/a&gt;: this vulnerability has a CVSS 3 Severity Score and MITRE score of just 2.8 (low); but when you look at other assessments, like the &lt;a href="https://nvd.nist.gov/vuln/detail/CVE-2025-32462"&gt;NIST NVD&lt;/a&gt;, it has a severity score of 8.8 (High). Our own security team rated this particular CVE as Ubuntu Priority High.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="wp-block-image"&gt;
&lt;figure class="aligncenter size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="988" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1898px) 1898px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1898/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fe67f%2FScreenshot-from-2025-09-23-09-15-47.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fe67f%2FScreenshot-from-2025-09-23-09-15-47.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fe67f%2FScreenshot-from-2025-09-23-09-15-47.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fe67f%2FScreenshot-from-2025-09-23-09-15-47.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fe67f%2FScreenshot-from-2025-09-23-09-15-47.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fe67f%2FScreenshot-from-2025-09-23-09-15-47.png 1920w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1898/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fe67f%2FScreenshot-from-2025-09-23-09-15-47.png 1898w" width="1898"/&gt;&lt;figcaption class="wp-element-caption"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Canonical’s CVE dashboard classified this CVE as 2.8 (low)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, why the difference? Well, it’s due to how hard it can be to assess and triage high-priority items that are sent to you for “immediate prioritization”… only for you to discover the vulnerability has been incorrectly classified, or cannot be fixed by the elements that it points to, or that the severe vulnerability is found in packages that went End of Life several years ago. You can start to see why CVE ratings are sometimes a bit of a ‘chocolate teapot’, to quote a colleague of mine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;What approach is better than issue-by-issue cybersecurity?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thankfully, there are better approaches to cybersecurity than whack-a-mole. In his piece, Mark recommends moving from targeting the ‘moles’ (security issues that pop up unexpectedly) to addressing the ‘insects’ (the systemic causes which attract the ‘moles’). This is what he calls “security insecticide”: building a proactive landscape through better security fundamentals, common libraries, and foundational controls – essentially, applying “insecticide” to eliminate underlying ‘grubs’ which brought the ‘moles’ to your ‘garden’ in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The logic is simple: tackle the grubs, and you tackle the moles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve seen the formalization of this approach lead to some fantastic results. For example, Microsoft’s “Patch Tuesday” elevated the security landscape, transforming end-user patching chaos into a strategic and consistent upstream operation. Now users can draw version updates in a controlled, effective, and timely manner, instead of issuing dozens of patches a week in a program that just interrupts work and makes users unhappy. I mean, imaging needing to immediately apply patches every time something was fixed on every bit of software you use?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even in container security, teams are moving away from constantly patching individual workloads to instead reducing the patching burden of their builds. Their new approach involves using trusted “gold images” from managed container registries that shift control upstream for greater consistency and reduced patching burdens. And in our own work at Canonical and on Ubuntu, we’ve been building a solid foundation that both addresses CVEs &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; creates a more secure environment and architecture that reduces the impact or prevalence of CVEs in the first place. For example, Ubuntu Pro entered general availability in 2023, and now extends its security maintenance across our product portfolio – alongside the &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/blog/imagining-the-future-of-cybersecurity"&gt;introduction of things like AppArmor&lt;/a&gt;, better authentication through authd, and more, which all make the stack more secure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, there’s just one problem with the cyber insecticide analogy. Mark correctly identifies the limitations of Application Security Posture Management as not going far enough – but I’d say this criticism applies to the ‘cyber insecticide’ model as well. We need something &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt;. Let me explain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;The problems with cyber insecticide&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s continue this analogy of moles and insects and think about the average garden: it’s made up of many kinds of plants, diverse soil types, and lots of different critters. Dealing with this complex environment is no simple task, even with ‘root-level, systemic methods’. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, you wouldn’t use the same spray for rootworm as you would for aphids – or maybe insecticide is not an option (if you don’t want to hurt bees or butterflies that pollinate your garden!) Also, your plants aren’t threatened by moles or insects only: they’re also at risk from birds, invasive plants, or voles (which eat roots, not bugs). There’s also the end product to consider: if your garden or produce is soaked in so much insecticide that things can’t grow, what’s the point?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s break down the many issues with the cyber insecticide approach. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Insecticide can be too broad&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Security efforts can affect the entire environment, causing friction and unwanted user/developer behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Insecticide can be not specific enough&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Efforts that are too broad can be too diluted to catch specific threats that require individual action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Insecticides are not universal pest control&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Focusing only on foundational security risks missing threats that aren’t linked to IT (such as social engineering, bad organizational processes, etc).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Insecticide doesn’t solve other systemic issues&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think of things like fertilizer, irrigation, and soil health – simply applying insecticide does nothing to fix those issues. In the same way in cybersecurity, better security isn’t just about focusing on threats or improving the robustness of your codebase and systems; it is also about facilitating faster development, new tool experimentation, and innovative practices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Insecticide can damage the soil and poison the end product&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;High friction in security requirements can create inflexible products and stifle innovation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Sometimes you just need to whack moles&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Critical and high-severity vulnerabilities will always pop up and need immediate fixes – especially as new and entirely unpredictable attack methods are discovered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;The best model for cybersecurity: beyond insecticide, to agronomy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s go back to our primary analogy for a second, to talk about how professional farmers approach problems in their field (literally).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Farmers know that a great garden is more than just insect management. That’s why they look holistically at agriculture across multiple factors  – such as soil composition, micronutrients, environmental factors, and so on – to have healthier gardens that grow more crops. This complex approach is called agronomy, and I feel that it’s a more applicable analogy for cybersecurity. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is because agronomy also understands that a field isn’t a monolith, but rather an complex ecosystem of pH levels, soil types, nutrient content, and water content. It uses a complex array of techniques and tools (for example, GPS, land mapping, pH testing, and soil water content analysis) to significantly increase yields while reducing inputs. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, foliar Nitrogen-Phosphorus-Potassium (NPK) fertilizer application is good, but attending to the micronutrient profile of the soil and demands of the plants is better: in controlled tests, the application of Zinc, Boron, Magnesium, and Sulphur (Zn-B-Mg-S) micronutrients increased yields between 0.5 to 1.8 tonnes per hectare, &lt;a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0378429021001477"&gt;compared to simple NPK-only regiments. &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Agronomy doesn’t just improve yields, or save farmers money, or prevent some crops suffering from fertilizer burn or overwatering – it also improves the health and sustainability of the land itself, reducing the impact of fertilizer, insecticide, herbicide, and so on, on the environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;‘Cyber agronomy’ copies its agricultural cousin by being a smarter, risk-focused, holistic, and systematic approach to security. It’s about thinking vertically and horizontally, understanding the intricate dependencies within your digital ecosystem, to look beyond merely reducing the impact of CVEs and create an operational environment that truly supports innovative, experimental, and sustainable practices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s certainly more work, and it requires a much broader scope. But the outcome is absolutely worth it: a secure environment that fosters growth and innovation, rather than one that’s borderline sterile from overapplication of security ‘chemicals’. It’s about achieving a security posture that’s not just compliant, but truly resilient and enabling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;So, how do you apply agronomy to cybersecurity?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Insecticide is important&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doubling down on fundamentals is still critical. None of this blog is intended to diminish the importance of ‘insecticide’ as a system deterrent to attacks or other cyber incidents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;… but you’ll always need to whack moles&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vulnerabilities are like death and taxes. There will be times when the most effective course of action is just whacking moles for a day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Think like a scientist about risk profiles &lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Farmers don’t have infinite money or time, and cybersecurity is the same. Having zero vulnerabilities is impossible, so your work is all about balancing risks against resources. A solid risk assessment process will help you define what sorts of hammers, insecticides, and fertilizer you need for maximum yield – without stretching everything to breaking point. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Reduce your environmental variation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don’t want to deal with 1000 moles that each need a special hammer. Similarly, you don’t want dozens of different operational or development environments where special tools or approaches are needed to fix simple problems. Therefore, your focus should be on reducing operational complexity by using repeatable base builds (such as charms), set common standards for hardware, software, and services, and source all packages from a single, verified vendor (ideally through your OS). Remember, every unique component makes your systems more complex and time-consuming to maintain. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Double down on training, for everyone&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Security is everyone’s responsibility, and &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/blog/a-cisos-guide-to-application-security-best-practices"&gt;AppSec&lt;/a&gt; isn’t just a bunch of security configurations. Any organization that’s serious about cybersecurity and compliance should have robust, comprehensive, company-wide training that makes cybersecurity a part of everyone’s job. At Canonical, we’ve created a comprehensive white paper to help you handle open source vulnerability management and improve your security posture. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;a aria-label=" (opens in a new tab)" class="p-button--small p-button--positive" href="https://ubuntu.com/engage/vulnerability-management" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"&gt;Download the whitepaper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At its heart, a CVE-by-CVE game of whack-a-mole is unsustainable. As the original article demonstrates, traditional issue-by-issue approaches are just not healthy for security teams with complex systems to manage long term and around the clock – and ‘cyber insecticide’ is a rallying call to a better way that looks at treating causes, rather than symptoms. However, I feel that ‘cyber agronomy’ could be the new gold standard: a new, complex, holistic, and &lt;em&gt;scientific &lt;/em&gt;approach that thinks beyond both insecticide and whack-a-mole to deeply improve cybersecurity in every facet of our work (while still understanding that, sometimes, you still need to just spend a day whacking moles).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Further reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/engage/vulnerability-management"&gt;A guide to open source vulnerability management&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://canonical.com/blog/what-is-application-security-appsec"&gt;What is Application Security (AppSec)?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://canonical.com/blog/a-cisos-guide-to-application-security-best-practices"&gt;A CISO’s guide to Application Security best practices&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://canonical.com/blog/how-to-implement-zero-trust-into-third-party-idps"&gt;Extra Factor Authentication: how to create zero trust IAM with third-party IdPs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Stephanie Domas (Stephanie Domas)</author><category>Hardening</category><category>Security</category><pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Mythbusting the scope of Livepatch protection</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/mythbusting-the-scope-of-livepatch-protection</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this article is to share the technical realities of security patching for the Linux kernel, and the intended scope of the Linux kernel&amp;#8217;s livepatch capability. We’ll cover when kernel live patching is most appropriate, and when updating deb and snap packages and then rebooting is the best option.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The purpose of this article is to share the technical realities of security patching for the Linux kernel, and the intended scope of the Linux kernel’s livepatch capability. We’ll cover when kernel live patching is most appropriate, and when updating deb and snap packages and then rebooting is the best option. &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="634" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1440px) 1440px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1440/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F1d0b%2Flivepatch-mythbusting.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F1d0b%2Flivepatch-mythbusting.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F1d0b%2Flivepatch-mythbusting.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F1d0b%2Flivepatch-mythbusting.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F1d0b%2Flivepatch-mythbusting.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F1d0b%2Flivepatch-mythbusting.png 1920w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1440/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F1d0b%2Flivepatch-mythbusting.png 1440w" width="1440"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/security/livepatch"&gt;Canonical Livepatch&lt;/a&gt; is a service that allows Ubuntu long-term support (LTS) users to apply critical kernel security patches without rebooting. Canonical Livepatch delivers live, rebootless security updates for high-priority kernel vulnerabilities on Ubuntu LTS, and is included with &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/pro"&gt;Ubuntu Pro&lt;/a&gt;. Ubuntu Pro is a subscription for security, hardening, compliance, and support for open source software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this article, we’ll run through Livepatch in more detail, in order to bust the myths that often arise around the subject of kernel live patching. We’ll highlight when live patching is the most effective option, and run through instances where a reboot is the more appropriate option. Crucially, we’ll explain why live patching complements updating deb packages and then rebooting, and why live patching isn’t a full-on replacement for patching all &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/security/cves"&gt;CVEs&lt;/a&gt; in all situations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical Livepatch is built for Ubuntu LTS, and is tightly coupled with the application binary interface (ABI), the layer between user-space applications and the operating system’s kernel. Extensible Firmware Interface (EFI) Secure Boot and Linux Kernel Lockdown are complementary security features that work together to protect the boot process and the running kernel, and Canonical Livepatch conforms with these standardized security processes and their chain of trust requirements. Canonical Livepatch does not insert updates through proprietary or nonstandard mechanisms that bypass these kernel lockdown rules, and guarantees the updates only come from a trusted publisher. Enterprises using Ubuntu choose Canonical Livepatch for this precise integration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;a aria-label=" (opens in a new tab)" class="p-button--small p-button--positive" href="https://ubuntu.com/security/livepatch#get-in-touch" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"&gt;Contact us to get started&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Myth #1: every vulnerability should be live patched&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A common misunderstanding we encounter is that live patching is desirable for every CVE, in every situation. However, not every CVE requires urgent attention or can be safely live patched without increasing operational risk. Live patching the kernel in memory is an exploit window mitigation solution, and is not a comparable substitute for installing software updates with apt, snap, or Landscape. Indeed, as others suggest, live patching 90-95% of vulnerabilities would be impractical, and doing this could introduce operational risks that hang machines. It’s likely that users are left looking for rollback capabilities, when this happens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical Livepatch patches kernel vulnerabilities with critical and high Common Vulnerability Scoring System (&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/security/cves/about#cvss-scores"&gt;CVSS&lt;/a&gt;) and &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/security/cves/about#priority"&gt;Ubuntu Priority&lt;/a&gt; ratings. Canonical targets vulnerabilities that have security implications, such as privilege escalation or remote code execution, and are practical to patch safely in-memory. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, Canonical Livepatch does not patch userspace libraries like OpenSSL or glibc, because that is the responsibility of &lt;a href="https://manpages.ubuntu.com/manpages/en/man8/unattended-upgrade.8.html"&gt;unattended-upgrades&lt;/a&gt; or a systems management tool, like &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/landscape"&gt;Canonical Landscape&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Myth #2: Live patches can trap you in a patched state&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two primary approaches to kernel live patching: incremental and cumulative patching. Incremental live patching stacks one security update upon another, and patching live-running code with in-memory overrides on an incremental basis can become fragile over long periods, especially when these updates are stacked in perpetuity without prior testing on a variety of hardware configurations. In this scenario, it’s understandable why readers believe in the need for rollback functionality, in order to resolve any unexpected interactions between patches, which can cause instability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, Canonical Livepatch eliminates the risk of instability by providing cumulative patches instead of stacking incremental ones, which makes rollbacks unnecessary in practice. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="1024" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536px) 1536px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1536/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Faaae%2Fimage.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Faaae%2Fimage.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Faaae%2Fimage.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Faaae%2Fimage.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Faaae%2Fimage.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Faaae%2Fimage.png 1920w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1536/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Faaae%2Fimage.png 1536w" width="1536"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before being published, Canonical runs every livepatch through the same testing and rigor as their kernel packages. Each patch is tested cumulatively with previous patches on real hardware, without emulation. Livepatch Client downloads a single cumulative patch for the running kernel. In practice, the failure rate of Canonical Livepatch deployments is vanishingly small, and for Canonical Livepatch, reboots remain the safest and most sensible rollback path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Myth #3: Live kernel patching is always preferable to installing updates and then rebooting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in our introduction, you should see live patching and installing an updated kernel package followed by rebooting as two security patching methods which complement each other – not as two alternate approaches to security. Canonical Livepatch provides a timely, quick solution to critical CVEs, as these need to be actioned immediately. By patching in the live kernel, Canonical Livepatch shrinks the exploit window for a given CVE and keeps your customers safe, without requiring a reboot associated with deb or snap package updates for the kernel. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, Canonical Livepatch is not a replacement for updating the kernel package and then rebooting. It is a tool that gives you more control by preventing a required unscheduled deb or snap kernel package update and reboot. Indeed, updating the kernel deb or snap package and then rebooting on a schedule is the responsible approach for security hygiene. No enterprise Linux operating system publisher recommends avoiding reboots indefinitely. Kernel modules like NVIDIA drivers often can’t be reloaded safely without updating deb packages and rebooting. In some edge cases, kernel updates can’t be livepatched due to ABI changes or complex restructuring. Security vulnerabilities exist in userland packages, and installing security patches and restarting services is not sufficient (or applicable) in certain situations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;libc6 is fundamental to virtually every process on a Linux system, and is packaged as glibc on Ubuntu. Even small security patches require restarting all linked processes, or more practically, a reboot. When updating libc6 even if services are restarted manually, some processes such as systemd, won’t reload libc6 cleanly. True safety comes with rebooting after updating standard libraries.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Intel and AMD microcode in the cpu-microcode package is loaded at boot or via a special mechanism at runtime. Runtime updates apply to cores already idle, or not running privileged code. To fully ensure all cores and threads operate with the updated microcode, updating the deb or snap package and then rebooting is required. The Spectre and Meltdown vulnerabilities were remediated with cpu-microcode updates.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The systemd and init packages are critical to system management, if vulnerabilities exist here. Mitigations for systemd require a restart of PID 1, which is impractical without rebooting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;dbus is a package responsible for inter-process communication (IPC) that allows applications to communicate with each other, and updating the deb package and then rebooting ensures a clean state.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;udev is a package which monitors kernel events and applies rules to create, configure, and control device nodes in the &lt;code&gt;/dev&lt;/code&gt; directory. Changes to udev (by way of installing a software update) require a reboot to ensure consistency.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Patches to crypto libraries such as openssl, gnutls, and libssl require restarting all dependent processes, after updating deb packages. Technically no system reboot is required, but practically it’s safer and faster to reboot after updating libraries, than to manually hunt down and restart everything safely.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Updates to hypervisors require restarting running virtual machines. Rebooting hypervisor hosts is often preferred, operationally.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Patches to display servers such as xorg and wayland require restarting the session, potentially disrupting desktop environments. While this is not a full reboot, it is disruptive enough that in practice it might as well be.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reboots cleanly flush accumulated state inconsistencies from memory leaks, hung file handles, and other problems that could fester with long uptime. Eliminating reboots would expose any operating system to these inefficiencies over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, trying to avoid &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; reboots results in incomplete security patching coverage, and leads to fragile patching strategies that involve service restarts and error prone dependency tracing. Rebooting provides a guaranteed clean slate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kernel live patching is part of a broader security strategy. Kernel live patching is not a replacement for traditional patch management, which includes updating deb packages and then rebooting, and defense-in-depth – however, tools like Canonical Livepatch provide you with more control over when, and how, reboots occur for the most critical vulnerabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-table"&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Component&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reboot Required after patching?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Frequency Recommendation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Kernel updates&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;When critical and high CVEs are patched.&lt;br/&gt;Every May and November if Livepatch is enabled, after each Ubuntu release.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;CPU Microcode updates&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;When updated.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;glibc, libssl, systemd, and dbus updates&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;When updated.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Container runtimes&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Restart containers, reboot only if needed.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Userland apps&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Sometimes&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Restarting services individually may be sufficient.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To ensure the highest levels of security, stability, and integrity in your Linux servers, performing periodic routine maintenance that includes deb package updates and a system reboot is not just recommended, it is essential. Annual, bi-annual, and more frequent security patching strategies and their respective pros and cons are covered in the “&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/engage/patching-automations-best-practices"&gt;Best Practices for Scheduling Security Patching Automation&lt;/a&gt;” webinar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical Livepatch is provided as part of Ubuntu Pro, a subscription which also includes other security patching solutions that cover over 30,000 open source software titles and their 100,000+ package dependencies, for up to 12 years. Organizations value Canonical’s transparency around testing and process, and trust Canonical’s machinery to build their kernels. That’s why organizations trust Canonical to use that same testing, process, and machinery to publish kernel livepatches. As the publisher and maintainer of Ubuntu, Canonical’s Ubuntu Pro bundle which includes Landscape and Livepatch is a smart fit for any organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To find out more about Canonical Livepatch, what customers have to say about it, and how you can enable it in your organization, visit our &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/security/livepatch"&gt;Livepatch page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Further reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://assets.ubuntu.com/v1/58f8d1e5-Livepatch_Datasheet.pdf"&gt;The Canonical Livepatch datasheet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://canonical.com/blog/an-overview-of-live-kernel-patching"&gt;Blog: An overview of live kernel patching &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/engage/patching-automations-best-practices"&gt;Webinar: Best practices for scheduling security patching automation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/pro"&gt;Webpage: Ubuntu Pro&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/landscape"&gt;Landscape&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Rajan Patel (Rajan Patel)</author><category>kernel</category><category>livepatch</category><pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 03:12:48 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How to build an awesome cloud gaming platform with Anbox Cloud</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/how-to-build-an-awesome-cloud-gaming-platform-with-anbox-cloud</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Why cloud gaming? Cloud gaming is changing the way we play. Instead of buying expensive hardware, players stream games from the cloud, like Netflix for games. This is no longer a futuristic idea, it&amp;#8217;s here. Services like NVIDIA GeForce Now, Sony PS Plus, and Xbox Cloud Gaming have shown what&amp;#8217;s possible: playing high-end games on [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Why cloud gaming?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cloud gaming is changing the way we play. Instead of buying expensive hardware, players stream games from the cloud, like Netflix for games.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is no longer a futuristic idea, it’s here. Services like NVIDIA GeForce Now, Sony PS Plus, and Xbox Cloud Gaming have shown what’s possible: playing high-end games on low-end devices by streaming all of your favorite games – from indie to AAA – from powerful cloud servers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But cloud gaming isn’t just about running games in the cloud. It’s about freeing players from hardware. Your phone becomes a console. Your laptop that doesn’t even have a dedicated GPU becomes a gaming rig. And to pull that off, your platform has to nail:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Responsiveness: ideally zero input lag, as if you were playing locally&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Availability: spin up sessions on demand, anywhere, as fast as possible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Security: isolated sessions, encrypted streams&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consistency: the same experience whatever the device&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Building your own cloud gaming platform is hard. Games are resource-hungry and GPU-intensive. Networks are messy and unreliable. Players have high expectations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the question is: &lt;em&gt;how do you deliver that experience reliably, at scale?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this blueprint, we’ll cover how to build a robust, scalable, and responsive cloud gaming platform using &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/anbox-cloud"&gt;Anbox Cloud&lt;/a&gt;, so you can stream Android games to any device, anywhere, with low latency, zero installs, and high scalability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Core concepts to get straight&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before you even think about spinning up a container or a VM, make sure that the following items are in place:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;1. Sessions are ephemeral, but progress is persistent&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A player’s game session is short-lived. Just like for Netflix, you don’t download a full movie to keep on your machine. You don’t “install” a game. You boot into a fresh, isolated environment, stream the gameplay, then free the session. That being said, depending on the game, a player expects to be able to load back into the same position they were in when they ended their session. Make sure that you properly store your users’ progress – they’ll never forgive you if they spent hours grinding and you didn’t save it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;2. Input latency is everything&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From trying multiple game streaming solutions myself, this is the most difficult part to get right. Sub-100ms round trip is your goal. Every ms counts. Stream too slow? Rage-quit. So your whole stack; codecs, transport protocols, even down to the server location, needs to be tuned for speed, not just stability. Of course, the “last mile” is beyond your control, from the end device to the Wi-Fi quality. Your role is to optimize every step preceding that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Worse than input latency is latency consistency. Any game turns into a nightmare once latency starts spiking: frames stall, timing breaks down, and you lose the ability to predict when inputs will land. That’s why you can’t just think about speed, you also need a plan for packet loss. &lt;a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/rfc4588#section-6.3"&gt;Retransmissions&lt;/a&gt; sound like a good idea, but if a packet is already late, resending it will make things worse. &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=igm7QkqxHqk"&gt;Forward Error Correction&lt;/a&gt; (FEC) solves this by adding redundancy upfront to allow the rebuild of missing data instantly. Anbox Cloud goes further with FlexFEC, a dynamic controller that adapts FEC overhead in real time based on packet loss feedback, round-trip time, available bitrate, and observed loss patterns. The result: you trade a bit of bandwidth for stability, letting the session degrade gracefully instead of stalling, giving you smoother gameplay under messy real-world Wi-Fi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;3. Modularity is good&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a natural boundary between:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Session control (your backend): user auth, matchmaking, orchestration&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Session execution (game workload, container): the isolated runtime (Android, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Session delivery (streaming stack): encode + stream to the player&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep those separate, and your system will scale and stay sane – and hopefully you will too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;What a cloud gaming platform looks like&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s paint the picture:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="1243" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1175px) 1175px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1175/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F7896%2Fimage.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F7896%2Fimage.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F7896%2Fimage.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F7896%2Fimage.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F7896%2Fimage.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F7896%2Fimage.png 1920w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1175/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F7896%2Fimage.png 1175w" width="1175"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Simplified architecture diagram of a cloud gaming platform&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’re gluing all this together with automation and efficient architecture and interface design. Ideally, the player should never know what’s under the hood. Just click and play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Building it (step by step)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s how to go from nothing to a working, scalable cloud gaming platform with Anbox Cloud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;1. Preparing the infrastructure&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ll need machines capable of running GPU-accelerated container workloads. These can be cloud VMs with NVIDIA GPUs, or bare-metal servers for maximum control and lower latency. Ubuntu 24.04 LTS is a solid base, with LXD and NVIDIA drivers installed. Anbox Cloud uses LXD containers with GPU acceleration, so everything rides on proper infrastructure underneath.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have two options for provisioning:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://canonical.com/microcloud"&gt;MicroCloud&lt;/a&gt; gives you a quick, opinionated stack that works well for edge deployments or small clusters. It’s easy to set up and fully integrated with Canonical’s ecosystem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://canonical.com/maas"&gt;MAAS&lt;/a&gt; gives you more control over bare-metal servers, especially across data centers or large-scale deployments. If you want to treat your physical GPUs like a cloud, MAAS is the way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether you’re using AWS, GCP, on-prem, or your own rack of GPUs, your goal is the same: provision a pool of hosts ready to run Android containers with minimal latency and predictable performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;2. Deploy Anbox Cloud&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With infrastructure in place, it’s time to bring Anbox Cloud online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anbox Cloud has a control plane (API, scheduler, gateway, media relay) and execution nodes where games run in containers. You deploy the control plane using Juju, Canonical’s service orchestration tool. It works across public clouds and bare metal, and makes deploying the entire stack repeatable and clean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo snap install --channel=3/stable juju
juju clouds
juju add-credential aws
juju bootstrap aws my-controller
juju add-model anbox-cloud&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the next steps (attaching your Ubuntu Pro subscription, deploying Anbox Cloud itself), follow the &lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/anbox-cloud/howto/install/deploy-juju/"&gt;official documentation&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;3. Upload a game&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can now push any Android APK into the platform. Anbox Cloud will wrap it into an image, launch a container, and stream the session.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s as easy as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;amc application create &amp;lt;path/to/application_content&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Follow the full documentation here: &lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/anbox-cloud/howto/application/create-application/"&gt;https://documentation.ubuntu.com/anbox-cloud/howto/application/create-application/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;4. Start a game session&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the application is uploaded, you can spin up a container, expose a WebRTC stream, and get a session URL back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s the first playable experience, running end to end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;From prototype to production&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve proven that a single game can stream end-to-end, the challenge becomes scaling it into a real platform. Your backend is now the brain of the operation: it decides when to start sessions, assigns users to containers, tracks play time, and cleans up when sessions end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Authentication, orchestration, matchmaking, all of this sits outside Anbox Cloud but plugs directly into its API. Whether you build with Django, Node.js, or Go, your backend isn’t just about launching sessions. It needs to handle dropped users, idle timeouts, reconnects, and the glue logic that makes your platform production-grade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The frontend is the player’s window into all of this. It doesn’t have to be flashy, just fast and responsive. Click “play,” get a session, and stream immediately. A web client works well, but any modern stack with WebRTC support can deliver. The key is adaptation: touch on mobile, mouse and keyboard on desktop, and controller support for those who expect it. Don’t overengineer on day one but make sure to get the stream stable, then evolve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;UX &amp;amp; scale considerations&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now comes the part that separates a demo from something players actually want to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Startup time is the first killer. Users don’t wait. If it takes ten seconds to boot a container, you’ve already lost them. Keep popular games “warm” by preloading and caching aggressively. Reuse layers wherever possible so that “click to play” really means play, not fetch and wait.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Video quality is the second test. Networks fluctuate, especially on mobile. Bitrate and resolution need to adapt seamlessly. Video quality can’t drop when someone switches from Wi-Fi to 4G or vice versa. Adaptive streaming and fallback modes inform the player that their session is still active.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then there’s latency, which you already know, is everything. Keep it under 100ms round trip and more importantly consistent, or it starts to feel broken and unusable. That’s why TURN server placement, fast negotiation, and regional hosting aren’t luxuries, they’re survival.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, when things go wrong, hide the plumbing. Reconnects shouldn’t feel like crashes. The game should feel continuous even when the network isn’t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sessions are ephemeral, but the experience should feel solid. Each player isolated, every stream encrypted, containers wiped clean at the end. That’s how you earn trust while scaling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Why this works&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This architecture isn’t magic, it’s modular. You’re not building a streaming platform from scratch. You’re assembling it from parts that are built to scale: &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/anbox-cloud"&gt;Anbox Cloud&lt;/a&gt; for the Android runtime and streaming layer, &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/lxd"&gt;LXD&lt;/a&gt; for containers, &lt;a href="https://juju.is/"&gt;Juju&lt;/a&gt; for orchestration, &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/maas"&gt;MAAS&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/microcloud"&gt;MicroCloud&lt;/a&gt; for infrastructure that works wherever you need it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s fast, securely maintained, scalable, and you stay in control. You can improve it, and own the experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s what players expect. That’s what your stack needs to deliver.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;FAQ&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Can I use this for non-gaming apps?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Yes. Any Android app works: productivity, education, even legacy enterprise tools. If it runs on Android, it runs here. And it streams just the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How scalable is this?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br/&gt;It scales horizontally. Add GPU-backed hosts, and you scale linearly with demand. No need to re-architect anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Can I run it on-prem instead of cloud?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Absolutely. That’s where MAAS or MicroCloud come in: same stack, just closer to your users or in your own data center.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Is it really better than using VMs?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br/&gt;For cloud gaming, yes. Containers start faster, use less memory, and are easier to manage at scale. If you’re thinking VMs are more “practical”, you’re probably building the wrong kind of platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Conclusion: Why Anbox Cloud?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because building cloud gaming from the ground up is hard, and you shouldn’t have to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anbox Cloud gives you the core building blocks: native Android containers, real-time streaming with WebRTC, GPU acceleration, and full automation capabilities. It scales horizontally with LXD and Juju, runs securely in isolated containers, and streams to any browser or device.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’re building a seamless gaming experience, assembling a production-ready platform, using open tools you control. With Anbox Cloud, you get the foundation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rest is yours to define. Focus on the player experience, your unique features, your business logic, not the infrastructure. When it works right, players won’t ask how it works, they’ll just play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Got a project idea? &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/anbox-cloud#get-in-touch"&gt;Connect with our team to explore it together.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Android is a trademark of Google LLC. Anbox Cloud uses assets available through the Android Open Source Project.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Bertrand Boisseau (Bertrand Boisseau)</author><category>Anbox</category><category>anbox cloud</category><category>Anbox Cloud Appliance</category><pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Canonical achieves IEC 62443-4-1 compliance in Industrial Automation and Control Systems</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/canonical-iec-62443-4-1</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Canonical is proud to announce it has achieved compliance with IEC 62443-4-1 for cybersecurity in Industrial Automation and Control Systems (IACS). Building on Canonical’s existing ISO/SAE 21434 certification, this milestone expands Ubuntu’s leadership in securing critical infrastructure at the intersection of IT and operational technology (OT) environments. Achieving IEC 62443-4-1 compliance ensures Canonical solutions can be deployed [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;Canonical is proud to announce it has achieved compliance with IEC 62443-4-1 for cybersecurity in Industrial Automation and Control Systems (IACS). Building on Canonical’s existing &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/blog/canonical-achieves-iso-21434-certification"&gt;&lt;u&gt;ISO/SAE 21434&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt; certification, this milestone expands Ubuntu’s leadership in securing critical infrastructure at the intersection of IT and operational technology (OT) environments. Achieving IEC 62443-4-1 compliance ensures Canonical solutions can be deployed with confidence across critical sectors backed by robust and long-term-supported, open source security processes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="wp-block-image"&gt;
&lt;figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"&gt;&lt;img alt="" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 477px) 477px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_477/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F379f%2FTUV-compliance-badge-no-background.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F379f%2FTUV-compliance-badge-no-background.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F379f%2FTUV-compliance-badge-no-background.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_477/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F379f%2FTUV-compliance-badge-no-background.png 477w" width="477"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;What is IEC 62443-4-1 certification? &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IEC 62443 is a globally recognized, rigorous framework for managing cybersecurity risk across the lifecycle of industrial control systems. Developed by ISA (the International Standards Society of Automation) and IEC (the International Electrotechnical Commission), IEC 62443 is a series of standards covering everything from secure product development to network segmentation and asset management, demonstrating that the organization’s policy and procedures, system architecture, components, and evaluation methods are designed to defend critical infrastructure against threats. IEC 62443-4-1, in particular, is the part that specifies the process requirements for the secure development of products used in industrial automation and control systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Canonical Security Management System establishes a fully-certified ISO/SAE 21434 and IEC 62443-4-1 framework demonstrating our commitment to systematic security governance, risk assessment, vulnerability management, and lifecycle security assurance for automotive and industrial software products. These reliable processes are based on Canonical’s Secure Software Development Lifecycle (SSDLC) and Ubuntu Pro services for vulnerability management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The audit for the IEC 62443-4-1 certification was conducted by TÜV SÜD. The certification is part of Canonical’s long-term dedication to cybersecurity across heavily regulated industries. Combined with &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/blog/canonical-achieves-iso-21434-certification"&gt;&lt;u&gt;our recently awarded ISO/SAE 21434 certification for automotive&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, this IEC 62443-4-1 certification reflects a coordinated effort to deliver securely-designed solutions across a wide range of industries, especially those facing multiple overlapping regulations like the &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/solutions/open-source-security/cyber-resilience-act"&gt;&lt;u&gt;Cyber Resilience Act (CRA)&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and the Radio Equipment Directive (RED).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These processes translate naturally into industrial-grade controls, such as threat modeling, security update management, security-related issues management, security guidelines and lifecycle management. Canonical open source solutions with IEC 62443-4-1 compliance enable asset owners to tailor systems across multi-vendor environments, providing a hardened, software-defined foundation for HMI, PLC, and edge-compute solutions in harsh industrial settings. Canonical solutions act as a benchmark for industrial-grade compute stacks, allowing ecosystem partners and original equipment manufacturers (OEMs) to accelerate innovation when building secure control systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“As a ctrlX World partner, Canonical supports the security and reliability of our automation solutions. Ubuntu Core is the securely-designed, containerized Linux behind our operating system ctrlX OS. Canonical’s IEC 62443-4-1 compliance aligns perfectly with our own cybersecurity commitments for the launch of our new ctrlX OS 3.6 LTS release,” said Steffen Münch, Lead Development and Security Operations at Bosch Rexroth. “This complements our IEC 62443 certifications and allows us to deliver long-term, industrial-grade automation solutions that meet the highest standards for security, interoperability, and lifecycle support.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu Pro for Devices offers extended support and patching, critical for long-lived industrial systems operating for 20+ years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/pro/devices" rel="noopener" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;p class="p-button--positive"&gt;Learn about Ubuntu Pro for Devices&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;About Canonical&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical, the publisher of Ubuntu, provides open source security, support and services. Our portfolio covers critical systems, from the smallest devices to the largest clouds, from the kernel to containers, from databases to AI. With customers that include top tech brands, emerging startups, governments and home users, Canonical delivers trusted open source for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn more at &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/%C2%A0"&gt;canonical.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Canonical (Canonical)</author><pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Canonical announces it will support and distribute NVIDIA CUDA in Ubuntu</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/canonical-announces-it-will-support-and-distribute-nvidia-cuda-in-ubuntu</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Today Canonical, the publisher of Ubuntu, announced support for the NVIDIA CUDA toolkit and the distribution of CUDA within Ubuntu’s repositories.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; CUDA is a parallel computing platform and programming model&amp;nbsp; that lets developers use NVIDIA GPUs for general-purpose processing. It exposes the GPU’s Single-Instruction Multiple Thread (SIMT) architecture, enabling fine-grained control over threads, memory hierarchies, [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;Today Canonical, the publisher of Ubuntu, announced support for the &lt;a href="https://developer.nvidia.com/cuda-toolkit"&gt;NVIDIA CUDA toolkit&lt;/a&gt; and the distribution of CUDA within Ubuntu’s repositories.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CUDA is a parallel computing platform and programming model  that lets developers use NVIDIA GPUs for general-purpose processing. It exposes the GPU’s Single-Instruction Multiple Thread (SIMT) architecture, enabling fine-grained control over threads, memory hierarchies, and kernels to accelerate large-scale numerical and tensor operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the long-time collaboration between Canonical and NVIDIA, the CUDA runtime has always been tested on Ubuntu, which is used in thousands of data centers. Distributing CUDA within Ubuntu will make it even easier for developers to build, iterate and deploy their AI apps using CUDA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A new, easier way to install NVIDIA CUDA&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Historically, developers would download the CUDA Toolkit directly from &lt;a href="https://docs.nvidia.com/cuda/cuda-installation-guide-linux/#ubuntu-installation"&gt;NVIDIA’s website&lt;/a&gt;. Today, Canonical is making it even easier for developers to access CUDA natively through their development environment. The CUDA toolkit and runtime will be directly distributed within Ubuntu. Developers using this new distribution channel will be able to use CUDA on their hardware with a native Ubuntu experience. Once CUDA redistribution is fully integrated into Ubuntu, application developers and system administrators can expect the current &lt;a href="https://docs.nvidia.com/cuda/cuda-installation-guide-linux/#ubuntu-installation"&gt;multi-step CUDA installation process&lt;/a&gt; to become a single command. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For application developers targeting Ubuntu systems, this new distribution model means they can simply declare the CUDA runtime, while Ubuntu manages its installation and compatibility across a wide range of supported NVIDIA hardware. This ensures that CUDA will be more accessible and integrated into a widely-used and trusted Linux distribution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ubuntu’s software ecosystem&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides supporting compatibility with runtimes like CUDA which are widely used for AI development, Ubuntu offers a securely-designed platform for developers using open source. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For over 20 years, Canonical has been committed to a consistent release schedule for Ubuntu, maintaining its software supply chain and establishing it as a reliable platform for running workloads across the cloud, desktop, and edge devices. Ubuntu uses Advanced Package Tool (APT) to manage software from hundreds of decentralized contributors, enabling projects to scale seamlessly to millions of users. By streamlining software distribution at scale, Ubuntu makes it possible for software to reach a massive user base while preserving the security and integrity of the open source software supply chain. Users of Ubuntu can get access to a number of options that help maintain their work, including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Long-Term Support (LTS) Releases:&lt;/strong&gt; Ubuntu offers LTS releases, which are guaranteed to receive security updates for at least five years. This is critical for enterprise customers who need stability and security for long-term deployments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://help.ubuntu.com/community/Repositories/Ubuntu"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trusted Repositories&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; Canonical maintains a vast network of software repositories, ensuring that all packages are tested, validated, and compatible with each other. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ubuntu Pro:&lt;/strong&gt; With an Ubuntu Pro subscription, users get expanded security maintenance for a wide range of open source packages, offering a complete and trustworthy software supply chain. With Ubuntu Pro, organizations can also expand the security maintenance period for every LTS for an additional 7 years, bringing coverage to a total of 12 years. Ubuntu Pro also includes access to &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/landscape"&gt;Landscape&lt;/a&gt;, which facilitates systems management for Ubuntu machines. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu Pro is free for personal use on up to 5 machines, and enterprises can try it for free for 30 days. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="wp-block-buttons is-layout-flex wp-block-buttons-is-layout-flex"&gt;
&lt;div class="wp-block-button"&gt;&lt;a class="wp-block-button__link wp-element-button" href="https://ubuntu.com/pro" rel="https://ubuntu.com/pro noopener" target="_blank"&gt;Learn more about Ubuntu Pro&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;About Canonical &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical, the publisher of Ubuntu, provides open source security, support, and services. Our portfolio covers critical systems, from the smallest devices to the largest clouds, from the kernel to containers, from databases to AI. With customers that include top tech brands, emerging startups, governments and home users, Canonical delivers trusted open source for everyone. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn more at &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/"&gt;https://canonical.com/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Learn more&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find out more about &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/nvidia"&gt;Canonical’s collaboration with NVIDIA.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Canonical (Canonical)</author><category>AI/ML</category><category>nvidia</category><category>Ubuntu</category><pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 14:30:49 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>