<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Ubuntu blog</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/feed</link><description>Ubuntu blog feed</description><atom:link href="https://ubuntu.com//blog/feed" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>Python Feedgen</generator><lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 11:33:40 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>SpacemiT announces the availability of  Ubuntu on K3/K1 series RISC-V AI computing platforms</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/spacemit-announces-availability-of-ubuntu-on-k3-k1-series</link><description>&lt;p&gt;SpacemiT (Hangzhou) Technology Co., Ltd. today announced a  collaboration with Canonical to make  Ubuntu available on SpacemiT&amp;#8217;s new K3 SoC and the existing K1 series RISC-V computing platforms. This collaboration marks a deep integration between open-source operating systems and open RISC-V silicon, bringing powerful, flexible, and reliable intelligent computing solutions to developers worldwide. Hardware platforms [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;SpacemiT (Hangzhou) Technology Co., Ltd. today announced a  collaboration with Canonical to make  Ubuntu available on SpacemiT’s new K3 SoC and the existing K1 series RISC-V computing platforms. This collaboration marks a deep integration between open-source operating systems and open RISC-V silicon, bringing powerful, flexible, and reliable intelligent computing solutions to developers worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hardware platforms designed for high-performance intelligent computing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SpacemiT’s new K3 series and the existing K1 series chips are built on proprietary RISC-V processor cores and integrate homogeneous AI computing capabilities. Designed for high-performance AI edge inference and AI robotics, the platforms are well suited for applications including robotics, intelligent security at the edge, industrial vision, and AI edge inference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="1139" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1267px) 1267px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1267/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fac59%2Fimage-1.jpeg" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fac59%2Fimage-1.jpeg 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fac59%2Fimage-1.jpeg 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fac59%2Fimage-1.jpeg 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fac59%2Fimage-1.jpeg 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fac59%2Fimage-1.jpeg 1920w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1267/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fac59%2Fimage-1.jpeg 1267w" width="1267"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Advancing intelligent computing: seamless OS integration &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the rapid advancement of artificial intelligence, edge computing, and robotics, the market increasingly requires hardware and software platforms that deliver both strong computing performance and high development efficiency. Built on advanced RISC-V architecture and innovative system design, SpacemiT’s K3 and K1 series chips provide an ideal platform for RISC-V high-performance computing. Ubuntu, one of the world’s most widely used Linux distributions, is known for its stability, rich software ecosystem, and strong community support. The availability of  Ubuntu on the K3 and K1 series means developers benefit from seamless hardware-software integration as well as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Familiar environment: low barrier to entry for  existing Ubuntu users&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ecosystem compatibility: seamless access to Ubuntu’s vast software repositories and application ecosystem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Community-driven innovation: access to global Ubuntu community resources, documentation and shared expertise&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="713" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1267px) 1267px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1267/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fa872%2Fimage.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fa872%2Fimage.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fa872%2Fimage.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fa872%2Fimage.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fa872%2Fimage.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fa872%2Fimage.png 1920w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1267/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fa872%2Fimage.png 1267w" width="1267"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introducing one of the first RVA23 compliant platforms with Ubuntu&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The RISC-V RVA23 profile, introduced in 2024, defines a mandatory set of hardware features for 64-bit processors to help facilitate a consistent software-to-hardware interface. Some of the mandatory features include vector computing for AI workloads, advanced security extensions and hypervisor support. SpacemiT’s K3 SoC is one of the first RVA23 compliant platforms available today. Canonical announced  &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/blog/canonical-releases-ubuntu-25-10-questing-quokka"&gt;adoption of RVA23&lt;/a&gt; as a baseline profile for RISC-V builds with the release of Ubuntu 25.10. This enables users of RVA23 compliant platforms with Ubuntu to leverage the full power of the chip out-of-the-box and gain a stable, high performing experience. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Collaborating on platform enablement &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With RVA23 compliance in mind, SpacemiT has taken the lead in enabling the Ubuntu 26.04 LTS Preview release on the K3 SoC, delivering a new RISC-V desktop experience. The enablement of Ubuntu 26.04 LTS, which will officially be released in April 2026, on the K3 chip will support RVA23-compliant computing systems and products worldwide, representing a milestone in the development of the RISC-V software ecosystem. This is expected to attract more developers and partners, accelerating ecosystem maturity with greater speed and efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="713" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1267px) 1267px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1267/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fef14%2Fimage.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fef14%2Fimage.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fef14%2Fimage.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fef14%2Fimage.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fef14%2Fimage.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fef14%2Fimage.png 1920w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1267/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fef14%2Fimage.png 1267w" width="1267"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ubuntu 24.04 LTS availability on SpacemiT’s existing K1 platform&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to enabling Ubuntu on the new K3 chip, SpacemiT and Canonical have also collaborated to enable Ubuntu 24.04 LTS across the broader SpacemiT lineup, including the K1 MUSE Book and MUSE Pi Pro. This initiative reflects the companies’ shared mission to bring a world-class Linux experience to the entire SpacemiT community. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A win-win collaboration to accelerate the RISC-V ecosystem&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Ubuntu is one of the most popular Linux distributions globally, and we are delighted to work with Canonical to bring Ubuntu to our K3/K1 intelligent computing platforms and jointly advance the open RISC-V architecture and Linux software ecosystem,” said Sun Yanbang, President of SpacemiT. “This collaboration not only provides developers with a more complete technical solution, but also reflects SpacemiT’s long-term commitment to open standards and open-source ecosystems. By combining Ubuntu’s mature software ecosystem with our advanced RISC-V hardware technologies, we aim to drive innovation and growth in intelligent computing,” he added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;”SpacemiT has significantly contributed to the fast-growing RISC-V ecosystem and leading adoption of RVA23 with Ubuntu 26.04,” said Cindy Goldberg, VP of Cloud and Silicon Partnerships at Canonical. “We’re delighted to work with SpacemiT to make the intelligent computing capabilities of the K3 and K1 series easily accessible to developers. Canonical is committed to amplifying the impact of open source software and making it available to users everywhere. The collaboration with SpacemiT aligns perfectly with our vision and our commitment to the RISC-Vecosystem.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;About Canonical&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical, the publisher of Ubuntu, provides open source security, support and services. Our portfolio covers critical systems, from the smallest devices to the largest clouds, from the kernel to containers, from databases to AI. With customers that include top tech brands, emerging startups, governments and home users, Canonical delivers trusted open source for everyone. Learn more at &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/"&gt;https://canonical.com/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;About SpacemiT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Founded in November 2021, SpacemiT is a computing ecosystem company built on next-generation RISC-V architecture. The company focuses on full-stack computing technologies including high-performance RISC-V CPU cores, RISC-V AI cores, NoC interconnects, RISC-V AI CPU chips, and software systems. SpacemiT delivers end-to-end computing system solutions and is committed to building the optimal native computing platform for the next AI era, enabling new applications such as AI computers and AI robots. &lt;a href="https://www.spacemit.com"&gt;https://www.spacemit.com&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="535" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1267px) 1267px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1267/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F41d4%2Fimage-1.jpeg" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F41d4%2Fimage-1.jpeg 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F41d4%2Fimage-1.jpeg 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F41d4%2Fimage-1.jpeg 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F41d4%2Fimage-1.jpeg 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F41d4%2Fimage-1.jpeg 1920w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1267/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F41d4%2Fimage-1.jpeg 1267w" width="1267"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Canonical (Canonical)</author><category>RISC-V</category><category>silicon</category><category>Ubuntu</category><pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>AI meets SQL Server 2025 on Ubuntu</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/sql-server-2025-on-ubuntu</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Partnership between Microsoft and Canonical Since 2016, when Microsoft announced its intention to make Linux a first class citizen in its ecosystem, Canonical and Microsoft have been working hand in hand to make that vision a reality. Ubuntu was among the first distributions to support the preview of SQL Server on Linux. Ubuntu was the [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Partnership between Microsoft and Canonical&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since 2016, when Microsoft announced its intention to make Linux a first class citizen in its ecosystem, Canonical and Microsoft have been working hand in hand to make that vision a reality. Ubuntu was among the first distributions to support the &lt;a href="https://blogs.microsoft.com/blog/2016/03/07/announcing-sql-server-on-linux"&gt;preview&lt;/a&gt; of SQL Server on Linux. Ubuntu was the &lt;a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/archive/blogs/wsl/windows-subsystem-for-linux-overview"&gt;first distribution&lt;/a&gt; offered in the launch of Windows Subsystem for Linux (WSL), and it remains the &lt;a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/wsl/install"&gt;default&lt;/a&gt; to this day. Ubuntu was also the first Linux distribution to support Azure’s &lt;a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/confidential-computing/quick-create-confidential-vm-portal-amd"&gt;Confidential VMs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SQL server has been a cornerstone of the ongoing collaboration to deliver a seamless Linux experience for developers and enterprises alike. Together, we have been able to meet growing customer demands with a number of joint offerings including ready-made and jointly &lt;a href="https://azuremarketplace.microsoft.com/en-us/marketplace/apps?filters=linux%3Bmicrosoft&amp;amp;page=1&amp;amp;search=Ubuntu"&gt;supported configurations&lt;/a&gt; for SQL Server on top of Ubuntu. In this article, we’ll take a look at our latest collaboration: SQL Server 2025 on Ubuntu.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SQL Server 2025&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/sql/linux/quickstart-install-connect-ubuntu?view=sql-server-ver17&amp;amp;tabs=ubuntu2004%2C2025ubuntu2204%2Codbc-ubuntu-1804"&gt;General Availability of SQL Server 2025 on Ubuntu 24.04&lt;/a&gt; is a milestone in our partnership. SQL Server 2025 brings several &lt;a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/sql/sql-server/what-s-new-in-sql-server-2025?view=sql-server-ver17"&gt;new features&lt;/a&gt;, including new AI capabilities such as vector search and external AI models integrations. Here’s how you can get up and running with these new capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Your new AI playground&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deploying a database server instance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s start by installing &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/lxd"&gt;LXD&lt;/a&gt;, our Canonical tool to easily manage virtual machines and containers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo snap install lxd 
sudo snap list | awk '/lxd/ {print $3}'
sudo lxd init --minimal # configure LXD&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s now create a virtual machine to serve as a playground:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo lxc launch ubuntu:24.04 mssql25 --vm -c limits.cpu=4 -c limits.memory=6GiB -d root,size=24GiB&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, we will be installing all the pre-requisites to get a SQL Server 2017 running:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo lxc exec mssql25 bash
su -l ubuntu
# Like always, we start by updating our packages
sudo apt -y update &amp;amp;&amp;amp; sudo apt -y upgrade

# Download and trust the Microsoft key 
curl -fsSL https://packages.microsoft.com/keys/microsoft.asc | sudo gpg --dearmor -o /usr/share/keyrings/microsoft-prod.gpg

# Register the SQL Server repository
curl -fsSL https://packages.microsoft.com/config/ubuntu/24.04/mssql-server-2025.list | sudo tee /etc/apt/sources.list.d/mssql-server-2025.list

# Ensures new repositories are loaded
sudo apt-get update

# Install SQL server and a password generator
sudo apt-get install -y mssql-server pwgen&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s now set up the installed SQL Server to get a running instance as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;PW="$(pwgen -sB 22 1)" # Generates SQL Server compliant-password
# Prepare some environment variables to setup SQL Server
install -d -m 700 ~/.secrets/sql
install -m 600 /dev/null ~/.secrets/sql/mssql.env

cat &amp;gt; ~/.secrets/sql/mssql.env &amp;lt;&amp;lt;EOF
MSSQL_PID=Developer
MSSQL_SA_PASSWORD='$PW'
SQLSERVER=127.0.0.1
SQLPORT=1433
SQLUSER=sa
SQLCMDPASSWORD='$PW'
EOF

# Export every line in mssql.env as an environment variable
set -a; . ~/.secrets/sql/mssql.env; set +a

# Set up SQL Server
sudo MSSQL_SA_PASSWORD="$MSSQL_SA_PASSWORD" MSSQL_PID="$MSSQL_PID" /opt/mssql/bin/mssql-conf -n setup

# Let's check that everything went fine
systemctl status mssql-server --no-pager&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will now install some additional tools to be able to connect to SQL Server&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;# Download the deb package
curl -sSL -O https://packages.microsoft.com/config/ubuntu/$(grep VERSION_ID /etc/os-release | cut -d '"' -f 2)/packages-microsoft-prod.deb
# Install the downloaded deb package
sudo dpkg -i packages-microsoft-prod.deb
# Delete the downloaded package
rm packages-microsoft-prod.deb
# Install Microsoft's ODBC driver and additional tools
sudo apt-get update
sudo apt-get install -y msodbcsql18  mssql-tools18 unixodbc-dev libodbc2
echo 'export PATH="$PATH:/opt/mssql-tools18/bin"' &amp;gt;&amp;gt; ~/.bashrc
source ~/.bashrc&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will run a query to check that everything is running as intended:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;/opt/mssql-tools18/bin/sqlcmd -S 127.0.0.1 -U sa -No -C -P "$SQLCMDPASSWORD"
SELECT @@VERSION AS 'SQL Server Version';
GO&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above should return the exact version of SQL Server you are running. So far, we’ve made simple interactions with SQL Server. In the next section, we will test some new exciting features of the 2025 edition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vector type&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A vector type is a contiguous array of fixed-length numbers designed to enable hardware-accelerated vectorized (SIMD) execution. A vector type is the perfect type to use to store embeddings (i.e. numerical representations) of objects manipulated by AI models such as text and images.  Let’s create a table with a column of type of vector as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;CREATE DATABASE DemoDb;
GO

USE DemoDb;
GO

ALTER DATABASE SCOPED CONFIGURATION SET PREVIEW_FEATURES = ON;
CREATE TABLE dbo.VectorDemo (id INT IDENTITY(1,1) PRIMARY KEY, embedding VECTOR(3) NOT NULL);
GO

INSERT INTO dbo.VectorDemo (embedding) VALUES ('[2,3,5]'), ('[7,11,13]'), ('[17,19,23]');
GO

DECLARE @q VECTOR(3) = '[7,11,13]';
SELECT embedding, VECTOR_DISTANCE('euclidean', embedding, @q) AS distance FROM dbo.VectorDemo ORDER BY distance;
GO

DECLARE @q2 VECTOR(3) = '[7,11,13]';
SELECT embedding, VECTOR_DISTANCE('cosine', embedding, @q2) AS distance FROM dbo.VectorDemo ORDER BY distance;
GO
exit&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have checked how to create a vector type and how to use the vector_distance operator. We will next provide an example of a more advanced use case involving calling an AI model and performing a similarity search.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AI models integration&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most exciting features of SQL Server 2025 is the ability to call AI models from within the comfort of your database in a structured way. Let’s check how:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AI models deployment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will start by deploying a local embedding model using Ollama.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;curl -fsSL https://ollama.com/install.sh | sh # Installs ollama
ollama pull nomic-embed-text # Pulls an embedding model
curl -k http://localhost:11434/api/tags  # Checks the api endpoint&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deploying a http proxy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SQL Server 2025 requires that model endpoints are exposed using https (not just plain http). We will therefore deploy and configure Caddy for that purpose as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo apt install -y caddy 

sudo cp /etc/caddy/Caddyfile /etc/caddy/Caddyfile.bak # Keep  a backup

sudo tee /etc/caddy/Caddyfile &amp;gt;/dev/null &amp;lt;&amp;lt;'EOF'
https://localhost:11435 {
  tls internal
  reverse_proxy 127.0.0.1:11434
}
EOF

sudo systemctl reload caddy # Needed to pick the previous changes

# We need the system to trust Caddy's certificate by doing the following:
sudo cp /var/lib/caddy/.local/share/caddy/pki/authorities/local/root.crt /usr/local/share/ca-certificates/caddy-local-root.crt

# We need also SQL Server system to trust Caddy's certificate:
sudo mkdir -p /var/opt/mssql/security/ca-certificates
sudo cp /var/lib/caddy/.local/share/caddy/pki/authorities/local/root.crt /var/opt/mssql/security/ca-certificates/caddy-local-root.crt
sudo chown -R mssql:mssql /var/opt/mssql/security
sudo chmod 744 /var/opt/mssql/security/ca-certificates
sudo chmod 644 /var/opt/mssql/security/ca-certificates/caddy-local-root.crt

# Update the VM's trusted certificates
sudo update-ca-certificates

# Restart SQL Server 
sudo systemctl restart mssql-server

# Check a few https endpoints 
curl -w '\n' https://localhost:11435/api/tags 
curl -w '\n' https://localhost:11435/api/embed \
  -H "Content-Type: application/json" \
  -d '{ "model":"nomic-embed-text", "input":"hello from caddy" }'&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Python dependencies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s now proceed with the installation of the pre-requisites to connect to the SQL Server instance using a python program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo apt install -y python3-openai python3-pyodbc&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Calling AI models from within SQL Server 2025&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will now enable SQL Server to use an external endpoint and then restart it to ensure it correctly picked the new trusted certificates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;/opt/mssql-tools18/bin/sqlcmd -S 127.0.0.1 -U sa -C -P "$SQLCMDPASSWORD" -Q "EXEC sp_configure 'external rest endpoint enabled', 1; RECONFIGURE;"
sudo systemctl restart mssql-server&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then we will write a simple Python script to test the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Connecting to the server programmatically&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Registering Ollama model via HTTPS proxy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Creating a vector column and feeding it with some examples using the registered model&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Creating a vector-optimized index and using it to perform similarity search&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;cat &amp;lt;&amp;lt;EOT &amp;gt; ~/mssqlvector.py
import pyodbc

# Define parameters based on your sqlcmd
server = '127.0.0.1'
database = 'DemoDb'
username = 'sa'
password = "$MSSQL_SA_PASSWORD"
port = '1433'

# Connection string using SQL Server Authentication
connection_string = (
    "DRIVER={ODBC Driver 18 for SQL Server};"
    f"SERVER={server},{port};"
    f"DATABASE={database};"
    f"UID={username};"
    f"PWD={{{password}}};"
    f"Encrypt=no;"
    f"Connection Timeout=7;"
    f"TrustServerCertificate=yes;"
)

try:
    conn = pyodbc.connect(connection_string)
    cur = conn.cursor()
    print("Connected to SQL Server!")

    # Example: simple query
    cur.execute("SELECT name FROM sys.databases;")
    for row in cur.fetchall():
        print(row)

    conn.autocommit = True

    # 1) Register Ollama model via HTTPS proxy
    cur.execute("""
IF NOT EXISTS (SELECT * FROM sys.external_models WHERE name='ollama')
CREATE EXTERNAL MODEL ollama
WITH (
        LOCATION   = 'https://localhost:11435/api/embed',
        API_FORMAT = 'Ollama',
        MODEL_TYPE = EMBEDDINGS,
        MODEL      = 'nomic-embed-text'   -- 768 dims
);
""")

    # 2) Create a new table including a vector column
    cur.execute("""
DROP TABLE IF EXISTS dbo.SupportMatrix;
CREATE TABLE dbo.SupportMatrix (
        id        INT IDENTITY PRIMARY KEY,
        sentence  NVARCHAR(400) NOT NULL,
        embedding VECTOR(768)   NULL
);
""")

    # 3) Insert your Ubuntu/SQL Server lines
    texts = [
        "Ubuntu 24.04 is supported by SQL Server 2025",
        "Ubuntu 22.04 is supported by SQL Server 2022",
        "Ubuntu 20.04 is supported by SQL Server 2019",
        "Ubuntu 18.04 is supported by SQL Server 2019"
    ]
    cur.executemany("INSERT INTO dbo.SupportMatrix(sentence) VALUES (?);", [(t,) for t in texts])

    # 4) Generate embeddings in-database (using the external model)
    cur.execute("""
UPDATE dbo.SupportMatrix
SET embedding = AI_GENERATE_EMBEDDINGS(sentence USE MODEL ollama)
WHERE embedding IS NULL;
""")

    # 5) Create an ANN similarity index (DiskANN) on the vector column
    cur.execute("""
IF NOT EXISTS (SELECT 1 FROM sys.indexes WHERE name = 'IX_SupportMatrix_Embedding')
CREATE VECTOR INDEX IX_SupportMatrix_Embedding
ON dbo.SupportMatrix(embedding)
WITH (METRIC = 'cosine', TYPE = 'diskann');
""")

    # 6) Run a similarity search with VECTOR_SEARCH (uses the ANN index)
    query_text = "What Ubuntu version is supported by SQL Server 2025?"
    cur.execute("""
DECLARE @q VECTOR(768) = AI_GENERATE_EMBEDDINGS(?, ollama);

SELECT TOP (3)
  t.id,
  t.sentence,
  s.distance
FROM VECTOR_SEARCH(
    table = dbo.SupportMatrix AS t,
    column = embedding,
    similar_to = @q,
    metric = 'cosine',
    top_n = 3
) AS s
ORDER BY s.distance, t.id;
""", (query_text,))

    print(f"Top matches for: '{query_text}'\n")
    for row in cur.fetchall():
        print(row)

except Exception as e:
    print("Connection failed:", e)

finally:
    conn.close()

EOT&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We then can use our python scipt as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;python3 ~/mssqlvector.py&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve checked some of the new AI-related features that you can use from within the comfort of your SQL Server database. Bringing AI closer to your data is a good recipe for getting more value out of your data without the challenges inherent to data duplication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another challenge companies need to address is securing the AI supply chain. Let’s look at how you can handle that next.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Your secure AI playground&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to get security updates for up to 25,000 open source packages, you can subscribe to Ubuntu Pro (free for personal use for up to 5 machines). You can check whether you have already a subscription by running the following command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;pro api u.pro.status.enabled_services.v1 | grep -c esm&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If not enabled then you can subscribe to Ubuntu Pro &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/pro/subscribe"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Once you get your token, just type:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo pro attach &amp;lt;token&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that you have covered all of your Canonical maintained packages, you should next check the providers of your other packages that aren’t included in Ubuntu Pro. The following command helps you identify all the deb packages that are not maintained directly by Canonical:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;dpkg-query -W -f='${Package}\n' | while read pkg; do
    src=$(apt-cache policy "$pkg" | grep -m 1 http | awk '{print $2}')
    if [[ -n "$src" &amp;amp;&amp;amp; "$src" != *ubuntu.com* ]]; then
        echo "$pkg -&amp;gt; $src"
    fi
done&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my testing virtual machine, the above yields the following Microsoft-provided packages:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;msodbcsql18 -&amp;gt; https://packages.microsoft.com/ubuntu/24.04/prod
mssql-server -&amp;gt; https://packages.microsoft.com/ubuntu/24.04/mssql-server-preview
mssql-tools18 -&amp;gt; https://packages.microsoft.com/ubuntu/24.04/prod
packages-microsoft-prod -&amp;gt; https://packages.microsoft.com/ubuntu/24.04/prod&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should only keep trusted sources such as Microsoft and Canonical.  You need also to perform the same checks for all the other types of packages or images you might be using (containers, snaps …). Unfortunately, many companies might overlook securing the models themselves. Canonical not only provides audited AI models but also ones that are optimized for your infrastructure. Let’s look at an example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Your optimized AI models&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical recently &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/blog/canonical-releases-inference-snaps"&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/inference-snaps/"&gt;inference snaps&lt;/a&gt; that take advantage of your silicon capabilities (whether CPUs or GPUs) to accelerate your AI workloads.  Here’s how you can install one:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo snap install qwen-vl --beta
qwen-vl status # Checks it finished successfully&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On my machine, I get:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;engine: cpu-avx512
endpoints:
    openai: http://localhost:8326/v1&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can then use the newly deployed model as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;curl http://localhost:8326/v1/chat/completions \
-H "Content-Type: application/json" \
-d '{ "model": "&amp;lt;model-name&amp;gt;", "messages": [{"role": "user", "content": "Who is the publisher of Ubuntu?"}],
"temperature": 0.7
}' | jq&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should then get a response to the supplied prompt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Running optimized AI models along Ubuntu Pro and SQL Server provides you with a secure and reliable stack to support your AI workflows. Canonical and Microsoft can help you go further with jointly supported offerings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Your supported AI playground&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We saw together how Canonical and Microsoft help you run an integrated AI stack from the operating system up to the database engine and the AI models. Canonical and Microsoft  deliver prebuilt Azure VM images with pre-configured SQL Server on top of Ubuntu Pro, with support from both companies. We can also help you run highly available and supported SQL Server deployments on top of Ubuntu Pro. Please &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/data#get-in-touch"&gt;contact us&lt;/a&gt; for more details.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Mohamed Wadie Nsiri (Mohamed Wadie Nsiri)</author><category>SQL Server</category><category>Ubuntu</category><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 14:34:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>AWS IoT Greengrass comes to Ubuntu Core</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/aws-iot-greengrass-comes-to-ubuntu-core</link><description>&lt;p&gt;AWS’s open source edge run time meets Canonical’s fully containerized OS for devices delivering a supported and robust end-to-end answer for enterprises looking to develop their own IoT hardware and solutions. London, February 3, 2026 &amp;#8212; Canonical and AWS are pleased to announce the release of the new snap for AWS IoT Greengrass, making the [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;h4 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;AWS’s open source edge run time meets Canonical’s fully containerized OS for devices delivering a supported and robust end-to-end answer for enterprises looking to develop their own IoT hardware and solutions.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;London, February 3, 2026 — Canonical and AWS are pleased to announce the release of the new snap for AWS IoT Greengrass, making the deployment of your IoT solutions easy and seamless all the way from silicon to the cloud&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the &lt;a href="https://snapcraft.io/aws-iot-greengrass"&gt;AWS IoT Greengrass agent&lt;/a&gt; now available as a snap package from the Canonical Snap Store, Ubuntu Core has become the ideal operating system for all your AWS IoT edge workloads and data ingress. Its broad compatibility with silicon hardware, long-term support, and proven, reliable performance unlock endless possibilities for your IoT devices utilizing the power of the AWS cloud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AWS Greengrass is one of the market-leading IoT edge platforms, bringing the comprehensive capabilities of the AWS cloud to distributed edge environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu Core offers extensive silicon compatibility, simplifying device deployment across various hardware platforms. Canonical further supports this by providing device enablement and certification for custom hardware, ensuring long-term support for your products. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The combined solutions enable enterprises to focus on their products with confidence, knowing their infrastructure and devices are covered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="wp-block-quote"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“AWS IoT Greengrass is the best way to bring the power of AWS to the edge, and what better option to partner it with than the industry leading OS for edge devices – Ubuntu Core? With the release of the Greengrass snap, enterprises will be hard pressed to find an easier, more secure, reliable or robust foundation for their IoT needs.” &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;– Michael Croft-White, Engineering Director, Canonical.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;The power of the cloud at the edge&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AWS Greengrass enables organizations to deploy and manage containerized applications and AWS Lambda functions directly onto their local hardware, streamlining their edge solution development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AWS IoT Greengrass brings processing and machine learning inference closer to the point of data collection. This makes it ideal for applications needing low latency and real-time decisions. Furthermore, with its reliable offline capabilities, Greengrass ensures continued operation during periods of intermittent network connectivity. Running on top of Canonical’s Ubuntu Core, enterprises can build, develop, and deploy sophisticated, resilient, and scalable edge solutions in sectors such as industrial automation, logistics, and automotive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Made for security, resilience, and longevity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu Core is purpose built for IoT and embedded devices. With Canonical’s reputation for industry-leading reliability and robust security and focus on long-term support commitment, you can rely on a predictable release cycle and stability across your entire fleet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Its minimal, containerized design with automatic, transactional updates can ensure timely delivery of security patches without downtime. Extensive hardware and silicon compatibility gives the freedom to optimize your device’s design for each and every use case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through Ubuntu Pro, both Ubuntu and Ubuntu Core can be extended with up to 15 years of maintenance and security updates with &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/security/esm"&gt;Canonical’s Expanded Security Maintenance (ESM)&lt;/a&gt;. This gives organizations the confidence that their IoT infrastructure remains securely maintained against  vulnerabilities for the long term, reducing operational risk and total cost of ownership.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Get the snap for AWS IoT Greengrass&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can download and install the snap from the &lt;a href="https://snapcraft.io/aws-iot-greengrass"&gt;Snap Store&lt;/a&gt; directly onto your IoT device with the following command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;snap install aws-iot-greengrass&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more information on Ubuntu Core, visit &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/core"&gt;ubuntu.com/core&lt;/a&gt;, or check out our &lt;a href="http://canonical.com/blog/tutorial-getting-started-with-aws-greengrass-on-ubuntu-core"&gt;tutorial blog&lt;/a&gt; for everything you need to get started, including a hands-on demo. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are not already familiar with AWS IoT Greengrass, more information can be found &lt;a href="https://aws.amazon.com/greengrass/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you interested in running Ubuntu Core with AWS IoT Greengrass on your devices and are working on a commercial project?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;a aria-label=" (opens in a new tab)" class="p-button--small p-button--positive" href="https://canonical.com/contact-us#get-in-touch" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"&gt;Get in touch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Further reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://canonical.com/blog/tutorial-getting-started-with-aws-greengrass-on-ubuntu-core"&gt;Tutorial: getting started with AWS Greengrass on Ubuntu Core&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/core"&gt;Ubuntu Core: The embedded Linux OS for devices&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://aws.amazon.com/greengrass/"&gt;Intelligence at the IoT Edge – AWS IoT Greengrass&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;About Canonical&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical, the publisher of Ubuntu, provides open-source security, support and services. Our portfolio covers critical systems, from the smallest devices to the largest clouds, from the kernel to containers, from databases to AI. With customers that include top tech brands, emerging startups, governments and home users, Canonical delivers trusted open source for everyone.&lt;br/&gt;Learn more at &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/"&gt;https://canonical.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Canonical (Canonical)</author><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 09:55:59 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Tutorial: getting started with AWS IoT Greengrass on Ubuntu Core</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/tutorial-getting-started-with-aws-greengrass-on-ubuntu-core</link><description>&lt;p&gt;We recently announced that you can now benefit from the combined power of Ubuntu Core and AWS IoT Greengrass to bring the computation, storage, and AI capabilities of the cloud closer to the edge. AWS IoT Greengrass is an open source edge runtime and cloud service that extends Amazon Web Services (AWS) capabilities to physical [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://canonical.com/blog/aws-iot-greengrass-comes-to-ubuntu-core"&gt;We recently announced &lt;/a&gt;that you can now benefit from the combined power of Ubuntu Core and AWS IoT Greengrass to bring the computation, storage, and AI capabilities of the cloud closer to the edge. AWS IoT Greengrass is an open source edge runtime and cloud service that extends Amazon Web Services (AWS) capabilities to physical devices. It means devices can act locally on data while still harnessing the cloud for management and analytics. This is essential for applications where latency can be critical, resilience is needed due to low or no network connectivity, or where privacy and data concerns are paramount. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/core"&gt;Ubuntu Core&lt;/a&gt; is a flavor of Ubuntu that has been specially optimized for IoT and embedded systems. The combination of the Ubuntu Core and AWS IoT Greengrass is ideal for those looking for reduced latency, lower bandwidth, and more efficient data processing. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This tutorial helps you get started using an Ubuntu Core device as a platform to deploy an AWS Greengrass based demonstration of video inference. To follow along you will need two devices: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An intel-based device, such as a NUC, for running Ubuntu Core &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A device for configuring your AWS deployment and running the dashboard to show you the results. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will also need a webcam to capture images and an AWS account. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both AWS and Ubuntu Core are available on a wide range of hardware platforms. However, this specific demo has been optimized for Intel – hence the device requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog will begin with a brief explanation of the solution before providing an overview of the architecture, and then guide you through the following steps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#install-ubuntu-core"&gt;Installing Ubuntu Core&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#create-aws-iam"&gt;Creating an AWS user account for the demo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#set-up-aws"&gt;Installing the Greengrass Snap package and connecting to your AWS account&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#prepare-deployment-environment"&gt;Preparing your deployment environment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#create-deploy-components"&gt;Creating and deploying Greengrass Components&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#set-up-web-interface"&gt;Setting up a web interface to view the demo outputs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, let’s get started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Solution summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The solution uses Greengrass Nucleus installed as a Snap package on Ubuntu Core.  It uses the strict confinement for snap packages to help maintain the highest level of security control and isolation.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Installing and configuring the Greengrass snap package takes only a couple of minutes. The package enables easy connection of Greengrass to the AWS Greengrass Service in your AWS account, including creation of the necessary certificate and permissions needed for the device to function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After installation and configuration, three Greengrass custom components are deployed to the device from AWS. These enable connection of a USB webcam for capturing local images. Using Computer Vision (CV) capabilities provided through Intel OpenVINO, these images can then be processed for object detection to create a high-performance power combination for local device inference. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results of the CV inference are sent to AWS Cloud IoT Core service using MQTT, a standard protocol for IoT devices. The annotated images with bounding boxes for object detection are uploaded to Amazon S3 from the device. Together, these enable a web-based dashboard to visualize annotated images and inference results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;High-level architecture and overview&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The diagram below shows the high-level view of the interaction of the different components that will be deployed to your device for the purposes of this demo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"&gt;&lt;img alt="" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 533px) 533px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_533/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2afd%2FDiagram-v3.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2afd%2FDiagram-v3.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2afd%2FDiagram-v3.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2afd%2FDiagram-v3.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_533/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2afd%2FDiagram-v3.png 533w" width="533"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The three components we will be deploying are: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CameraHandler
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Manages the connection to the USB webcam.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Captures an image from the webcam every 30 seconds.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stores the image locally (within the confinement of Greengrass snap package).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Publishes a message using Greengrass IPC on the camera/images topic with the path to the locally stored image file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;InferenceHandler
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Subscribes to the camera/images topic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When it receives a message on that topic it processes the image so that it can be sent to OpenVINO for inference.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Calls the OpenVINO Model Server container to carry out the inference.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Upon receiving the inference results it annotates the image with bounding boxes and uploads the annotated image to Amazon S3.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sends a MQTT message to AWS IoT Core on the topic camera/inference.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deletes the local images.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;OpenVINOServerHandler
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Downloads the relevant Computer Vision ML model from Amazon S3.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Runs the standard Docker image for OpenVINO Model Server for inference using the provided ML model.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Requirements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The minimum requirements for edge devices running Ubuntu Core is available in &lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/core/reference/system-requirements/"&gt;our documentation&lt;/a&gt;. While Ubuntu Core is available for many architectures, this demo is targeted at Intel CPUs because it uses the Intel OpenVINO driver, and we will need: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;512MB RAM&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1GB storage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 x USB ports &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Internet connection (wifi or cabled)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will also need:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 USB memory sticks (min: 8GB)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;USB webcam &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deployment device
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A laptop/desktop for creating the deployment and running the dashboard&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="install-ubuntu-core"&gt;1. Installing Ubuntu Core&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, we need to set up our Ubuntu Core device.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu Core is a minimal, immutable flavor of Ubuntu which provides a reliable and secure platform for connected devices. To get started with it, Canonical have provided reference images that can be flashed onto certain devices and provide you a working environment. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu Core’s immutability and automatic updates make it the perfect platform for an embedded IoT workloading, meaning the user won’t have to worry about the device breaking in the field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we have flashed the Ubuntu Core image to our device, we will need to be able to connect to it. This will require an Ubuntu SSO account and an SSH keypair. You can skip this step if you already have an account, otherwise you can sign up for one &lt;a href="https://login.ubuntu.com/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To authenticate yourself when trying to connect to your Ubuntu Core device, you will need to upload a public SSH key to your SSO account. This will then be automatically downloaded to the Core device during initial configuration and allow you to log into a console. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To generate and upload an SSH key pair, follow the steps detailed in our documentation: &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/core/docs/connect-with-ssh"&gt;Connect to Ubuntu Core with SSH&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, we are ready to set up the device.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will be booting the device into a live Ubuntu environment using the first of our two USB sticks. From this instance, we can then flash the device storage with the Ubuntu Core image that we copied onto the second USB memory stick.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Follow &lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/desktop/en/latest/how-to/create-a-bootable-usb-stick/"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; tutorial to create a bootable USB stick with Ubuntu Desktop&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Download the &lt;a href="https://cdimage.ubuntu.com/ubuntu-core/24/stable/current/ubuntu-core-24-amd64.img.xz"&gt;reference Ubuntu Core 24 image for AMD/Intel 64bit devices&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Boot your device into Ubuntu Desktop using your first USB stick.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once in Ubuntu Desktop, insert your second USB stick and locate the Ubuntu Core image file. This will be something like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;/media/ubuntu/&amp;lt;disk-label&amp;gt;/ubuntu-core-24-amd64.img.xz&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s decompress that file to give us a raw image:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;unxz ubuntu-core-24-amd-64.img.xz&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, flash it to the device:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;dd if=ubuntu-core-24-amd-64.img of=/dev/&amp;lt;target disk&amp;gt; bs=32M status=progress&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are not sure what your local target disk is, run &lt;strong&gt;sudo fdisk -l&lt;/strong&gt;. This will list all your storage devices. You are looking for something like &lt;strong&gt;/dev/nvme01n1&lt;/strong&gt;. Note, this will completely erase anything on your target device, and replace it with Ubuntu Core. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once complete, you can remove all your USB sticks and reboot the device, which should start the Ubuntu Core initial configuration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Follow this wizard process and configure your network connection. You will be prompted to enter your Ubuntu SSO credentials, which will automatically download your SSH Keys to the device. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once configured, your device will be up and running. On screen, there will be a message explaining how to connect to this device from any other device on the network with a command such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;ssh &amp;lt;ubuntu SSO user name&amp;gt;@&amp;lt;device IP address&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Congratulations. You now have a secure, robust Ubuntu Core device. Now, let’s give it some cloud-connected superpowers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="create-aws-iam"&gt;2. Creating AWS IAM Users&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To create and deploy the AWS components for this demo, we need to create two IAM users with programmatic access (Access Key and Secret Access Key) for Greengrass installation. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To set up an IAM User:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to your AWS account access portal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Search for the IAM service.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From the Access Management sidebar, select Users and then create a user.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pick a name for this user. When prompted for permissions, select “Attach Policies Directly”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select the policies detailed for each user below.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h4 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greengrass device user: &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first user is for installing the Greengrass device – we’ll refer to them as the “Greengrass Device User” from now on. It is recommended to give this user &lt;em&gt;AWSGreengrassFullAccess&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;AWSIoTFullAccess&lt;/em&gt; permissions – this is slightly more than is required, but will ensure the user has everything necessary to get started. A finer grained breakdown of AWS permissions used can be found in the &lt;a href="https://github.com/aws-samples/sample-greengrass-ubuntucore-computervision"&gt;component repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When creating this user, make sure you create and download the Access Keys as you will be prompted to enter them during the Greengrass installation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deployment user:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second user is needed to configure the deployment and resources – we’ll call them the “Deployment User” from now on. This user will require a few more permissions. This user should be granted the &lt;em&gt;PowerUserAccess and IAMFullAccess&lt;/em&gt; policies in addition to the &lt;em&gt;AWSIoTFullAccess&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;AWSGreengrassFullAccess&lt;/em&gt; policies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Obtain Access Keys for users: &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having created both the Greengrass Device User and the Deployment User we need to obtain their access key. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select a user from your list and look for the Access Keys section.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click “Create Access Key.’&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select AWS CLI. Create the Keys and make sure to save a copy of them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will use the access keys during the following steps to configure the device and deployment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="set-up-aws"&gt;3. Setting Up AWS on your Ubuntu Core device&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The installation of Greengrass is simple and quick, following the steps below on your Ubuntu Core device.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install the aws-iot-greengrass snap from the store (for more information, visit our &lt;a href="https://snapcraft.io/aws-iot-greengrass"&gt;webpage&lt;/a&gt;) and run the configuration command:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo snap install aws-iot-greengrass

sudo aws-iot-greengrass.configure
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;ol start="2"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When prompted, enter the IAM user Access Key and Secret Access Key for your Greengrass device user. Make sure to specify the AWS region that you are using and the name you want for the device in the AWS IoT Core portal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Monitor the log messages on the screen to ensure successful configuration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check your AWS account to ensure that you can see the device listed as an “IoT Thing” and as a “Greengrass Core Device”. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure the necessary interfaces are connected to allow the Greengrass snap to interact with the device and webcam by running the following commands:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo snap connect aws-iot-greengrass:docker docker:docker-daemon
sudo snap connect aws-iot-greengrass:docker-executables docker:docker-executables
sudo snap connect aws-iot-greengrass:camera&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="prepare-deployment-environment"&gt;4. Preparing your deployment environment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having created our device, we now will create some components and deploy them to the device. Let’s start by setting up the environment for this on your second Ubuntu device. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The components themselves and scripts to help make the installation process simple are available on &lt;a href="https://github.com/aws-samples/sample-greengrass-ubuntucore-computervision"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. Start by cloning this repo to your local device:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo apt install git
git clone 
https://github.com/aws-samples/sample-greengrass-ubuntucore-computervision&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, we will need to install and configure the AWS CLI. This will allow us to log in to AWS and perform all the necessary actions. The login command will prompt you for the Access Key and Secret Access Key created in the previous steps – in this case, use the ones for the Deployment User.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;snap install aws-cli --classic

aws configure&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we are logged in, we can create our components. As mentioned, the component uses the Intel OpenVINO models for image analysis. These need downloading separately using the provided script in the repository:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo apt install curl zip 
download_model.sh&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we’ll make sure we have all other dependencies installed and create a python virtual environment to keep everything together. From the local repository directory, run:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo apt install python3-venv
python3 -m venv greengrass-deploy
source greengrass-deploy/bin/activate
pip install -r requirements-deploy.txt&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="create-deploy-components"&gt;5. Creating and deploying components&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we can deploy the components to the device, we will create an S3 bucket to store our images and a user account so we can access the web dashboard we will create.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is all handled by the following script.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;python3 setup_aws_resources.py --s3-bucket your-bucket-name --region us-east-1&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The script will create:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Greengrass Token Exchange Role and Role Alias (required for Greengrass components to access AWS services)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;S3 bucket (for component artifacts and the latest processed image)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cognito resources and a demo user (for React dashboard authentication)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IoT policies and IAM roles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the web dashboard will be accessing our AWS resources, we will need to create a user for that purpose that allows for username/password authentication. The user will be &lt;a href="mailto:demo@example.com"&gt;demo@example.com&lt;/a&gt; and you will be prompted for the password you would like to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: The InferenceHandlerCore component uploads each processed image to the same S3 location (camera/latest-inference.jpg), overwriting the previous image. This keeps storage minimal and simplifies the dashboard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And now, it is time to deploy components by simply running the script and follow the prompts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;python3 deploy_greengrass_components.py&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will guide you through the process including: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;create: Uploads component artifacts to S3 and creates Greengrass components in AWS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;deploy: Creates a deployment targeting your IoT Thing/Greengrass Core Device&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the script has run, you should be able to see the status of your deployments and the components being delivered to your device. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If you need more information on the scripts, or debugging any issues, the repository contains a &lt;a href="https://github.com/aws-samples/sample-greengrass-ubuntucore-computervision/react-web/README.md"&gt;readme.md&lt;/a&gt; file with more details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="set-up-web-interface"&gt;6. Setting up a web interface to view the results&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, the deployment has completed and our device is happily running away doing its own thing on the edge. We want to see what it is up to, so let’s deploy a dashboard. The dashboard runs locally, connecting to AWS to display the most recent captured image alongside the inference model output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dashboard is provided with the component repository and more information on it can be found in the /react-web folder. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scripts have been provided below to perform all the necessary setup steps. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The configuration for the dashboard, to ensure it connects to the correct locations, is stored in the .env file that is automatically populated when you run the deploy_greengrass_components script. If you need to recreate it, you can run the script again with the following settings:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;python3 deploy_greengrass_components.py --stage setup --s3-bucket 
your-bucket-name --region us-east-1&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having configured everything, install the dependencies necessary for the dashboard. From the react-web/ folder in the repository, run:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;apt install npm
npm install&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, start the dashboard server with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;npm start&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open &lt;strong&gt;http://localhost:3000&lt;/strong&gt; to view the dashboard. Log in with the demo user credentials created in the previous stage and click “Connect” to see the S3 images. Click “Subscribe” to view the model output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"&gt;&lt;img alt="" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 840px) 840px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_840/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F282f%2FImage-recognition-v2.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F282f%2FImage-recognition-v2.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F282f%2FImage-recognition-v2.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F282f%2FImage-recognition-v2.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_840/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F282f%2FImage-recognition-v2.png 840w" width="840"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Next steps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We hope that, having set up this demo, you get an insight into what you can do with AWS IoT Greengrass and Ubuntu Core. From here, you can further explore the options to build components, deploy, manage, and monitor remotely, as well as scaling up. In addition, Ubuntu Core will keep you secure and up to date automatically. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In future blogs, we will explore more specific Ubuntu Core management options directly from AWS Greengrass.  Keep your eyes peeled!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What will you build next? A smart factory monitor? An automated sales kiosk? A robotic production line? Whatever it is, Ubuntu Core and AWS Greengrass have your back. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether you are a startup bringing your concept to market or already have large fleets of devices deployed in the field, we have the expertise and infrastructure to launch and support you.&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/core#get-in-touch"&gt; Contact our team here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Further reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://canonical.com/blog/aws-iot-greengrass-comes-to-ubuntu-core"&gt;AWS IoT Greengrass comes to Ubuntu Core&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/core"&gt;Ubuntu Core: The embedded Linux OS for devices&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://aws.amazon.com/greengrass/"&gt;Intelligence at the IoT Edge – AWS IoT Greengrass&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Canonical (Canonical)</author><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 09:55:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How to avoid package End of Life through backporting </title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/how-to-avoid-package-end-of-life-through-backporting</link><description>&lt;p&gt;When a Git vulnerability hit systems past Ubuntu package end of life, teams had to reassess security options. Learn how to stay protected beyond standard support.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;In July 2025, git received &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/security/CVE-2025-48384"&gt;CVE-2025-48384&lt;/a&gt;, a high vulnerability allowing arbitrary code execution when cloning repositories. The US Cybersecurity and Infrastructure Security Agency added it to their Known Exploited Vulnerabilities catalog after confirming active exploitation in the wild.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your Ubuntu system had already passed the End of Standard Support when this vulnerability was disclosed, you faced a choice: subscribe to Ubuntu Pro for the security patch, or continue running git with a known remote code execution vulnerability on your developer workstations and CI/CD infrastructure. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This scenario highlights a critical decision point: how do you maintain security when packages lose standard support? This blog explores your options and how Canonical’s backporting strategy helps you stay protected. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;The impact of End of Standard Support&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Support lifecycle directly affects your system security. Although Canonical maintains LTS releases for extended periods, there inevitably comes a point where decisions are required to avoid running unsecured packages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Ubuntu 20.04 LTS reached End of Standard Support in April 2025, thousands of packages in the main repository lost free security maintenance. A typical enterprise server runs around 800 packages, which almost guarantees that some packages will no longer be covered by free security updates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Understanding End of Standard Support vs End of Life&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s what many users misunderstand: End of Standard Support and End of Life are different concepts for Canonical built and supported packages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical provides two types of security coverage. The first is standard security maintenance, which lasts 5 years and provides free security updates for packages in the main repository only. Universe repository packages never receive free security updates, even during this period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After 5 years, main repository packages stop receiving free updates but remain functional. Security patches continue to be developed and released for another 10 years through Ubuntu Pro subscriptions, the second type of coverage, covering both main and universe repositories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;End of Life occurs at the 15-year mark, when the Ubuntu Pro period with legacy add-on concludes. Only then do security patches stop being developed entirely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="314" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 917px) 917px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_917/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fbba5%2Flidia-random-slides.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fbba5%2Flidia-random-slides.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fbba5%2Flidia-random-slides.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fbba5%2Flidia-random-slides.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fbba5%2Flidia-random-slides.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_917/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fbba5%2Flidia-random-slides.png 917w" width="917"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re running Ubuntu and want to check your current support status, you can easily do this via the terminal:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;pro security-status&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This shows which packages have active security coverage and which represent potential vulnerability exposure in your infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;What are the actual risks?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dependency problem significantly compounds the risk. When package A depends on package B, which depends on package C, an unsupported package anywhere in that chain creates vulnerability across your entire stack. &lt;a href="https://www.endorlabs.com/learn/state-of-dependency-management-2023"&gt;Research from Endor Labs&lt;/a&gt; analyzing software packages found that 95 percent of all vulnerabilities are found in transitive dependencies, meaning most security risk in your software supply chain is indirect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Systems without security updates remain vulnerable to every threat disclosed after support ends. The git vulnerability demonstrates how attackers exploit publicly documented weaknesses. Malicious repositories become attack vectors for remote code execution on developer workstations and CI/CD systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond immediate security exposure, organizations face tangible compliance and operational consequences. The EU Cyber Resilience Act, which applies from December 2027, requires manufacturers to provide timely security updates throughout a product’s lifecycle. Frameworks like FedRAMP, FISMA, and HIPAA require FIPS-140 certified cryptographic modules, while PCI-DSS mandates current security patches and vendor support. Running unsupported packages puts organizations at risk of failing these regulatory requirements. Organizations also face compatibility issues when newer packages expect updated dependencies and limited support when troubleshooting production incidents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Your options when standard support ends&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Upgrade to a newer LTS release&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upgrading moves your infrastructure to an LTS version within its 5-year standard support window. This restores free security updates for packages in the main repository and eliminates the support gap for those packages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This approach works well when you have resources to test deployment thoroughly, your applications are compatible with the newer release, and you have time for comprehensive validation. The challenge is that major upgrades carry real costs and risks. Version jumps can break compatibility, require application changes, or introduce dependencies that need extensive testing before production deployment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start="2"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Enable Ubuntu Pro for expanded security maintenance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enabling Ubuntu Pro on your infrastructure extends security coverage from 5 years to 15 years for packages in both main and universe repositories. This allows you to continue running your current release while receiving backported security patches. Canonical’s security team actively scans, triages, and backports critical, high, and select medium CVEs to all maintained LTS releases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The backporting strategy means Canonical applies security fixes to your current package versions rather than forcing major upgrades. You receive vulnerability patches without the breaking changes that come with major version jumps or the re-certification requirements that disrupt tightly controlled compliance environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu Pro covers thousands of packages across main and universe. For organizations requiring the full 15-year support window, the legacy add-on becomes available after 10 years of coverage at 50% above the standard Ubuntu Pro subscription cost. We recommend this approach for organizations seeking cost-effective security and compliance. Ubuntu Pro offloads much of the vulnerability management effort while providing comprehensive coverage across open-source packages with simple, predictable pricing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read about Canonical’s technical approach to security backporting and long term maintenance in our documentation at &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/security/esm"&gt;ubuntu.com/security/esm&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start="3"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Run without security updates&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though not recommended, you can consciously choose to run packages without active support. This might be considered when the package handles genuinely non-critical functionality, the system operates in complete isolation from network exposure, or strong compensating controls effectively mitigate the vulnerability risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be explicit about this choice and thoroughly document it. Maintain a register of unsupported packages with clear business justification, documented risk assessment, and regular review schedules. This will help you audit your system much faster in the future. What represents acceptable risk today may not remain acceptable as the threat landscape evolves and new attack patterns emerge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Running without support through ignorance or inertia differs fundamentally from making a conscious risk acceptance decision with appropriate governance and executive approval.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;How expanded security maintenance works&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical’s security team monitors for vulnerabilities daily and evaluates their impact on supported packages. When vulnerabilities affect packages under Ubuntu Pro coverage, engineers apply available upstream patches or backport security fixes from newer versions to your maintained release. Updates undergo rigorous testing to verify stability and compatibility before becoming available through standard package management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For embargoed vulnerabilities like the recent git security issues, Canonical prepares fixes in advance and releases them precisely when the embargo lifts, ensuring you’re protected the moment the vulnerability becomes public knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This approach means you don’t face a forced choice between security and operational stability. You maintain your current, tested environment while receiving necessary security patches that preserve compatibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;How to choose the right approach after End of Standard support&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LTS release support timelines are predictable. Ubuntu 20.04 released in April 2020 and reached End of Standard Support in April 2025, exactly 5 years later. Begin planning at least 6 months before standard support concludes. This gives you time to audit affected packages, test upgrade paths, secure budget, and coordinate infrastructure changes. Strategic planning prevents emergency decisions under pressure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your decision depends on risk tolerance, compliance requirements, engineering capacity, and budget. Most enterprises use a combination approach. Overall, our suggestions are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You should choose to upgrade your LTS when you can test thoroughly, your stack supports the next LTS, and staying current aligns with your strategy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose expanded security maintenance when you need stability, lack upgrade resources, or require patches without version mandates.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You should &lt;strong&gt;only &lt;/strong&gt;accept running without updates if you can reasonably maintain minimal risk exposure, can implement strong compensating controls, and have explicit documented approval.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The worst outcome is no decision at all, allowing support coverage to lapse through inaction.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;What should you do today?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Run &lt;strong&gt;pro security-status&lt;/strong&gt; to assess your current coverage. Identify which packages will lose standard support and when.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Ubuntu 20.04 or earlier, standard support has ended. Those systems need decisions now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-pullquote"&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Explore Ubuntu Pro options at &lt;a href="http://ubuntu.com/pro"&gt;ubuntu.com/pro&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/contact-us/form?product=pro"&gt;contact our team&lt;/a&gt; to discuss your requirements.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Read more:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/about/release-cycle"&gt;Understand Ubuntu release cycle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/pro/linux-patch-management-with-pro"&gt;See which packages Ubuntu Pro supports&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/security/security-standards"&gt;Run Ubuntu in high-security environments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Lidia Luna Puerta (Lidia Luna Puerta)</author><category>backporting</category><category>EOL</category><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 09:15:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Showcasing open design in action: Loughborough University design students explore open source projects</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/showcasing-open-design-in-action-loughborough-university-design-students-explore-open-source-projects</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Last year, we collaborated with two design student teams from Loughborough University in the UK. These students were challenged to work on open source project briefs. Team 1 focused on non-code contributions, while Team 2’s brief was to create a unified documentation experience, giving them a chance to apply their design skills to real-world problems [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="372" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 660px) 660px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_660/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F42a7%2Fimage.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F42a7%2Fimage.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F42a7%2Fimage.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F42a7%2Fimage.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_660/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F42a7%2Fimage.png 660w" width="660"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year, we collaborated with two design student teams from Loughborough University in the UK. These students were challenged to work on open source project briefs. Team 1 focused on non-code contributions, while Team 2’s brief was to create a unified documentation experience, giving them a chance to apply their design skills to real-world problems within the open source ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We reached out to &lt;a href="https://www.lboro.ac.uk/schools/design-creative-arts/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"&gt;Loughborough University School of Design and Creative Arts&lt;/a&gt; because there is a real need for non-code contributions in the open source ecosystem. Design thinking, which goes beyond the code to consider the user experience, is paramount if we want open source to thrive and gain ever more widespread adoption. Each team tackled a unique challenge that reflects the growing need for design thinking in open source, where developers have traditionally led, but where a better user experience is now urgently needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post celebrates their thoughtful work, sharing reflections from their design journey, and invites others to consider contributing to open source projects!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interested in checking out the project briefs yourself? The briefs are open for anyone to explore, think about, and attempt to solve. Whether you’re thinking of ideas, writing them on a napkin, or developing your solution, there are no limitations to your creativity here! &lt;a href="https://assets.ubuntu.com/v1/7bd9c15e-project_briefs_for_universities.pdf" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"&gt;Get the briefs here&lt;/a&gt; (PDF).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Team 1: Improving design approachability in open source&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Project brief: Increase designer participation in open source projects and contributing non-code contributions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Objective: Help improve how designers engage with open source projects by lowering barriers to entry and encouraging more meaningful design contributions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Team members: &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/mirunaalini-meera-alagarajah-3755211b3/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"&gt;Mirunaalini Alagarajah&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/giridharpabbati/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"&gt;Giridhar pabbati&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/jiarui-he-579796336/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"&gt;Jiarui He&lt;/a&gt;, Lechen Zou, &lt;a href="https://sdcapgshow2025.lboro.ac.uk/student/clara-lin/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"&gt;Clara Lin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Check out their &lt;a href="https://assets.ubuntu.com/v1/52567bad-final_slides_cocreate_5_canonical_compressed.pdf" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"&gt;project presentation&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Reflection from the team&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h4 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;What was it like working on a real open source design challenge?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project really challenged us as a team, testing our collaboration, adaptability, and time management skills. Tackling a real client brief helped us engage more deeply with the problem and understand its real-world context. Working with Canonical was particularly motivating, as it gave us the sense that our efforts were contributing to something genuinely impactful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;What surprised you most about open source?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a team, we realised we hadn’t truly thought about the various barriers designers encounter when engaging with open source projects. We also found it fascinating that many designers are quite protective of their work, which makes open sharing a real challenge. It created a unique tension –everyone wanted to learn from others, but few felt comfortable giving their work away for free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;What design decision did your team focus on and why?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We used insights from our user research to guide our design direction, ensuring that each decision was grounded in evidence. Prototyping allowed us to test various design details and components, which helped us refine our approach and gain a much clearer sense of direction. As a team, we brought diverse backgrounds and skill sets—those with stronger design experience naturally took the lead in developing and refining the visual aspects of the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;How has this experience influenced how you think about design and collaboration?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On reflection, there were many possible directions we could have taken, but in hindsight, grounding our decisions in user insights and continuous testing helped align the team around a clear vision. Regular client feedback was invaluable in refining our approach and ensuring we stayed true to user needs. Additionally, leveraging each team member’s strengths allowed us to work more efficiently and make the most of our diverse skills. Overall, it was a valuable experience that taught us how to collaborate rapidly and effectively to address a real-world brief.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Team 2: Unifying Juju’s documentation ecosystem&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Project brief: Improve the accessibility, clarity, and cohesiveness of Juju’s documentation to enhance user experience and encourage adoption.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Objective: Reimagining how users discover and learn about Juju (Canonical’s open source application orchestration engine for the deployment, integration, and lifecycle management) by improving the documentation experience. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Team members:&lt;a href="https://sharvarirai.framer.website/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"&gt; Sharvari Rai&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/bavraj-virdi-120030254/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"&gt;Bavraj Virdi&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/xinya-wang-79297b390/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"&gt;Xinya Wang&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/siying-fan-324508368/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"&gt;Siying Fan&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/qingwan-yu-b138a8368/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"&gt;Qingwan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/qingwan-yu-b138a8368/"&gt; Yu&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Check out their &lt;a href="https://www.figma.com/deck/sl4Je3lBfLQIAHLTKVVJsK/Canonical?node-id=1-126&amp;amp;viewport=-88%2C-46%2C0.52&amp;amp;t=mKdUYsomHF7yzYyI-1&amp;amp;scaling=min-zoom&amp;amp;content-scaling=fixed&amp;amp;page-id=0%3A1" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"&gt;project presentation&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Reflection from the team&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h4 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;What were your first impressions about the problem space?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we were first introduced to the project, our initial reaction was that the brief felt highly technical and complex, with unfamiliar terms like charms, operators, and Kubernetes. As none of us came from a technical or programming background, the documentation space felt like a challenge for us was the learning curve of diving in and understanding what is in the documentation and what it means. We struggled to identify a clear starting point and to understand the overall purpose of Juju beyond the jargon. Since the platform is mainly aimed at developers, it was difficult at first to relate to or imagine user needs. Despite that, this initial confusion actually helped us empathise with potential users facing similar barriers, and it highlighted the importance of clarity and structure in the documentation. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;What was your approach to designing a more unified documentation experience?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our approach began with breaking down the brief into simpler terms and mapping the current documentation ecosystem so we could better understand the challenges. As a team, we created personas for both new and experienced users, which helped us think about different entry points and the level of guidance each group might need. We then sketched user journeys to highlight pain points and challenges. From there, we focused on developing a single, structured information architecture with clearer pathways for learning and troubleshooting.  The aim was to allow users to move confidently between different sections without having to relearn how to navigate each time. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;What were the biggest challenges your team encountered during the project?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main challenge was the steep learning curve of immersing ourselves in the technical complexity of the Juju ecosystem and its vast open source documentation, especially since most of us came from non-technical backgrounds. We had to quickly grasp the product and its entire linked ecosystem. As direct access to real users was limited, we relied heavily on secondary data, community forums, and the creation of personas to accurately map realistic pain points. Our constant goal was to balance technical accuracy with the required user-centred clarity, which pushed us to fundamentally rethink how developer documentation can effectively guide users without overwhelming them. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;What skills or takeaways are you bringing with you from this experience?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project was a major lesson in how to embrace and navigate ambiguity. This was a truly crucial learning experience when dealing with an unfamiliar domain, evolving product documentation, and diverse stakeholder needs. We significantly strengthened our ability to translate dense technical research into clear, actionable design recommendations. We also honed our communication and collaboration skills as a team, successfully aligning our user-focused vision with Canonical’s roadmap. Most importantly, we learned that user advocacy is vital even in highly technical environments, and that our focus is ultimately on humanising complex systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;🎉Congratulations to both teams!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We would like to thank and congratulate both teams for their creativity, thoughtful research, and commitment to enhancing open source experiences through design. They approached complex, open-ended problems with maturity and curiosity, and their outcomes were both inspiring and practical. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their fresh perspectives also reminded us of the value of questioning assumptions and looking at familiar challenges through new eyes, reinforcing how much we as practitioners can learn from emerging designers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We hope these projects have not only added valuable work to their portfolios but also opened doors to future engagement with open source communities. We encourage them (and any other designer out there) to continue exploring open source, contributing through design, and helping shape more inclusive, user-friendly technologies!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Interested in running a project like this?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you part of a university looking to bring open source design into your curriculum? &lt;a href="https://canonical.design/blog/open-design-the-opportunity-design-students-didnt-know-they-were-missing" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"&gt;We’re looking for academic partners&lt;/a&gt; who want to give students meaningful, real-world experiences while contributing to the global open source ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reach out at &lt;a href="mailto:opendesign@canonical.com" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"&gt;opendesign@canonical.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn more at &lt;a href="https://canonical.design/blog/open-design-the-opportunity-design-students-didnt-know-they-were-missing" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"&gt;Canonical.design&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Join the Canonical design team&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re looking for designers who care about craft and how systems work under the hood. At Canonical, design sits at the intersection of UX, engineering, and open source where we shape cohesive, accessible experiences across cloud, desktop, and IoT products.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you enjoy solving complex problems and turning technical depth into clarity, explore our open roles: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://canonical.com/careers/web-and-design" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"&gt;canonical.com/careers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Miguel Divo (Miguel Divo)</author><category>Design</category><category>open design</category><category>University</category><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 11:09:04 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Canonical Ubuntu and Ubuntu Pro now available on AWS European Sovereign Cloud</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/ubuntu-aws-european-sovereign-cloud</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Canonical announced it is a launch partner for the AWS European Sovereign Cloud, with Ubuntu and Ubuntu Pro now available. This new independent cloud for Europe enables organizations to run secure, enterprise workloads with full operational autonomy and EU data residency. By combining the performance and expanded security coverage of Ubuntu Pro with AWS sovereignty controls, customers can meet stringent EU regulatory requirements while continuing to innovate at scale.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;January 15, 2026 – Canonical, the publisher of Ubuntu and provider of open source security, support, and services, announced today that it is a launch partner for the AWS European Sovereign Cloud, a new independent cloud for Europe, with Ubuntu and Ubuntu Pro now available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical’s Ubuntu Pro delivers a securely designed, stable, and enterprise-ready foundation for open source innovation while providing customers with the same security, availability, and performance they expect from AWS. This enables customers to meet stringent operational autonomy and data residency requirements within the European Union (EU).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The AWS European Sovereign Cloud is a fully featured, independently operated sovereign cloud backed by strong technical controls, sovereign assurances, and legal protections designed to meet the needs of European governments and enterprises. The AWS European Sovereign Cloud infrastructure is entirely located within the EU and operates independently from existing regions. Customers using the AWS European Sovereign Cloud will benefit from the full power of AWS including the same services portfolio, security, availability, performance, familiar architecture, APIs, and innovations such as the AWS Nitro System.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The AWS European Sovereign Cloud represents a significant step forward for organizations operating under EU regulatory frameworks,”&lt;/em&gt; said Cindy Goldberg, VP Cloud and Silicon Partnerships at Canonical. &lt;em&gt; By combining the performance and the expanded security coverage of Ubuntu Pro with AWS’s sovereignty controls and technical assurances, we’re delivering the compliance support and innovation our customers need to accelerate their digital transformation while meeting stringent EU regulatory requirements.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discover Ubuntu and Ubuntu Pro on the AWS European Sovereign Cloud today on the AWS EC2 console. Launch now on the &lt;a href="https://eusc-de-east-1.console.amazonaws-eusc.eu/ec2/home?region=eusc-de-east-1#LaunchInstances:ami=ami-0a121bf2036630575"&gt;European Sovereign Cloud EC2 console&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;About Canonical &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical, the publisher of Ubuntu, provides open source security, support, and services. Our portfolio covers critical systems, from the smallest devices to the largest clouds, from the kernel to containers, from databases to AI. With customers that include top tech brands, emerging startups, governments and home users, Canonical delivers trusted open source for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn more at https://canonical.com/&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Canonical (Canonical)</author><category>AWS</category><category>Sovereign cloud</category><category>Ubuntu</category><category>Ubuntu Pro</category><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 22:06:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How to build DORA-ready infrastructure with verifiable provenance and reliable support</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/build-dora-ready-infrastructure-with-verifiable-provenance</link><description>&lt;p&gt;DORA requires organizations to know what they run, where it came from, and how it’s maintained. Learn how to build infrastructure with verifiable provenance.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;The Digital Operational Resilience Act (DORA) came into force across the EU on January 17, 2025, fundamentally changing how financial institutions must approach infrastructure and technology assets resilience. Its requirements around ICT risk management, operational resilience, and third-party oversight signal a broader shift that will ripple across regulated industries worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At its core, DORA demands something deceptively simple: organizations must know exactly what they’re running, where it came from, and how to fix it when something breaks. For technical teams managing complex stacks spanning bare metal, the OS, kernel, and applications, this translates into a hard requirement for provenance: transparent, verifiable lineage from source code all the way up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;The provenance problem: you can’t verify what you can’t see&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traditional vendor stacks create a fundamental compliance problem: they’re opaque by design. When you deploy a proprietary solution, you’re accepting someone else’s assurances about what’s inside. You can’t inspect the source code. You can’t verify the build process. You can’t independently validate that a security patch actually addresses the vulnerability it claims to fix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Software Bills of Materials (SBOMs) have emerged as an important transparency tool and represent progress, they fail to solve this fundamental inspection problem. An SBOM tells you what components are present in proprietary software, but you still can’t examine the source code itself or verify the build process yourself. For regulated organizations facing requirements like DORA, this creates a compliance gap, where you can document dependencies but cannot truly verify their integrity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DORA explicitly requires financial entities to maintain oversight of their ICT infrastructure, including third-party dependencies. So, how do you maintain oversight of something you can’t inspect?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open source becomes essential here. With open source software:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You get reproducible inspectability all the way down the supply chain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can trace every component back to the developer who wrote it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can verify builds&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can audit changes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can understand exactly what’s running in your environment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;The single developer problem (and why Ubuntu Pro matters)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s the uncomfortable truth about modern infrastructure: critical components in your stack likely trace back to a single developer somewhere on the internet, maintaining a library in their spare time. An estimate, based on analysis of &lt;a href="http://ecosyste.ms"&gt;ecosyste.ms&lt;/a&gt; data, shows that a relatively small group, on the order of ten thousand people, supports the majority of the world’s open source software users. In the Tidelift 2024 State of the Open Source Maintainer survey, 61% of unpaid maintainers reported working alone on their projects. When the Heartbleed vulnerability was discovered in 2014, OpenSSL—used by 66% of web servers at the time—was maintained by just a handful of volunteers, only one working full time, with the project receiving about $2,000 in annual donations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These individual maintainers are doing heroic work. But from a resilience perspective, it’s a risk. What happens when that developer moves on? Gets burned out? Simply stops maintaining the package?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is worsening: in 2024, almost 60% of maintainers reported having quit or considered quitting their maintenance work, with many citing burnout, insufficient compensation, and overwhelming demands on their time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Investing in open source is a form of infrastructure security: it reduces your dependence on unpaid, solo maintainers and builds sustainable maintenance pipelines with professional support, timely security patching, and long-term viability. When enterprises pay for Ubuntu Pro, part of that funding flows back into the open source ecosystem through Canonical’s upstream engineering work and direct financial support for the projects Ubuntu depends on.​&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical does not just repackage open source; our engineers contribute features and fixes upstream across the projects shipped in Ubuntu, and we commit security maintenance for components long after their upstream end of life, such as continuing to backport OpenSSL 1.1.1 fixes for supported Ubuntu releases. Ubuntu Pro packages this ecosystem investment into a single subscription: up to 15 years of security maintenance for thousands of open source packages, plus the assurance that Canonical is actively collaborating with and funding the communities behind them. Instead of betting your resilience on a single unpaid maintainer, you get a vendor whose business model is aligned with keeping that open source infrastructure secure and sustainable over the long term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;From responsibility to assurance: system-level, not vendor-level&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a fundamental difference between a vendor taking responsibility for their products and a platform providing assurance for your entire system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When an Ubuntu Pro customer from the financial industry asked, “How do we get all machines FIPS-enabled and CIS-compliant?”, that’s not a question about a single application. It’s a question about system-level security compliance across thousands of machines, down to the operating system and the metal beneath it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu Pro answers this by providing a single, verifiable stack with end-to-end provenance. The focus shifts from trusting individual vendors to establishing a unified security posture where every layer is supported, patched, and verifiable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For finance organizations, this changes the conversation from “Do we trust this vendor?” to “Can we verify and validate our entire infrastructure up to the application layer?” The answer needs to be yes, and you need documentation to prove it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;The DORA advantage: knowing what you don’t know&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discovering what you don’t know proves more challenging than fixing known compliance issues. What packages are actually running in production? Which versions? What’s their patch status? What potential exposures might an auditor find during their next review?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Ubuntu Pro, you get continuous visibility, security maintenance and support:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Complete inventory: Enumerate exactly what’s running across your infrastructure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provenance tracking: Every package has verifiable lineage back to source&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Continuous patching: Both main and universe repository packages receive security updates&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compliance tooling: Built-in capabilities for CIS hardening, FIPS certification, and compliance reporting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Beyond compliance: building for what comes next&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think of compliance as the baseline, not the goal. While DORA is a regulatory requirement for financial services in the EU, smart organizations across industries are using it as a model for their own resilience programs. The principles it codifies, operational resilience, supply chain transparency, systematic risk management, are universal concerns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trajectory is clear: more regulation, more scrutiny, more demands for transparency and provenance. When your industry’s equivalent of DORA arrives (and it will), you need infrastructure that can already demonstrate:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Verifiable provenance for every component in your stack&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Long-term support commitments backed by professional teams&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;System-level security compliance down to the OS and infrastructure layer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Complete source code transparency and documented patching processes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu Pro applies these principles to open source infrastructure, combining transparent components with long-term security maintenance and support so your stack is ready for whatever comes next.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn more about other security standards we support: &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/security/security-standards"&gt;ubuntu.com/security/security-standards&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-pullquote"&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/contact-us/form?product=pro"&gt;Get in touch&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/pro/free-trial"&gt;start a 30-day Ubuntu Pro free trial&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.eiopa.europa.eu/digital-operational-resilience-act-dora_en"&gt;Digital Operational Resilience Act (DORA) – EIOPA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/eli/reg/2022/2554/oj/eng"&gt;Regulation (EU) 2022/2554 – EUR-Lex&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://blog.tidelift.com/maintainer-burnout-is-real"&gt;Tidelift 2024 State of the Open Source Maintainer Report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://socket.dev/blog/the-unpaid-backbone-of-open-source"&gt;The Unpaid Backbone of Open Source – Socket&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/thebakersinstitute/2014/04/23/what-heartbleed-means-for-critical-infrastructure-2/"&gt;Critical infrastructure for the Web – Forbes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/blog/canonical-thanks-dev-giving-back-to-open-source-developers"&gt;Canonical + thanks.dev&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Lidia Luna Puerta (Lidia Luna Puerta)</author><category>Compliance</category><category>DORA</category><category>Security</category><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 09:53:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Deploy your Spring Boot application to production</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/deploy-spring-application-to-production</link><description>&lt;p&gt;In this article we walk through the steps required to deploy a Spring Boot application to production using Juju and Kubernetes. The goal is to showcase the integration of the application with essential services like PostgreSQL for database management and Traefik for ingress control.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;In a previous article, we covered how easy it is to create &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/blog/spring-boot-containers-made-easy"&gt;Spring Boot containers&lt;/a&gt; with Rockcraft. So the next logical step is to deploy and operate your application in a production environment. The Juju ecosystem is the key to making this process straightforward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this article we walk through the steps required to deploy a Spring Boot application to production using Juju and Kubernetes. The goal is to showcase the integration of the application with essential services like PostgreSQL for database management and Traefik for ingress control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="1080" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1920px) 1920px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F91ec%2FDiagram-deploy-spring-production-16_9.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F91ec%2FDiagram-deploy-spring-production-16_9.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F91ec%2FDiagram-deploy-spring-production-16_9.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F91ec%2FDiagram-deploy-spring-production-16_9.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F91ec%2FDiagram-deploy-spring-production-16_9.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F91ec%2FDiagram-deploy-spring-production-16_9.png 1920w" width="1920"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ordinarily, deploying and operating Spring Boot containers is easier said than done. Any non-trivial application will require integrations with other software components like databases, message brokers, and authentication services. Some of these components are complex to operate. What’s more, your application will need to be exposed to the outside world. And for Day 2 operations, you’ll also need to perform routine maintenance and properly monitor your application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, Juju provides a strong ecosystem composed of a multitude of high quality software operators that enables deployment, integration and lifecycle management at any scale, on any infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the release of the Spring Boot framework extensions for &lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/rockcraft/stable/"&gt;Rockcraft&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/charmcraft/stable/"&gt;Charmcraft&lt;/a&gt;, if your application follows the 12-factor methodology best practices, you can benefit from the Juju ecosystem out of the box.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are developing a Spring Boot application we recommend you to try out the &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/blog/devpack-spring-support-ubuntu"&gt;devpack support for Spring&lt;/a&gt; and then follow &lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/charmcraft/latest/tutorial/kubernetes-charm-spring-boot/"&gt;this tutorial to write your Spring Boot charm&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But without further ado, let’s see how it all works by charming &lt;a href="https://spring-petclinic.github.io/"&gt;spring-petclinic&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Set up a developer machine with Canonical Kubernetes and Juju&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will start with a virtual machine created from scratch using &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/multipass"&gt;Multipass&lt;/a&gt; and prepare our development machine with the help of the &lt;a href="https://github.com/canonical/concierge"&gt;Concierge&lt;/a&gt; tool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Launch the new virtual machine and shell into it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="p-code-snippet"&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__block--icon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;multipass launch --cpus 4 --disk 30G --memory 4G --name blogpost 24.04&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__block--icon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;multipass shell blogpost&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will provision the testing machine with Concierge, which will install and configure Rockcraft, Charmcraft, Canonical Kubernetes and Juju. Besides that, we will update the load balancer to serve under the machine’s main IP and install an OCI image registry:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="p-code-snippet"&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__block--icon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo snap install --classic concierge&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__block--icon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo concierge prepare -p k8s --charmcraft-channel latest/edge&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__block--icon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;PREFSRC=$(ip -4 -j route get 2.2.2.2 | jq -r '.[] | .prefsrc')&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__block--icon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo k8s set load-balancer.cidrs=$PREFSRC/32&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__block--icon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;curl https://raw.githubusercontent.com/canonical/spring-petclinic/refs/heads/resources/registry.yaml | kubectl apply -f - &lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Get spring-petclinic application&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://spring-petclinic.github.io/"&gt;spring-petclinic&lt;/a&gt; is the app we’ll be charming. It’s a sample application created by the Spring team to demonstrate a real-world web app using the Spring Framework. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clone the spring-petclinic repository. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="p-code-snippet"&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__block--icon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;git clone https://github.com/canonical/spring-petclinic.git&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__block--icon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;cd spring-petclinic&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following the &lt;a href="https://github.com/canonical/spring-petclinic"&gt;spring-petclinic repository instructions&lt;/a&gt;, you can build a jar and run it with the command line. It is quite easy, but clearly not production ready, even the database in-memory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Create the rock&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s prepare a rock – a compliant OCI image – for the application. We could use either Maven or Gradle to build the application, but for this example we will use Maven. From the spring-petclinic directory, remove the Gradle artifacts and initialize the rockcraft project:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="p-code-snippet"&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__block--icon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;rm -rf build.gradle gradlew gradle&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__block--icon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;rockcraft init --profile spring-boot-framework&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pack the rock and upload it to the OCI registry :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="p-code-snippet"&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__block--icon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;ROCKCRAFT_ENABLE_EXPERIMENTAL_EXTENSIONS=True rockcraft pack&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__block--icon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;rockcraft.skopeo copy --insecure-policy --dest-tls-verify=false oci-archive:spring-petclinic_0.1_amd64.rock docker://localhost:32000/spring-petclinic:0.1&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point we have a fully compliant OCI image. But to fully integrate with the Juju ecosystem we need a charm, a software operator. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Create the charm&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s build it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="p-code-snippet"&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__block--icon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;mkdir charm&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__block--icon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;cd charm&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__block--icon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;charmcraft init --profile spring-boot-framework --name spring-petclinic&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we want to use PostgreSQL instead of an in-memory database, add the following lines to the file &lt;code&gt;charmcraft.yaml&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="p-code-snippet"&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__blocklanguage-yaml"&gt;
&lt;code&gt;&lt;strong style="color: #204A87;"&gt;requires&lt;/strong&gt;:
  &lt;strong style="color: #204A87;"&gt;postgresql&lt;/strong&gt;:
    &lt;strong style="color: #204A87;"&gt;interface&lt;/strong&gt;: postgresql_client
    &lt;strong style="color: #204A87;"&gt;optional&lt;/strong&gt;: false
    &lt;strong style="color: #204A87;"&gt;limit&lt;/strong&gt;: 1&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And we are ready to create a charm. Pack it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="p-code-snippet"&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__block--icon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;CHARMCRAFT_ENABLE_EXPERIMENTAL_EXTENSIONS=True charmcraft pack&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Let’s test it&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point we have a charm for spring-petclinic that will integrate seamlessly with PostgreSQL. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s test it with a new Juju model in a Kubernetes cloud:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="p-code-snippet"&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__block--icon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;juju add-model spring-petclinic&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__block--icon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;juju deploy ./spring-petclinic_amd64.charm spring-petclinic --resource app-image=localhost:32000/spring-petclinic:0.1 --config app-profiles=postgres
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deploy PostgreSQL and Traefik and integrate with spring-petclinic:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="p-code-snippet"&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__block--icon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;juju deploy postgresql-k8s --trust&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__block--icon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;juju integrate spring-petclinic postgresql-k8s&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="p-code-snippet"&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__block--icon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;juju deploy traefik-k8s --trust&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__block--icon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;juju integrate spring-petclinic traefik-k8s&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a while, your production ready application will be ready for use! You can check it with the command &lt;code&gt;juju status&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="646" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1676px) 1676px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1676/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F8199%2Fterminal_screenshot-deploy-spring-production-screenshot.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F8199%2Fterminal_screenshot-deploy-spring-production-screenshot.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F8199%2Fterminal_screenshot-deploy-spring-production-screenshot.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F8199%2Fterminal_screenshot-deploy-spring-production-screenshot.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F8199%2Fterminal_screenshot-deploy-spring-production-screenshot.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F8199%2Fterminal_screenshot-deploy-spring-production-screenshot.png 1920w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1676/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F8199%2Fterminal_screenshot-deploy-spring-production-screenshot.png 1676w" width="1676"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can get the URL of the application with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="p-code-snippet"&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__block--icon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;juju run traefik-k8s/0 show-proxied-endpoints&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And just like that, you can use it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="740" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1295px) 1295px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1295/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fd600%2Ffirefox_screenshot-1.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fd600%2Ffirefox_screenshot-1.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fd600%2Ffirefox_screenshot-1.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fd600%2Ffirefox_screenshot-1.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fd600%2Ffirefox_screenshot-1.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fd600%2Ffirefox_screenshot-1.png 1920w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1295/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fd600%2Ffirefox_screenshot-1.png 1295w" width="1295"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The application is running in a Kubernetes cluster, with Trafik acting as an ingress. Your spring-petclinic application is now using PostgreSQL to store its data. The Charmed PostgreSQL K8s has provided credentials for the database to the spring-petclinic application, and is ready to be operated in a production-grade environment. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not bad for a start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Get in touch&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you have a project or setup where you want to employ this solution? If you have any questions about the 12-factor tooling for Rockcraft and Charmcraft, reach out in our &lt;a href="https://matrix.to/#/#12-factor-charms:ubuntu.com"&gt;Matrix Channel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;What’s next?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/charmcraft/latest/tutorial/kubernetes-charm-spring-boot/"&gt;Follow the Spring Boot tutorial&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/charmcraft/stable/howto/manage-charms/#publish-a-charm-on-charmhub"&gt;Publish your charm in CharmHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Javier de la Puente (Javier de la Puente)</author><category>charm</category><category>Charms</category><category>cloud</category><category>Juju</category><category>juju charms</category><category>kubernetes</category><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 12:00:54 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Minimal Ubuntu Pro: lean images backed by enterprise-grade security</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/minimal-ubuntu-pro-on-public-clouds</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The security landscape is growing continually in complexity. Whatever industry you work in, your organization has to contend with evolving threats and ever-stricter compliance requirements, whilst at the same time facing pressure to build fast and scale smart. This is especially true when innovating on the public cloud.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Deploy Minimal Ubuntu Pro across AWS, Azure, and Google Cloud&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The security landscape is growing continually in complexity. Whatever industry you work in, your organization has to contend with evolving threats and ever-stricter compliance requirements, whilst at the same time facing pressure to build fast and scale smart. This is especially true when innovating on the public cloud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Minimal Ubuntu Pro is built to help you meet those challenges. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Minimized attack surface. Enhanced security.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Users of Ubuntu value its accessibility, robustness, and mature ecosystem. That’s why Canonical works with major cloud vendors to make optimized Ubuntu images available on their platforms. This includes Minimal Ubuntu – Ubuntu images which are optimized to have the smallest footprint possible and make security more straightforward. Minimal Ubuntu Pro builds on these images by making security in the public cloud more efficient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu Pro is Canonical’s comprehensive subscription for open source security. Through Ubuntu Pro, organizations receive up to 15 years of security maintenance (with the legacy add-on), tools for compliance automation, and kernel live patching. Minimal Ubuntu Pro brings these features to Minimal Ubuntu, combined with a convenient, metered per-hour billing on Amazon EC2, Google GCP and Microsoft Azure. By bringing these two technologies together, customers can combine the smallest Ubuntu footprint with enterprise-grade security and compliance features. It is the perfect starting point for automated cloud deployments in your production environments. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether you are deploying cloud workloads, containers, or regulated infrastructure, Minimal Ubuntu Pro offers a unique blend of minimalism, control, and long-term support, without sacrificing compatibility or flexibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Why security-aware companies choose Minimal Ubuntu Pro&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Perfect for cloud operations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Minimal Ubuntu Pro builds on the strengths of Minimal Ubuntu: the smallest Ubuntu base image for VMs and containers. Its lightweight design enables faster provisioning and scaling, with a 50% smaller image size and 40% faster boot times. At the same time, it retains optimizations for leading cloud hypervisors (AWS, GCP, Azure, KVM, LXD) through a custom kernel, drivers, and agents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re running microservices, containerized applications, or ephemeral workloads, this is the image you want on the public cloud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tight control over installed software&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Minimal Ubuntu Pro is fully compatible with the entire Ubuntu package ecosystem. Applications that already work on classic Ubuntu Server will retain full compatibility, provided dependencies are installed. You decide exactly what your environment includes, with the added benefit of extended security coverage for critical and high CVEs, including third-party open source packages, delivered through the Ubuntu Pro subscription.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This fine-grained control is crucial for DevSecOps practices, automated CI/CD pipelines, and infrastructure-as-code workflows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reduced attack surface by design&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every unnecessary package is a potential risk. Minimal Ubuntu Pro ships with only the essential components required to boot and connect, dramatically reducing exposure. Fewer packages mean fewer CVEs to track, fewer patches to apply, and less overall maintenance. For example, documentation, text editors, and locale files are removed, leaving only what’s necessary to run your workloads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This makes Minimal Ubuntu Pro ideal for teams building golden images, zero-trust environments, or security-hardened cloud instances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Enterprise-grade hardening and compliance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu Pro unlocks advanced security and compliance features, including up to 15 years of CVE patching across both Main and Universe repositories for Ubuntu LTS releases, optional FIPS 140-3 certified cryptographic modules for government compliance, and CIS and DISA-STIG hardening profiles for regulated environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether your target is FedRAMP, NIST, HIPAA, or another framework, Minimal Ubuntu Pro helps accelerate compliance with trusted tooling and validated configurations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Available on all the major cloud platforms&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Minimal Ubuntu Pro is available on AWS, Azure, and GCP. Whichever platform you choose to innovate on, Minimal Ubuntu Pro offers consistency and robustness:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Comes with an optimized kernel tailored for each cloud environment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Certified across all supported virtual machine types and instance families&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maintains the same deep cloud integration as standard Ubuntu Server, including support for telemetry, fleet management, and platform-specific services&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;How to get it&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;On AWS:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using AWS Marketplace by searching for “&lt;a href="https://aws.amazon.com/marketplace/search/results?searchTerms=Minimal+Ubuntu+Pro&amp;amp;CREATOR=565feec9-3d43-413e-9760-c651546613f2&amp;amp;filters=CREATOR"&gt;Minimal Ubuntu Pro&lt;/a&gt;”  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using AWS CLI:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;aws ssm get-parameters --names /aws/service/canonical/ubuntu/pro-minimal/$VERSION/stable/current/amd64/hvm/ebs-gp2/ami-id&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where &lt;code&gt;$VERSION&lt;/code&gt; is one of 20.04, 22.04 or 24.04 (For 24.04 you need to change &lt;code&gt;ebs-gp2&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;ebs-gp3&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;On GCP:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using Google Cloud Console by selecting “Ubuntu Pro” in the operating system selection and “&lt;strong&gt;Ubuntu 2x.04 LTS Minimal Pro&lt;/strong&gt;” as the version.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using Google Cloud Shell and booting a VM, specifying “&lt;code&gt;image=projects/ubuntu-os-pro-cloud/global/images/ubuntu-minimal-pro…&lt;/code&gt;”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;On Azure:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Selecting &lt;strong&gt;Minimal Ubuntu Pro Azure&lt;/strong&gt; Marketplace or Portal:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For 20.04 LTS, use the dedicated&lt;a href="https://marketplace.microsoft.com/en-us/product/virtual-machines/canonical.0001-com-ubuntu-pro-minimal-focal"&gt; Ubuntu Pro Minimal 20.04&lt;/a&gt; listing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For 22.04 and 24.04 LTS, find the unified&lt;a href="https://marketplace.microsoft.com/en-us/product/virtual-machines/canonical.ubuntu-22_04-lts"&gt; Ubuntu 22.04 LTS&lt;/a&gt; or&lt;a href="https://marketplace.microsoft.com/en-us/product/virtual-machines/canonical.ubuntu-24_04-lts"&gt; 24.04 LTS&lt;/a&gt; offers and select the “&lt;strong&gt;Ubuntu Pro Minimal&lt;/strong&gt;” plan.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using CLI:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;az vm create \
  --name $VIRTUAL_MACHINE_NAME \
  --resource-group $RESOURCE_GROUP_NAME \
  --image $UBUNTU_IMAGE_URN \
  --generate-ssh-keys&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where &lt;code&gt;$UBUNTU_IMAGE_URN&lt;/code&gt; is either:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;Canonical:0001-com-ubuntu-pro-minimal-focal:pro-minimal-20_04-lts:latest&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;Canonical:ubuntu-22_04-lts:ubuntu-pro-minimal:latest&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;Canonical:ubuntu-24_04-lts:ubuntu-pro-minimal:latest&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Next steps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Minimal Ubuntu Pro offers a powerful combination of performance, precision, and protection. It’s a practical solution for organizations seeking to scale confidently while adhering to the most stringent security and compliance standards. With Minimal Ubuntu Pro, you gain precise control over your environment, resulting in a minimal attack surface and expanded security coverage against critical and high-severity CVEs from the moment it’s deployed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get Minimal Ubuntu Pro 24.04 on &lt;a href="https://aws.amazon.com/marketplace/pp/prodview-4yqsoi5afvjqu"&gt;AWS&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href="https://marketplace.microsoft.com/en-us/product/virtual-machines/canonical.ubuntu-24_04-lts"&gt;Azure&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href="https://console.cloud.google.com/compute/instancesAdd?imageId=5466964067713924514&amp;amp;imageProjectId=ubuntu-os-pro-cloud"&gt;GPC&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Further reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/public-cloud/all-clouds-explanation/ubuntu-base-and-minimal-images/"&gt;Ubuntu base and minimal images – Public Cloud documentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://wiki.ubuntu.com/Minimal"&gt;What is Minimal Ubuntu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Carlos Bravo (Carlos Bravo)</author><category>AWS</category><category>azure</category><category>GCP</category><category>minimal ubuntu</category><category>Ubuntu Pro</category><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 15:07:56 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>London called, and the world answered: creating a Summit without borders</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/london-called-and-the-world-answered-creating-a-summit-without-borders</link><description>&lt;p&gt;When we announced that the Ubuntu Summit 25.10 would be a remote event, we knew we were taking a big step. We asked ourselves: how can we capture the spirit of an in-person community event and convey its energy through a screen? How can we connect the circle of friends from all over the world? [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;When we announced that the Ubuntu Summit 25.10 would be a remote event, we knew we were taking a big step. We asked ourselves: how can we capture the spirit of an in-person community event and convey its energy through a screen? How can we connect the circle of friends from all over the world? We certainly had an ambitious quest with the Quokka edition of the Ubuntu Summit!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"&gt;&lt;div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper"&gt;
&lt;iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="304" loading="lazy" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/gKMz7FVPJjo?feature=oembed" title="Ubuntu Summit 25.10 | Highlights" width="540"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class="wp-element-caption"&gt;Ubuntu Summit 25.10 | Highlights&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;The digital hallway track&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have been to an in-person event, you most likely have enjoyed the moments between talks. Those unscripted, unplanned parts of a conference create the hallway track experience. And while presentations bring valuable knowledge the hallway track creates connections, opens the door to collaboration and community building. Our quest was noble but challenging: we wanted to ensure that no matter where you live, you had a front row seat to the future of open source. And what we saw from you was incredibly inspiring. You tuned in, engaged with the speakers, and really created the most welcoming and fun remote hallway track. The Ubuntu Discourse exploded with activities! We loved seeing the &lt;a href="https://discourse.ubuntu.com/t/ubupets-share-a-photo/69964"&gt;lovely UbuPets&lt;/a&gt;, your awesome &lt;a href="https://discourse.ubuntu.com/t/screenshot-showcase-share-a-photo/70239/23"&gt;screenshot showcase&lt;/a&gt;, and the engagement with the polls. We also embarked together on an easter egg hunt throughout the event, with all sorts of Ubuntu related logos hidden in the stream.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Open source, open music&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We know that every quest needs an epic soundtrack! In our case, the soundtrack had to be as open source as the event. The amazing folks at &lt;a href="https://www.lorenzosmusic.com/"&gt;Lorenzo’s Music&lt;/a&gt; took on the challenge and put together the Creative Commons stream that  kept the energy high throughout the event. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was an incredible experience that took a lot of work and coordination between talented artists, and we’re not just talking about music. &lt;a href="https://www.sylvia-ritter.com/"&gt;Sylvia Ritter&lt;/a&gt; provided her fantastic artwork for an amazing visual experience. Ryno crafted the stream for both days and piped it through to the Lorenzo’s Music YouTube channel, together with song metadata. Last but not least, Creative Commons artists played live sets at the end of each day. Want to tune in and relive the sounds of the summit? Check out &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xDqJvZXkqFc"&gt;day one&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PpyNRlyc1rw"&gt;day two&lt;/a&gt; Creative Commons music streams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="1143" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 2027px) 2027px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_2027/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F0e13%2FUbuntu-Summit-25.10-CCMUSIC.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F0e13%2FUbuntu-Summit-25.10-CCMUSIC.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F0e13%2FUbuntu-Summit-25.10-CCMUSIC.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F0e13%2FUbuntu-Summit-25.10-CCMUSIC.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F0e13%2FUbuntu-Summit-25.10-CCMUSIC.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F0e13%2FUbuntu-Summit-25.10-CCMUSIC.png 1920w" width="2027"/&gt;&lt;figcaption class="wp-element-caption"&gt;Ubuntu Summit 25.10 Creative Commons music stream.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;The extended effect&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, the Ubuntu Summit was about global connection, going beyond London and the main stage. The event also connected us to the local Ubuntu circles from all over the world. The Ubuntu Summit Extended events are what turned a remote conference into a global celebration of the spirit of Ubuntu: “I am because we all are”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The great thing about the extended events was that each community put their own spin on the event. In Uyo, the &lt;a href="https://discourse.ubuntu.com/t/ubuntu-25-10-summit-extended-uyo-edition/71564"&gt;Nigerian community gathered 40 developers&lt;/a&gt;, celebrated the release of Ubuntu 25.10, and hosted their own set of talks. The &lt;a href="https://discourse.ubuntu.com/t/ubuntu-summit-25-10-portugal-extension/71092"&gt;Ubuntu Portugal community&lt;/a&gt; did not just watch the stream. They synced up between Porto and Lisbon, shared meals, discussions, sightseeing, in a true representation of the spirit of Ubuntu. In Windhoek, the &lt;a href="https://discourse.ubuntu.com/t/ubuntu-25-10-summit-extended-namibia/74741"&gt;Namibian community&lt;/a&gt; organized a gathering of local open source enthusiasts and embraced the spirit of the new Ubuntu Summit experience. Over in Thessaloniki, the &lt;a href="https://eiosifidis.blogspot.com/2025/10/ubuntu-summit-extended-25.10-release-party.html"&gt;Greek community&lt;/a&gt; transformed the University of Macedonia into a buzzing hub of discussion and discovery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From university halls to hackerspaces, you proved that while the signal was digital, the connection was human.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="1600" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 2000px) 2000px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_2000/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fdde1%2FUbuntu-Summit-25.10-extended-collage.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fdde1%2FUbuntu-Summit-25.10-extended-collage.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fdde1%2FUbuntu-Summit-25.10-extended-collage.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fdde1%2FUbuntu-Summit-25.10-extended-collage.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fdde1%2FUbuntu-Summit-25.10-extended-collage.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fdde1%2FUbuntu-Summit-25.10-extended-collage.png 1920w" width="2000"/&gt;&lt;figcaption class="wp-element-caption"&gt;Ubuntu Summit Extended events organized by local communities.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Talks that took us to the stars… or was it Mars?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ubuntu Summit is a showcase for the innovative and the ambitious, and Ubuntu Summit 25.10 delivered some of our most audacious talks yet. If you missed the live stream, do not worry! You can find the &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLwFSk464RMxmyKN2yob1dcIbrUuJupDQQ"&gt;Ubuntu Summit 25.10 playlist on YouTube&lt;/a&gt; covering Life, the Universe, and Everything!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don’t know where to start, we have a few suggestions for you:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://discourse.ubuntu.com/t/doom-in-space/67019"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOOM in Space&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; We always say Ubuntu is everywhere, but &lt;strong&gt;Ólafur Waage&lt;/strong&gt; proved it by running DOOM on the European Space Agency’s OPS-SAT satellite. This talk perfectly captured the spirit of the Ubuntu Summit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://discourse.ubuntu.com/t/elevating-the-linux-desktop-with-cosmic-de/67250"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elevating The Linux Desktop with COSMIC DE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Victoria Brekenfeld&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Carl Richell&lt;/strong&gt; inspired us with the impressive COSMIC desktop environment, showing us how Rust is elevating the Linux desktop experience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://discourse.ubuntu.com/t/are-we-stuck-with-the-same-desktop-ux-forever/67253"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are We Stuck with the Same Desktop UX Forever?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Scott Jenson&lt;/strong&gt; challenged us to think bigger about our interfaces. His talk was a masterclass on breaking free from old paradigms, and why open source is the perfect playground for the next generation of desktop UX.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="1600" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 2000px) 2000px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_2000/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fdfd4%2FUbuntu-Summit-25.10-talks-collage.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fdfd4%2FUbuntu-Summit-25.10-talks-collage.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fdfd4%2FUbuntu-Summit-25.10-talks-collage.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fdfd4%2FUbuntu-Summit-25.10-talks-collage.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fdfd4%2FUbuntu-Summit-25.10-talks-collage.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fdfd4%2FUbuntu-Summit-25.10-talks-collage.png 1920w" width="2000"/&gt;&lt;figcaption class="wp-element-caption"&gt;Ubuntu Summit 25.10 talks.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Thank you to our global circle of friends&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether you were &lt;a href="https://ubu.link/ubuntusummit-extended"&gt;organizing a watch party&lt;/a&gt; in Lisbon, debating the future of AI on Discourse, or just enjoying the stream with a cup of tea at home, &lt;strong&gt;thank you! &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You proved that the Ubuntu Summit is more than a venue; it is a community. By going remote, we didn’t step back, we reached out. And because of you, we empowered more voices and sparked more ideas than ever before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ubuntu Summit 25.10 is a wrap, but the clock is already ticking for the Ubuntu Summit 26.04 adventure. Until then, keep the conversation going on Discourse, enjoy the playlist, and if you are feeling innovative and ambitious, &lt;a href="https://ubu.link/ubuntusummit-cfp"&gt;submit a talk!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><author>ilvipero (ilvipero)</author><category>Ubuntu</category><category>Ubuntu Summit</category><category>ubuntu summit 25.10</category><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 14:46:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Canonical announces Ubuntu support for the NVIDIA Rubin platform</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/nvidia-vera-rubin-ubuntu-support</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Official Ubuntu support for the NVIDIA Rubin platform, including the NVIDIA Vera Rubin NVL72 rack-scale systems, announced at CES 2026 CES 2026, Las Vegas. – Canonical, the publisher of Ubuntu, is pleased to announce official support for the NVIDIA Rubin platform and the latest distributions of the new NVIDIA Nemotron 3 open models.&amp;nbsp; As AI [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Official Ubuntu support for the NVIDIA Rubin platform, including the NVIDIA Vera Rubin NVL72 rack-scale systems, announced at CES 2026&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;CES 2026, Las Vegas.&lt;/em&gt; – Canonical, the publisher of Ubuntu, is pleased to announce official support for the NVIDIA Rubin platform and the latest distributions of the new &lt;a href="https://www.nvidia.com/en-us/ai-data-science/foundation-models/nemotron/"&gt;NVIDIA Nemotron&lt;/a&gt; 3 open models. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As AI workloads transition from small-scale proof of concepts to massive-scale AI factories, the need for a stable, high-performance operating system substrate has never been greater. Ubuntu provides that foundation, unifying the NVIDIA Vera CPU, NVIDIA Rubin GPU, and &lt;a href="https://www.nvidia.com/en-us/networking/products/data-processing-unit/"&gt;NVIDIA BlueField-4 DPU&lt;/a&gt; into a cohesive execution environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;AI democratization requires more than powerful silicon; it needs a secure, frictionless environment from cloud to edge&lt;/em&gt;,” said Justin Boitano, Vice President, Enterprise AI Products, NVIDIA. “&lt;em&gt;Our work with Canonical ensures enterprises can deploy the NVIDIA Rubin platform, including the rack-scale Vera Rubin NVL72, on the Ubuntu foundation they already trust, streamlining the path from development to production with enterprise-grade security, and removing friction so organizations can innovate with confidence.&lt;/em&gt;“&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;Our collaboration with NVIDIA reinforces Canonical’s mission to democratize AI&lt;/em&gt;,” said Cindy Goldberg, VP Cloud and Silicon Partnerships at Canonical. “&lt;em&gt;By unifying the CPU, GPU, and DPU into a single, cohesive Ubuntu execution environment, we are making it easier to build private or sovereign clouds and the next generation of intelligent applications. Enterprises can build for the future on a secure foundation they trust.&lt;/em&gt;“&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First-class Arm support for Vera Rubin&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NVIDIA Vera Rubin NVL72 rack presents a scalable architecture for integrated AI compute, pairing the custom Arm-based Vera CPU with the Rubin GPU. In Ubuntu 26.04, Arm is a first-class citizen with x86 performance parity. Canonical is integrating critical upstream features including Nested Virtualization and MPAM (Memory System Resource Partitioning and Monitoring). These tools enable providers to partition memory bandwidth and cache at the hardware level, ensuring predictable performance for multi-tenant AI workloads. This infrastructure will be further reinforced with native Arm support in&lt;a href="https://canonical.com/maas/blog/openstack-with-sunbeam-for-medium-scale-cloud-infrastructure"&gt; OpenStack Sunbeam&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/data/spark"&gt;Apache Spark&lt;/a&gt;, allowing data engineers to run end-to-end pipelines on Arm-native silicon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, Ubuntu serves as the host OS for &lt;a href="https://www.nvidia.com/en-us/data-center/mission-control/"&gt;NVIDIA Mission Control&lt;/a&gt; software, which accelerates every aspect of infrastructure operations — from configuring deployments and integrating with facilities to managing clusters and workloads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Streamlined inference with Nemotron inference snaps&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deploying large language models (LLMs) often involves complex dependency management and version conflicts. To solve this, Canonical has introduced &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/blog/canonical-releases-inference-snaps"&gt;inference snaps&lt;/a&gt;. In a recent &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/live/rR3TpJvM150?si=MNWEIdBTXz_B6Eeu"&gt;livestream with the NVIDIA Developer community&lt;/a&gt;, Canonical’s team presented inference snaps for DGX Spark, showing how a single snap install command brings silicon-optimized AI models to every Ubuntu machine. To further this effort, Canonical will be collaborating with the NVIDIA team on packaging and distribution of the NVIDIA Nemotron-3 family of open models, starting with Nano models. Packaging these models using inference snaps provides a containerized, immutable environment that includes all necessary libraries and runtimes, ensuring that it is optimized for the new NVIDIA platforms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BlueField-4 and scalable storage&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Performance of the Rubin platform is further amplified by its data pipeline. Canonical is recommitting to the NVIDIA BlueField-4 DPU as an important networking and security component of NVIDIA platforms. With 64 NVIDIA Grace CPU cores and 800G/s throughput, BlueField-4 makes scaling AI Factories even more efficient. Ubuntu serves as a foundational environment for &lt;a href="https://developer.nvidia.com/networking/doca"&gt;NVIDIA DOCA&lt;/a&gt;  – allowing for seamless offloading of networking, storage, and security tasks from the Vera CPU to the DPU.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In collaboration with storage partners, Canonical is ensuring that Ubuntu’s storage subsystem is optimized for the GPUDirect Storage capabilities of BlueField-4. This enables high-speed data access between NVMe storage and Rubin GPU memory, eliminating bottlenecks. Whether deploying on-premises or in a sovereign cloud, the combination of Ubuntu and BlueField-4 provides the bare-metal isolation and hardware-root-of-trust necessary for secure, multi-tenant AI infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Learn more&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Visit us at CES booth #10562 in LVCC, North Hall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find out more about &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/nvidia"&gt;Canonical’s collaboration with NVIDIA.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Canonical (Canonical)</author><category>AI</category><category>AI/ML</category><category>nvidia</category><category>NVIDIA AI Enterprise</category><category>Ubuntu</category><pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 23:15:00 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>