<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Ubuntu blog</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/feed</link><description>Ubuntu blog feed</description><atom:link href="https://ubuntu.com//blog/feed" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>Python Feedgen</generator><lastBuildDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 12:07:09 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>How to avoid package End of Life through backporting </title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/how-to-avoid-package-end-of-life-through-backporting</link><description>&lt;p&gt;When a Git vulnerability hit systems past Ubuntu package end of life, teams had to reassess security options. Learn how to stay protected beyond standard support.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;In July 2025, git received &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/security/CVE-2025-48384"&gt;CVE-2025-48384&lt;/a&gt;, a high vulnerability allowing arbitrary code execution when cloning repositories. The US Cybersecurity and Infrastructure Security Agency added it to their Known Exploited Vulnerabilities catalog after confirming active exploitation in the wild.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your Ubuntu system had already passed the End of Standard Support when this vulnerability was disclosed, you faced a choice: subscribe to Ubuntu Pro for the security patch, or continue running git with a known remote code execution vulnerability on your developer workstations and CI/CD infrastructure. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This scenario highlights a critical decision point: how do you maintain security when packages lose standard support? This blog explores your options and how Canonical’s backporting strategy helps you stay protected. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;The impact of End of Standard Support&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Support lifecycle directly affects your system security. Although Canonical maintains LTS releases for extended periods, there inevitably comes a point where decisions are required to avoid running unsecured packages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Ubuntu 20.04 LTS reached End of Standard Support in April 2025, thousands of packages in the main repository lost free security maintenance. A typical enterprise server runs around 800 packages, which almost guarantees that some packages will no longer be covered by free security updates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Understanding End of Standard Support vs End of Life&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s what many users misunderstand: End of Standard Support and End of Life are different concepts for Canonical built and supported packages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical provides two types of security coverage. The first is standard security maintenance, which lasts 5 years and provides free security updates for packages in the main repository only. Universe repository packages never receive free security updates, even during this period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After 5 years, main repository packages stop receiving free updates but remain functional. Security patches continue to be developed and released for another 10 years through Ubuntu Pro subscriptions, the second type of coverage, covering both main and universe repositories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;End of Life occurs at the 15-year mark, when the Ubuntu Pro period with legacy add-on concludes. Only then do security patches stop being developed entirely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="314" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 917px) 917px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_917/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fbba5%2Flidia-random-slides.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fbba5%2Flidia-random-slides.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fbba5%2Flidia-random-slides.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fbba5%2Flidia-random-slides.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fbba5%2Flidia-random-slides.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_917/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fbba5%2Flidia-random-slides.png 917w" width="917"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re running Ubuntu and want to check your current support status, you can easily do this via the terminal:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;pro security-status&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This shows which packages have active security coverage and which represent potential vulnerability exposure in your infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;What are the actual risks?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dependency problem significantly compounds the risk. When package A depends on package B, which depends on package C, an unsupported package anywhere in that chain creates vulnerability across your entire stack. &lt;a href="https://www.endorlabs.com/learn/state-of-dependency-management-2023"&gt;Research from Endor Labs&lt;/a&gt; analyzing software packages found that 95 percent of all vulnerabilities are found in transitive dependencies, meaning most security risk in your software supply chain is indirect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Systems without security updates remain vulnerable to every threat disclosed after support ends. The git vulnerability demonstrates how attackers exploit publicly documented weaknesses. Malicious repositories become attack vectors for remote code execution on developer workstations and CI/CD systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond immediate security exposure, organizations face tangible compliance and operational consequences. The EU Cyber Resilience Act, which applies from December 2027, requires manufacturers to provide timely security updates throughout a product’s lifecycle. Frameworks like FedRAMP, FISMA, and HIPAA require FIPS-140 certified cryptographic modules, while PCI-DSS mandates current security patches and vendor support. Running unsupported packages puts organizations at risk of failing these regulatory requirements. Organizations also face compatibility issues when newer packages expect updated dependencies and limited support when troubleshooting production incidents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Your options when standard support ends&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Upgrade to a newer LTS release&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upgrading moves your infrastructure to an LTS version within its 5-year standard support window. This restores free security updates for packages in the main repository and eliminates the support gap for those packages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This approach works well when you have resources to test deployment thoroughly, your applications are compatible with the newer release, and you have time for comprehensive validation. The challenge is that major upgrades carry real costs and risks. Version jumps can break compatibility, require application changes, or introduce dependencies that need extensive testing before production deployment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start="2"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Enable Ubuntu Pro for expanded security maintenance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enabling Ubuntu Pro on your infrastructure extends security coverage from 5 years to 15 years for packages in both main and universe repositories. This allows you to continue running your current release while receiving backported security patches. Canonical’s security team actively scans, triages, and backports critical, high, and select medium CVEs to all maintained LTS releases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The backporting strategy means Canonical applies security fixes to your current package versions rather than forcing major upgrades. You receive vulnerability patches without the breaking changes that come with major version jumps or the re-certification requirements that disrupt tightly controlled compliance environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu Pro covers thousands of packages across main and universe. For organizations requiring the full 15-year support window, the legacy add-on becomes available after 10 years of coverage at 50% above the standard Ubuntu Pro subscription cost. We recommend this approach for organizations seeking cost-effective security and compliance. Ubuntu Pro offloads much of the vulnerability management effort while providing comprehensive coverage across open-source packages with simple, predictable pricing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read about Canonical’s technical approach to security backporting and long term maintenance in our documentation at &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/security/esm"&gt;ubuntu.com/security/esm&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start="3"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Run without security updates&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though not recommended, you can consciously choose to run packages without active support. This might be considered when the package handles genuinely non-critical functionality, the system operates in complete isolation from network exposure, or strong compensating controls effectively mitigate the vulnerability risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be explicit about this choice and thoroughly document it. Maintain a register of unsupported packages with clear business justification, documented risk assessment, and regular review schedules. This will help you audit your system much faster in the future. What represents acceptable risk today may not remain acceptable as the threat landscape evolves and new attack patterns emerge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Running without support through ignorance or inertia differs fundamentally from making a conscious risk acceptance decision with appropriate governance and executive approval.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;How expanded security maintenance works&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical’s security team monitors for vulnerabilities daily and evaluates their impact on supported packages. When vulnerabilities affect packages under Ubuntu Pro coverage, engineers apply available upstream patches or backport security fixes from newer versions to your maintained release. Updates undergo rigorous testing to verify stability and compatibility before becoming available through standard package management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For embargoed vulnerabilities like the recent git security issues, Canonical prepares fixes in advance and releases them precisely when the embargo lifts, ensuring you’re protected the moment the vulnerability becomes public knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This approach means you don’t face a forced choice between security and operational stability. You maintain your current, tested environment while receiving necessary security patches that preserve compatibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;How to choose the right approach after End of Standard support&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LTS release support timelines are predictable. Ubuntu 20.04 released in April 2020 and reached End of Standard Support in April 2025, exactly 5 years later. Begin planning at least 6 months before standard support concludes. This gives you time to audit affected packages, test upgrade paths, secure budget, and coordinate infrastructure changes. Strategic planning prevents emergency decisions under pressure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your decision depends on risk tolerance, compliance requirements, engineering capacity, and budget. Most enterprises use a combination approach. Overall, our suggestions are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You should choose to upgrade your LTS when you can test thoroughly, your stack supports the next LTS, and staying current aligns with your strategy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose expanded security maintenance when you need stability, lack upgrade resources, or require patches without version mandates.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You should &lt;strong&gt;only &lt;/strong&gt;accept running without updates if you can reasonably maintain minimal risk exposure, can implement strong compensating controls, and have explicit documented approval.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The worst outcome is no decision at all, allowing support coverage to lapse through inaction.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;What should you do today?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Run &lt;strong&gt;pro security-status&lt;/strong&gt; to assess your current coverage. Identify which packages will lose standard support and when.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Ubuntu 20.04 or earlier, standard support has ended. Those systems need decisions now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-pullquote"&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Explore Ubuntu Pro options at &lt;a href="http://ubuntu.com/pro"&gt;ubuntu.com/pro&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/contact-us/form?product=pro"&gt;contact our team&lt;/a&gt; to discuss your requirements.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Read more:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/about/release-cycle"&gt;Understand Ubuntu release cycle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/pro/linux-patch-management-with-pro"&gt;See which packages Ubuntu Pro supports&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/security/security-standards"&gt;Run Ubuntu in high-security environments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Lidia Luna Puerta (Lidia Luna Puerta)</author><category>backporting</category><category>EOL</category><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 09:15:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Showcasing open design in action: Loughborough University design students explore open source projects</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/showcasing-open-design-in-action-loughborough-university-design-students-explore-open-source-projects</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Last year, we collaborated with two design student teams from Loughborough University in the UK. These students were challenged to work on open source project briefs. Team 1 focused on non-code contributions, while Team 2’s brief was to create a unified documentation experience, giving them a chance to apply their design skills to real-world problems [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="372" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 660px) 660px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_660/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F42a7%2Fimage.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F42a7%2Fimage.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F42a7%2Fimage.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F42a7%2Fimage.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_660/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F42a7%2Fimage.png 660w" width="660"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year, we collaborated with two design student teams from Loughborough University in the UK. These students were challenged to work on open source project briefs. Team 1 focused on non-code contributions, while Team 2’s brief was to create a unified documentation experience, giving them a chance to apply their design skills to real-world problems within the open source ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We reached out to &lt;a href="https://www.lboro.ac.uk/schools/design-creative-arts/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"&gt;Loughborough University School of Design and Creative Arts&lt;/a&gt; because there is a real need for non-code contributions in the open source ecosystem. Design thinking, which goes beyond the code to consider the user experience, is paramount if we want open source to thrive and gain ever more widespread adoption. Each team tackled a unique challenge that reflects the growing need for design thinking in open source, where developers have traditionally led, but where a better user experience is now urgently needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post celebrates their thoughtful work, sharing reflections from their design journey, and invites others to consider contributing to open source projects!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interested in checking out the project briefs yourself? The briefs are open for anyone to explore, think about, and attempt to solve. Whether you’re thinking of ideas, writing them on a napkin, or developing your solution, there are no limitations to your creativity here! &lt;a href="https://assets.ubuntu.com/v1/7bd9c15e-project_briefs_for_universities.pdf" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"&gt;Get the briefs here&lt;/a&gt; (PDF).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Team 1: Improving design approachability in open source&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Project brief: Increase designer participation in open source projects and contributing non-code contributions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Objective: Help improve how designers engage with open source projects by lowering barriers to entry and encouraging more meaningful design contributions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Team members: &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/mirunaalini-meera-alagarajah-3755211b3/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"&gt;Mirunaalini Alagarajah&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/giridharpabbati/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"&gt;Giridhar pabbati&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/jiarui-he-579796336/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"&gt;Jiarui He&lt;/a&gt;, Lechen Zou, &lt;a href="https://sdcapgshow2025.lboro.ac.uk/student/clara-lin/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"&gt;Clara Lin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Check out their &lt;a href="https://assets.ubuntu.com/v1/52567bad-final_slides_cocreate_5_canonical_compressed.pdf" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"&gt;project presentation&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Reflection from the team&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h4 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;What was it like working on a real open source design challenge?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project really challenged us as a team, testing our collaboration, adaptability, and time management skills. Tackling a real client brief helped us engage more deeply with the problem and understand its real-world context. Working with Canonical was particularly motivating, as it gave us the sense that our efforts were contributing to something genuinely impactful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;What surprised you most about open source?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a team, we realised we hadn’t truly thought about the various barriers designers encounter when engaging with open source projects. We also found it fascinating that many designers are quite protective of their work, which makes open sharing a real challenge. It created a unique tension –everyone wanted to learn from others, but few felt comfortable giving their work away for free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;What design decision did your team focus on and why?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We used insights from our user research to guide our design direction, ensuring that each decision was grounded in evidence. Prototyping allowed us to test various design details and components, which helped us refine our approach and gain a much clearer sense of direction. As a team, we brought diverse backgrounds and skill sets—those with stronger design experience naturally took the lead in developing and refining the visual aspects of the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;How has this experience influenced how you think about design and collaboration?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On reflection, there were many possible directions we could have taken, but in hindsight, grounding our decisions in user insights and continuous testing helped align the team around a clear vision. Regular client feedback was invaluable in refining our approach and ensuring we stayed true to user needs. Additionally, leveraging each team member’s strengths allowed us to work more efficiently and make the most of our diverse skills. Overall, it was a valuable experience that taught us how to collaborate rapidly and effectively to address a real-world brief.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Team 2: Unifying Juju’s documentation ecosystem&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Project brief: Improve the accessibility, clarity, and cohesiveness of Juju’s documentation to enhance user experience and encourage adoption.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Objective: Reimagining how users discover and learn about Juju (Canonical’s open source application orchestration engine for the deployment, integration, and lifecycle management) by improving the documentation experience. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Team members:&lt;a href="https://sharvarirai.framer.website/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"&gt; Sharvari Rai&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/bavraj-virdi-120030254/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"&gt;Bavraj Virdi&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/xinya-wang-79297b390/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"&gt;Xinya Wang&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/siying-fan-324508368/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"&gt;Siying Fan&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/qingwan-yu-b138a8368/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"&gt;Qingwan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/qingwan-yu-b138a8368/"&gt; Yu&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Check out their &lt;a href="https://www.figma.com/deck/sl4Je3lBfLQIAHLTKVVJsK/Canonical?node-id=1-126&amp;amp;viewport=-88%2C-46%2C0.52&amp;amp;t=mKdUYsomHF7yzYyI-1&amp;amp;scaling=min-zoom&amp;amp;content-scaling=fixed&amp;amp;page-id=0%3A1" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"&gt;project presentation&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Reflection from the team&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h4 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;What were your first impressions about the problem space?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we were first introduced to the project, our initial reaction was that the brief felt highly technical and complex, with unfamiliar terms like charms, operators, and Kubernetes. As none of us came from a technical or programming background, the documentation space felt like a challenge for us was the learning curve of diving in and understanding what is in the documentation and what it means. We struggled to identify a clear starting point and to understand the overall purpose of Juju beyond the jargon. Since the platform is mainly aimed at developers, it was difficult at first to relate to or imagine user needs. Despite that, this initial confusion actually helped us empathise with potential users facing similar barriers, and it highlighted the importance of clarity and structure in the documentation. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;What was your approach to designing a more unified documentation experience?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our approach began with breaking down the brief into simpler terms and mapping the current documentation ecosystem so we could better understand the challenges. As a team, we created personas for both new and experienced users, which helped us think about different entry points and the level of guidance each group might need. We then sketched user journeys to highlight pain points and challenges. From there, we focused on developing a single, structured information architecture with clearer pathways for learning and troubleshooting.  The aim was to allow users to move confidently between different sections without having to relearn how to navigate each time. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;What were the biggest challenges your team encountered during the project?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main challenge was the steep learning curve of immersing ourselves in the technical complexity of the Juju ecosystem and its vast open source documentation, especially since most of us came from non-technical backgrounds. We had to quickly grasp the product and its entire linked ecosystem. As direct access to real users was limited, we relied heavily on secondary data, community forums, and the creation of personas to accurately map realistic pain points. Our constant goal was to balance technical accuracy with the required user-centred clarity, which pushed us to fundamentally rethink how developer documentation can effectively guide users without overwhelming them. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;What skills or takeaways are you bringing with you from this experience?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project was a major lesson in how to embrace and navigate ambiguity. This was a truly crucial learning experience when dealing with an unfamiliar domain, evolving product documentation, and diverse stakeholder needs. We significantly strengthened our ability to translate dense technical research into clear, actionable design recommendations. We also honed our communication and collaboration skills as a team, successfully aligning our user-focused vision with Canonical’s roadmap. Most importantly, we learned that user advocacy is vital even in highly technical environments, and that our focus is ultimately on humanising complex systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;🎉Congratulations to both teams!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We would like to thank and congratulate both teams for their creativity, thoughtful research, and commitment to enhancing open source experiences through design. They approached complex, open-ended problems with maturity and curiosity, and their outcomes were both inspiring and practical. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their fresh perspectives also reminded us of the value of questioning assumptions and looking at familiar challenges through new eyes, reinforcing how much we as practitioners can learn from emerging designers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We hope these projects have not only added valuable work to their portfolios but also opened doors to future engagement with open source communities. We encourage them (and any other designer out there) to continue exploring open source, contributing through design, and helping shape more inclusive, user-friendly technologies!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Interested in running a project like this?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you part of a university looking to bring open source design into your curriculum? &lt;a href="https://canonical.design/blog/open-design-the-opportunity-design-students-didnt-know-they-were-missing" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"&gt;We’re looking for academic partners&lt;/a&gt; who want to give students meaningful, real-world experiences while contributing to the global open source ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reach out at &lt;a href="mailto:opendesign@canonical.com" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"&gt;opendesign@canonical.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn more at &lt;a href="https://canonical.design/blog/open-design-the-opportunity-design-students-didnt-know-they-were-missing" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"&gt;Canonical.design&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Join the Canonical design team&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re looking for designers who care about craft and how systems work under the hood. At Canonical, design sits at the intersection of UX, engineering, and open source where we shape cohesive, accessible experiences across cloud, desktop, and IoT products.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you enjoy solving complex problems and turning technical depth into clarity, explore our open roles: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://canonical.com/careers/web-and-design" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"&gt;canonical.com/careers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Miguel Divo (Miguel Divo)</author><category>Design</category><category>open design</category><category>University</category><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 11:09:04 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Canonical Ubuntu and Ubuntu Pro now available on AWS European Sovereign Cloud</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/ubuntu-aws-european-sovereign-cloud</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Canonical announced it is a launch partner for the AWS European Sovereign Cloud, with Ubuntu and Ubuntu Pro now available. This new independent cloud for Europe enables organizations to run secure, enterprise workloads with full operational autonomy and EU data residency. By combining the performance and expanded security coverage of Ubuntu Pro with AWS sovereignty controls, customers can meet stringent EU regulatory requirements while continuing to innovate at scale.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;January 15, 2026 – Canonical, the publisher of Ubuntu and provider of open source security, support, and services, announced today that it is a launch partner for the AWS European Sovereign Cloud, a new independent cloud for Europe, with Ubuntu and Ubuntu Pro now available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical’s Ubuntu Pro delivers a securely designed, stable, and enterprise-ready foundation for open source innovation while providing customers with the same security, availability, and performance they expect from AWS. This enables customers to meet stringent operational autonomy and data residency requirements within the European Union (EU).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The AWS European Sovereign Cloud is a fully featured, independently operated sovereign cloud backed by strong technical controls, sovereign assurances, and legal protections designed to meet the needs of European governments and enterprises. The AWS European Sovereign Cloud infrastructure is entirely located within the EU and operates independently from existing regions. Customers using the AWS European Sovereign Cloud will benefit from the full power of AWS including the same services portfolio, security, availability, performance, familiar architecture, APIs, and innovations such as the AWS Nitro System.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The AWS European Sovereign Cloud represents a significant step forward for organizations operating under EU regulatory frameworks,”&lt;/em&gt; said Cindy Goldberg, VP Cloud and Silicon Partnerships at Canonical. &lt;em&gt; By combining the performance and the expanded security coverage of Ubuntu Pro with AWS’s sovereignty controls and technical assurances, we’re delivering the compliance support and innovation our customers need to accelerate their digital transformation while meeting stringent EU regulatory requirements.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discover Ubuntu and Ubuntu Pro on the AWS European Sovereign Cloud today on the AWS EC2 console. Launch now on the &lt;a href="https://eusc-de-east-1.console.amazonaws-eusc.eu/ec2/home?region=eusc-de-east-1#LaunchInstances:ami=ami-0a121bf2036630575"&gt;European Sovereign Cloud EC2 console&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;About Canonical &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical, the publisher of Ubuntu, provides open source security, support, and services. Our portfolio covers critical systems, from the smallest devices to the largest clouds, from the kernel to containers, from databases to AI. With customers that include top tech brands, emerging startups, governments and home users, Canonical delivers trusted open source for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn more at https://canonical.com/&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Canonical (Canonical)</author><category>AWS</category><category>Sovereign cloud</category><category>Ubuntu</category><category>Ubuntu Pro</category><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 22:06:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How to build DORA-ready infrastructure with verifiable provenance and reliable support</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/build-dora-ready-infrastructure-with-verifiable-provenance</link><description>&lt;p&gt;DORA requires organizations to know what they run, where it came from, and how it’s maintained. Learn how to build infrastructure with verifiable provenance.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;The Digital Operational Resilience Act (DORA) came into force across the EU on January 17, 2025, fundamentally changing how financial institutions must approach infrastructure and technology assets resilience. Its requirements around ICT risk management, operational resilience, and third-party oversight signal a broader shift that will ripple across regulated industries worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At its core, DORA demands something deceptively simple: organizations must know exactly what they’re running, where it came from, and how to fix it when something breaks. For technical teams managing complex stacks spanning bare metal, the OS, kernel, and applications, this translates into a hard requirement for provenance: transparent, verifiable lineage from source code all the way up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;The provenance problem: you can’t verify what you can’t see&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traditional vendor stacks create a fundamental compliance problem: they’re opaque by design. When you deploy a proprietary solution, you’re accepting someone else’s assurances about what’s inside. You can’t inspect the source code. You can’t verify the build process. You can’t independently validate that a security patch actually addresses the vulnerability it claims to fix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Software Bills of Materials (SBOMs) have emerged as an important transparency tool and represent progress, they fail to solve this fundamental inspection problem. An SBOM tells you what components are present in proprietary software, but you still can’t examine the source code itself or verify the build process yourself. For regulated organizations facing requirements like DORA, this creates a compliance gap, where you can document dependencies but cannot truly verify their integrity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DORA explicitly requires financial entities to maintain oversight of their ICT infrastructure, including third-party dependencies. So, how do you maintain oversight of something you can’t inspect?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open source becomes essential here. With open source software:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You get reproducible inspectability all the way down the supply chain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can trace every component back to the developer who wrote it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can verify builds&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can audit changes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can understand exactly what’s running in your environment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;The single developer problem (and why Ubuntu Pro matters)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s the uncomfortable truth about modern infrastructure: critical components in your stack likely trace back to a single developer somewhere on the internet, maintaining a library in their spare time. An estimate, based on analysis of &lt;a href="http://ecosyste.ms"&gt;ecosyste.ms&lt;/a&gt; data, shows that a relatively small group, on the order of ten thousand people, supports the majority of the world’s open source software users. In the Tidelift 2024 State of the Open Source Maintainer survey, 61% of unpaid maintainers reported working alone on their projects. When the Heartbleed vulnerability was discovered in 2014, OpenSSL—used by 66% of web servers at the time—was maintained by just a handful of volunteers, only one working full time, with the project receiving about $2,000 in annual donations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These individual maintainers are doing heroic work. But from a resilience perspective, it’s a risk. What happens when that developer moves on? Gets burned out? Simply stops maintaining the package?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is worsening: in 2024, almost 60% of maintainers reported having quit or considered quitting their maintenance work, with many citing burnout, insufficient compensation, and overwhelming demands on their time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Investing in open source is a form of infrastructure security: it reduces your dependence on unpaid, solo maintainers and builds sustainable maintenance pipelines with professional support, timely security patching, and long-term viability. When enterprises pay for Ubuntu Pro, part of that funding flows back into the open source ecosystem through Canonical’s upstream engineering work and direct financial support for the projects Ubuntu depends on.​&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canonical does not just repackage open source; our engineers contribute features and fixes upstream across the projects shipped in Ubuntu, and we commit security maintenance for components long after their upstream end of life, such as continuing to backport OpenSSL 1.1.1 fixes for supported Ubuntu releases. Ubuntu Pro packages this ecosystem investment into a single subscription: up to 15 years of security maintenance for thousands of open source packages, plus the assurance that Canonical is actively collaborating with and funding the communities behind them. Instead of betting your resilience on a single unpaid maintainer, you get a vendor whose business model is aligned with keeping that open source infrastructure secure and sustainable over the long term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;From responsibility to assurance: system-level, not vendor-level&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a fundamental difference between a vendor taking responsibility for their products and a platform providing assurance for your entire system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When an Ubuntu Pro customer from the financial industry asked, “How do we get all machines FIPS-enabled and CIS-compliant?”, that’s not a question about a single application. It’s a question about system-level security compliance across thousands of machines, down to the operating system and the metal beneath it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu Pro answers this by providing a single, verifiable stack with end-to-end provenance. The focus shifts from trusting individual vendors to establishing a unified security posture where every layer is supported, patched, and verifiable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For finance organizations, this changes the conversation from “Do we trust this vendor?” to “Can we verify and validate our entire infrastructure up to the application layer?” The answer needs to be yes, and you need documentation to prove it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;The DORA advantage: knowing what you don’t know&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discovering what you don’t know proves more challenging than fixing known compliance issues. What packages are actually running in production? Which versions? What’s their patch status? What potential exposures might an auditor find during their next review?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Ubuntu Pro, you get continuous visibility, security maintenance and support:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Complete inventory: Enumerate exactly what’s running across your infrastructure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provenance tracking: Every package has verifiable lineage back to source&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Continuous patching: Both main and universe repository packages receive security updates&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compliance tooling: Built-in capabilities for CIS hardening, FIPS certification, and compliance reporting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Beyond compliance: building for what comes next&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think of compliance as the baseline, not the goal. While DORA is a regulatory requirement for financial services in the EU, smart organizations across industries are using it as a model for their own resilience programs. The principles it codifies, operational resilience, supply chain transparency, systematic risk management, are universal concerns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trajectory is clear: more regulation, more scrutiny, more demands for transparency and provenance. When your industry’s equivalent of DORA arrives (and it will), you need infrastructure that can already demonstrate:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Verifiable provenance for every component in your stack&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Long-term support commitments backed by professional teams&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;System-level security compliance down to the OS and infrastructure layer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Complete source code transparency and documented patching processes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu Pro applies these principles to open source infrastructure, combining transparent components with long-term security maintenance and support so your stack is ready for whatever comes next.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn more about other security standards we support: &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/security/security-standards"&gt;ubuntu.com/security/security-standards&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-pullquote"&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/contact-us/form?product=pro"&gt;Get in touch&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/pro/free-trial"&gt;start a 30-day Ubuntu Pro free trial&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.eiopa.europa.eu/digital-operational-resilience-act-dora_en"&gt;Digital Operational Resilience Act (DORA) – EIOPA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/eli/reg/2022/2554/oj/eng"&gt;Regulation (EU) 2022/2554 – EUR-Lex&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://blog.tidelift.com/maintainer-burnout-is-real"&gt;Tidelift 2024 State of the Open Source Maintainer Report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://socket.dev/blog/the-unpaid-backbone-of-open-source"&gt;The Unpaid Backbone of Open Source – Socket&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/thebakersinstitute/2014/04/23/what-heartbleed-means-for-critical-infrastructure-2/"&gt;Critical infrastructure for the Web – Forbes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/blog/canonical-thanks-dev-giving-back-to-open-source-developers"&gt;Canonical + thanks.dev&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Lidia Luna Puerta (Lidia Luna Puerta)</author><category>Compliance</category><category>DORA</category><category>Security</category><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 09:53:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Deploy your Spring Boot application to production</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/deploy-spring-application-to-production</link><description>&lt;p&gt;In this article we walk through the steps required to deploy a Spring Boot application to production using Juju and Kubernetes. The goal is to showcase the integration of the application with essential services like PostgreSQL for database management and Traefik for ingress control.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;In a previous article, we covered how easy it is to create &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/blog/spring-boot-containers-made-easy"&gt;Spring Boot containers&lt;/a&gt; with Rockcraft. So the next logical step is to deploy and operate your application in a production environment. The Juju ecosystem is the key to making this process straightforward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this article we walk through the steps required to deploy a Spring Boot application to production using Juju and Kubernetes. The goal is to showcase the integration of the application with essential services like PostgreSQL for database management and Traefik for ingress control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="1080" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1920px) 1920px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F91ec%2FDiagram-deploy-spring-production-16_9.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F91ec%2FDiagram-deploy-spring-production-16_9.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F91ec%2FDiagram-deploy-spring-production-16_9.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F91ec%2FDiagram-deploy-spring-production-16_9.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F91ec%2FDiagram-deploy-spring-production-16_9.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F91ec%2FDiagram-deploy-spring-production-16_9.png 1920w" width="1920"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ordinarily, deploying and operating Spring Boot containers is easier said than done. Any non-trivial application will require integrations with other software components like databases, message brokers, and authentication services. Some of these components are complex to operate. What’s more, your application will need to be exposed to the outside world. And for Day 2 operations, you’ll also need to perform routine maintenance and properly monitor your application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, Juju provides a strong ecosystem composed of a multitude of high quality software operators that enables deployment, integration and lifecycle management at any scale, on any infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the release of the Spring Boot framework extensions for &lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/rockcraft/stable/"&gt;Rockcraft&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/charmcraft/stable/"&gt;Charmcraft&lt;/a&gt;, if your application follows the 12-factor methodology best practices, you can benefit from the Juju ecosystem out of the box.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are developing a Spring Boot application we recommend you to try out the &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/blog/devpack-spring-support-ubuntu"&gt;devpack support for Spring&lt;/a&gt; and then follow &lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/charmcraft/latest/tutorial/kubernetes-charm-spring-boot/"&gt;this tutorial to write your Spring Boot charm&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But without further ado, let’s see how it all works by charming &lt;a href="https://spring-petclinic.github.io/"&gt;spring-petclinic&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Set up a developer machine with Canonical Kubernetes and Juju&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will start with a virtual machine created from scratch using &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/multipass"&gt;Multipass&lt;/a&gt; and prepare our development machine with the help of the &lt;a href="https://github.com/canonical/concierge"&gt;Concierge&lt;/a&gt; tool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Launch the new virtual machine and shell into it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="p-code-snippet"&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__block--icon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;multipass launch --cpus 4 --disk 30G --memory 4G --name blogpost 24.04&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__block--icon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;multipass shell blogpost&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will provision the testing machine with Concierge, which will install and configure Rockcraft, Charmcraft, Canonical Kubernetes and Juju. Besides that, we will update the load balancer to serve under the machine’s main IP and install an OCI image registry:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="p-code-snippet"&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__block--icon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo snap install --classic concierge&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__block--icon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo concierge prepare -p k8s --charmcraft-channel latest/edge&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__block--icon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;PREFSRC=$(ip -4 -j route get 2.2.2.2 | jq -r '.[] | .prefsrc')&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__block--icon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo k8s set load-balancer.cidrs=$PREFSRC/32&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__block--icon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;curl https://raw.githubusercontent.com/canonical/spring-petclinic/refs/heads/resources/registry.yaml | kubectl apply -f - &lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Get spring-petclinic application&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://spring-petclinic.github.io/"&gt;spring-petclinic&lt;/a&gt; is the app we’ll be charming. It’s a sample application created by the Spring team to demonstrate a real-world web app using the Spring Framework. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clone the spring-petclinic repository. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="p-code-snippet"&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__block--icon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;git clone https://github.com/canonical/spring-petclinic.git&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__block--icon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;cd spring-petclinic&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following the &lt;a href="https://github.com/canonical/spring-petclinic"&gt;spring-petclinic repository instructions&lt;/a&gt;, you can build a jar and run it with the command line. It is quite easy, but clearly not production ready, even the database in-memory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Create the rock&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s prepare a rock – a compliant OCI image – for the application. We could use either Maven or Gradle to build the application, but for this example we will use Maven. From the spring-petclinic directory, remove the Gradle artifacts and initialize the rockcraft project:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="p-code-snippet"&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__block--icon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;rm -rf build.gradle gradlew gradle&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__block--icon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;rockcraft init --profile spring-boot-framework&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pack the rock and upload it to the OCI registry :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="p-code-snippet"&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__block--icon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;ROCKCRAFT_ENABLE_EXPERIMENTAL_EXTENSIONS=True rockcraft pack&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__block--icon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;rockcraft.skopeo copy --insecure-policy --dest-tls-verify=false oci-archive:spring-petclinic_0.1_amd64.rock docker://localhost:32000/spring-petclinic:0.1&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point we have a fully compliant OCI image. But to fully integrate with the Juju ecosystem we need a charm, a software operator. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Create the charm&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s build it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="p-code-snippet"&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__block--icon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;mkdir charm&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__block--icon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;cd charm&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__block--icon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;charmcraft init --profile spring-boot-framework --name spring-petclinic&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we want to use PostgreSQL instead of an in-memory database, add the following lines to the file &lt;code&gt;charmcraft.yaml&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="p-code-snippet"&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__blocklanguage-yaml"&gt;
&lt;code&gt;&lt;strong style="color: #204A87;"&gt;requires&lt;/strong&gt;:
  &lt;strong style="color: #204A87;"&gt;postgresql&lt;/strong&gt;:
    &lt;strong style="color: #204A87;"&gt;interface&lt;/strong&gt;: postgresql_client
    &lt;strong style="color: #204A87;"&gt;optional&lt;/strong&gt;: false
    &lt;strong style="color: #204A87;"&gt;limit&lt;/strong&gt;: 1&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And we are ready to create a charm. Pack it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="p-code-snippet"&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__block--icon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;CHARMCRAFT_ENABLE_EXPERIMENTAL_EXTENSIONS=True charmcraft pack&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Let’s test it&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point we have a charm for spring-petclinic that will integrate seamlessly with PostgreSQL. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s test it with a new Juju model in a Kubernetes cloud:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="p-code-snippet"&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__block--icon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;juju add-model spring-petclinic&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__block--icon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;juju deploy ./spring-petclinic_amd64.charm spring-petclinic --resource app-image=localhost:32000/spring-petclinic:0.1 --config app-profiles=postgres
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deploy PostgreSQL and Traefik and integrate with spring-petclinic:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="p-code-snippet"&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__block--icon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;juju deploy postgresql-k8s --trust&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__block--icon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;juju integrate spring-petclinic postgresql-k8s&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="p-code-snippet"&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__block--icon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;juju deploy traefik-k8s --trust&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__block--icon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;juju integrate spring-petclinic traefik-k8s&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a while, your production ready application will be ready for use! You can check it with the command &lt;code&gt;juju status&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="646" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1676px) 1676px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1676/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F8199%2Fterminal_screenshot-deploy-spring-production-screenshot.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F8199%2Fterminal_screenshot-deploy-spring-production-screenshot.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F8199%2Fterminal_screenshot-deploy-spring-production-screenshot.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F8199%2Fterminal_screenshot-deploy-spring-production-screenshot.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F8199%2Fterminal_screenshot-deploy-spring-production-screenshot.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F8199%2Fterminal_screenshot-deploy-spring-production-screenshot.png 1920w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1676/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F8199%2Fterminal_screenshot-deploy-spring-production-screenshot.png 1676w" width="1676"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can get the URL of the application with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="p-code-snippet"&gt;
&lt;pre class="p-code-snippet__block--icon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;juju run traefik-k8s/0 show-proxied-endpoints&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And just like that, you can use it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="740" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1295px) 1295px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1295/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fd600%2Ffirefox_screenshot-1.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fd600%2Ffirefox_screenshot-1.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fd600%2Ffirefox_screenshot-1.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fd600%2Ffirefox_screenshot-1.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fd600%2Ffirefox_screenshot-1.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fd600%2Ffirefox_screenshot-1.png 1920w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1295/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fd600%2Ffirefox_screenshot-1.png 1295w" width="1295"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The application is running in a Kubernetes cluster, with Trafik acting as an ingress. Your spring-petclinic application is now using PostgreSQL to store its data. The Charmed PostgreSQL K8s has provided credentials for the database to the spring-petclinic application, and is ready to be operated in a production-grade environment. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not bad for a start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Get in touch&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you have a project or setup where you want to employ this solution? If you have any questions about the 12-factor tooling for Rockcraft and Charmcraft, reach out in our &lt;a href="https://matrix.to/#/#12-factor-charms:ubuntu.com"&gt;Matrix Channel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;What’s next?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/charmcraft/latest/tutorial/kubernetes-charm-spring-boot/"&gt;Follow the Spring Boot tutorial&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/charmcraft/stable/howto/manage-charms/#publish-a-charm-on-charmhub"&gt;Publish your charm in CharmHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Javier de la Puente (Javier de la Puente)</author><category>charm</category><category>Charms</category><category>cloud</category><category>Juju</category><category>juju charms</category><category>kubernetes</category><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 12:00:54 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Minimal Ubuntu Pro: lean images backed by enterprise-grade security</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/minimal-ubuntu-pro-on-public-clouds</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The security landscape is growing continually in complexity. Whatever industry you work in, your organization has to contend with evolving threats and ever-stricter compliance requirements, whilst at the same time facing pressure to build fast and scale smart. This is especially true when innovating on the public cloud.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Deploy Minimal Ubuntu Pro across AWS, Azure, and Google Cloud&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The security landscape is growing continually in complexity. Whatever industry you work in, your organization has to contend with evolving threats and ever-stricter compliance requirements, whilst at the same time facing pressure to build fast and scale smart. This is especially true when innovating on the public cloud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Minimal Ubuntu Pro is built to help you meet those challenges. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Minimized attack surface. Enhanced security.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Users of Ubuntu value its accessibility, robustness, and mature ecosystem. That’s why Canonical works with major cloud vendors to make optimized Ubuntu images available on their platforms. This includes Minimal Ubuntu – Ubuntu images which are optimized to have the smallest footprint possible and make security more straightforward. Minimal Ubuntu Pro builds on these images by making security in the public cloud more efficient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu Pro is Canonical’s comprehensive subscription for open source security. Through Ubuntu Pro, organizations receive up to 15 years of security maintenance (with the legacy add-on), tools for compliance automation, and kernel live patching. Minimal Ubuntu Pro brings these features to Minimal Ubuntu, combined with a convenient, metered per-hour billing on Amazon EC2, Google GCP and Microsoft Azure. By bringing these two technologies together, customers can combine the smallest Ubuntu footprint with enterprise-grade security and compliance features. It is the perfect starting point for automated cloud deployments in your production environments. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether you are deploying cloud workloads, containers, or regulated infrastructure, Minimal Ubuntu Pro offers a unique blend of minimalism, control, and long-term support, without sacrificing compatibility or flexibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Why security-aware companies choose Minimal Ubuntu Pro&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Perfect for cloud operations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Minimal Ubuntu Pro builds on the strengths of Minimal Ubuntu: the smallest Ubuntu base image for VMs and containers. Its lightweight design enables faster provisioning and scaling, with a 50% smaller image size and 40% faster boot times. At the same time, it retains optimizations for leading cloud hypervisors (AWS, GCP, Azure, KVM, LXD) through a custom kernel, drivers, and agents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re running microservices, containerized applications, or ephemeral workloads, this is the image you want on the public cloud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tight control over installed software&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Minimal Ubuntu Pro is fully compatible with the entire Ubuntu package ecosystem. Applications that already work on classic Ubuntu Server will retain full compatibility, provided dependencies are installed. You decide exactly what your environment includes, with the added benefit of extended security coverage for critical and high CVEs, including third-party open source packages, delivered through the Ubuntu Pro subscription.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This fine-grained control is crucial for DevSecOps practices, automated CI/CD pipelines, and infrastructure-as-code workflows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reduced attack surface by design&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every unnecessary package is a potential risk. Minimal Ubuntu Pro ships with only the essential components required to boot and connect, dramatically reducing exposure. Fewer packages mean fewer CVEs to track, fewer patches to apply, and less overall maintenance. For example, documentation, text editors, and locale files are removed, leaving only what’s necessary to run your workloads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This makes Minimal Ubuntu Pro ideal for teams building golden images, zero-trust environments, or security-hardened cloud instances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Enterprise-grade hardening and compliance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu Pro unlocks advanced security and compliance features, including up to 15 years of CVE patching across both Main and Universe repositories for Ubuntu LTS releases, optional FIPS 140-3 certified cryptographic modules for government compliance, and CIS and DISA-STIG hardening profiles for regulated environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether your target is FedRAMP, NIST, HIPAA, or another framework, Minimal Ubuntu Pro helps accelerate compliance with trusted tooling and validated configurations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Available on all the major cloud platforms&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Minimal Ubuntu Pro is available on AWS, Azure, and GCP. Whichever platform you choose to innovate on, Minimal Ubuntu Pro offers consistency and robustness:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Comes with an optimized kernel tailored for each cloud environment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Certified across all supported virtual machine types and instance families&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maintains the same deep cloud integration as standard Ubuntu Server, including support for telemetry, fleet management, and platform-specific services&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;How to get it&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;On AWS:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using AWS Marketplace by searching for “&lt;a href="https://aws.amazon.com/marketplace/search/results?searchTerms=Minimal+Ubuntu+Pro&amp;amp;CREATOR=565feec9-3d43-413e-9760-c651546613f2&amp;amp;filters=CREATOR"&gt;Minimal Ubuntu Pro&lt;/a&gt;”  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using AWS CLI:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;aws ssm get-parameters --names /aws/service/canonical/ubuntu/pro-minimal/$VERSION/stable/current/amd64/hvm/ebs-gp2/ami-id&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where &lt;code&gt;$VERSION&lt;/code&gt; is one of 20.04, 22.04 or 24.04 (For 24.04 you need to change &lt;code&gt;ebs-gp2&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;ebs-gp3&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;On GCP:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using Google Cloud Console by selecting “Ubuntu Pro” in the operating system selection and “&lt;strong&gt;Ubuntu 2x.04 LTS Minimal Pro&lt;/strong&gt;” as the version.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using Google Cloud Shell and booting a VM, specifying “&lt;code&gt;image=projects/ubuntu-os-pro-cloud/global/images/ubuntu-minimal-pro…&lt;/code&gt;”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;On Azure:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Selecting &lt;strong&gt;Minimal Ubuntu Pro Azure&lt;/strong&gt; Marketplace or Portal:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For 20.04 LTS, use the dedicated&lt;a href="https://marketplace.microsoft.com/en-us/product/virtual-machines/canonical.0001-com-ubuntu-pro-minimal-focal"&gt; Ubuntu Pro Minimal 20.04&lt;/a&gt; listing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For 22.04 and 24.04 LTS, find the unified&lt;a href="https://marketplace.microsoft.com/en-us/product/virtual-machines/canonical.ubuntu-22_04-lts"&gt; Ubuntu 22.04 LTS&lt;/a&gt; or&lt;a href="https://marketplace.microsoft.com/en-us/product/virtual-machines/canonical.ubuntu-24_04-lts"&gt; 24.04 LTS&lt;/a&gt; offers and select the “&lt;strong&gt;Ubuntu Pro Minimal&lt;/strong&gt;” plan.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using CLI:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;pre class="wp-block-code"&gt;&lt;code&gt;az vm create \
  --name $VIRTUAL_MACHINE_NAME \
  --resource-group $RESOURCE_GROUP_NAME \
  --image $UBUNTU_IMAGE_URN \
  --generate-ssh-keys&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where &lt;code&gt;$UBUNTU_IMAGE_URN&lt;/code&gt; is either:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;Canonical:0001-com-ubuntu-pro-minimal-focal:pro-minimal-20_04-lts:latest&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;Canonical:ubuntu-22_04-lts:ubuntu-pro-minimal:latest&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;Canonical:ubuntu-24_04-lts:ubuntu-pro-minimal:latest&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Next steps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Minimal Ubuntu Pro offers a powerful combination of performance, precision, and protection. It’s a practical solution for organizations seeking to scale confidently while adhering to the most stringent security and compliance standards. With Minimal Ubuntu Pro, you gain precise control over your environment, resulting in a minimal attack surface and expanded security coverage against critical and high-severity CVEs from the moment it’s deployed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get Minimal Ubuntu Pro 24.04 on &lt;a href="https://aws.amazon.com/marketplace/pp/prodview-4yqsoi5afvjqu"&gt;AWS&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href="https://marketplace.microsoft.com/en-us/product/virtual-machines/canonical.ubuntu-24_04-lts"&gt;Azure&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href="https://console.cloud.google.com/compute/instancesAdd?imageId=5466964067713924514&amp;amp;imageProjectId=ubuntu-os-pro-cloud"&gt;GPC&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Further reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://documentation.ubuntu.com/public-cloud/all-clouds-explanation/ubuntu-base-and-minimal-images/"&gt;Ubuntu base and minimal images – Public Cloud documentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://wiki.ubuntu.com/Minimal"&gt;What is Minimal Ubuntu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Carlos Bravo (Carlos Bravo)</author><category>AWS</category><category>azure</category><category>GCP</category><category>minimal ubuntu</category><category>Ubuntu Pro</category><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 15:07:56 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>London called, and the world answered: creating a Summit without borders</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/london-called-and-the-world-answered-creating-a-summit-without-borders</link><description>&lt;p&gt;When we announced that the Ubuntu Summit 25.10 would be a remote event, we knew we were taking a big step. We asked ourselves: how can we capture the spirit of an in-person community event and convey its energy through a screen? How can we connect the circle of friends from all over the world? [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;When we announced that the Ubuntu Summit 25.10 would be a remote event, we knew we were taking a big step. We asked ourselves: how can we capture the spirit of an in-person community event and convey its energy through a screen? How can we connect the circle of friends from all over the world? We certainly had an ambitious quest with the Quokka edition of the Ubuntu Summit!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"&gt;&lt;div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper"&gt;
&lt;iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="304" loading="lazy" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/gKMz7FVPJjo?feature=oembed" title="Ubuntu Summit 25.10 | Highlights" width="540"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption class="wp-element-caption"&gt;Ubuntu Summit 25.10 | Highlights&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;The digital hallway track&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have been to an in-person event, you most likely have enjoyed the moments between talks. Those unscripted, unplanned parts of a conference create the hallway track experience. And while presentations bring valuable knowledge the hallway track creates connections, opens the door to collaboration and community building. Our quest was noble but challenging: we wanted to ensure that no matter where you live, you had a front row seat to the future of open source. And what we saw from you was incredibly inspiring. You tuned in, engaged with the speakers, and really created the most welcoming and fun remote hallway track. The Ubuntu Discourse exploded with activities! We loved seeing the &lt;a href="https://discourse.ubuntu.com/t/ubupets-share-a-photo/69964"&gt;lovely UbuPets&lt;/a&gt;, your awesome &lt;a href="https://discourse.ubuntu.com/t/screenshot-showcase-share-a-photo/70239/23"&gt;screenshot showcase&lt;/a&gt;, and the engagement with the polls. We also embarked together on an easter egg hunt throughout the event, with all sorts of Ubuntu related logos hidden in the stream.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Open source, open music&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We know that every quest needs an epic soundtrack! In our case, the soundtrack had to be as open source as the event. The amazing folks at &lt;a href="https://www.lorenzosmusic.com/"&gt;Lorenzo’s Music&lt;/a&gt; took on the challenge and put together the Creative Commons stream that  kept the energy high throughout the event. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was an incredible experience that took a lot of work and coordination between talented artists, and we’re not just talking about music. &lt;a href="https://www.sylvia-ritter.com/"&gt;Sylvia Ritter&lt;/a&gt; provided her fantastic artwork for an amazing visual experience. Ryno crafted the stream for both days and piped it through to the Lorenzo’s Music YouTube channel, together with song metadata. Last but not least, Creative Commons artists played live sets at the end of each day. Want to tune in and relive the sounds of the summit? Check out &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xDqJvZXkqFc"&gt;day one&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PpyNRlyc1rw"&gt;day two&lt;/a&gt; Creative Commons music streams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="1143" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 2027px) 2027px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_2027/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F0e13%2FUbuntu-Summit-25.10-CCMUSIC.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F0e13%2FUbuntu-Summit-25.10-CCMUSIC.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F0e13%2FUbuntu-Summit-25.10-CCMUSIC.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F0e13%2FUbuntu-Summit-25.10-CCMUSIC.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F0e13%2FUbuntu-Summit-25.10-CCMUSIC.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F0e13%2FUbuntu-Summit-25.10-CCMUSIC.png 1920w" width="2027"/&gt;&lt;figcaption class="wp-element-caption"&gt;Ubuntu Summit 25.10 Creative Commons music stream.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;The extended effect&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, the Ubuntu Summit was about global connection, going beyond London and the main stage. The event also connected us to the local Ubuntu circles from all over the world. The Ubuntu Summit Extended events are what turned a remote conference into a global celebration of the spirit of Ubuntu: “I am because we all are”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The great thing about the extended events was that each community put their own spin on the event. In Uyo, the &lt;a href="https://discourse.ubuntu.com/t/ubuntu-25-10-summit-extended-uyo-edition/71564"&gt;Nigerian community gathered 40 developers&lt;/a&gt;, celebrated the release of Ubuntu 25.10, and hosted their own set of talks. The &lt;a href="https://discourse.ubuntu.com/t/ubuntu-summit-25-10-portugal-extension/71092"&gt;Ubuntu Portugal community&lt;/a&gt; did not just watch the stream. They synced up between Porto and Lisbon, shared meals, discussions, sightseeing, in a true representation of the spirit of Ubuntu. In Windhoek, the &lt;a href="https://discourse.ubuntu.com/t/ubuntu-25-10-summit-extended-namibia/74741"&gt;Namibian community&lt;/a&gt; organized a gathering of local open source enthusiasts and embraced the spirit of the new Ubuntu Summit experience. Over in Thessaloniki, the &lt;a href="https://eiosifidis.blogspot.com/2025/10/ubuntu-summit-extended-25.10-release-party.html"&gt;Greek community&lt;/a&gt; transformed the University of Macedonia into a buzzing hub of discussion and discovery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From university halls to hackerspaces, you proved that while the signal was digital, the connection was human.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="1600" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 2000px) 2000px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_2000/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fdde1%2FUbuntu-Summit-25.10-extended-collage.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fdde1%2FUbuntu-Summit-25.10-extended-collage.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fdde1%2FUbuntu-Summit-25.10-extended-collage.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fdde1%2FUbuntu-Summit-25.10-extended-collage.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fdde1%2FUbuntu-Summit-25.10-extended-collage.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fdde1%2FUbuntu-Summit-25.10-extended-collage.png 1920w" width="2000"/&gt;&lt;figcaption class="wp-element-caption"&gt;Ubuntu Summit Extended events organized by local communities.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Talks that took us to the stars… or was it Mars?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ubuntu Summit is a showcase for the innovative and the ambitious, and Ubuntu Summit 25.10 delivered some of our most audacious talks yet. If you missed the live stream, do not worry! You can find the &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLwFSk464RMxmyKN2yob1dcIbrUuJupDQQ"&gt;Ubuntu Summit 25.10 playlist on YouTube&lt;/a&gt; covering Life, the Universe, and Everything!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don’t know where to start, we have a few suggestions for you:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://discourse.ubuntu.com/t/doom-in-space/67019"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOOM in Space&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; We always say Ubuntu is everywhere, but &lt;strong&gt;Ólafur Waage&lt;/strong&gt; proved it by running DOOM on the European Space Agency’s OPS-SAT satellite. This talk perfectly captured the spirit of the Ubuntu Summit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://discourse.ubuntu.com/t/elevating-the-linux-desktop-with-cosmic-de/67250"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elevating The Linux Desktop with COSMIC DE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Victoria Brekenfeld&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Carl Richell&lt;/strong&gt; inspired us with the impressive COSMIC desktop environment, showing us how Rust is elevating the Linux desktop experience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://discourse.ubuntu.com/t/are-we-stuck-with-the-same-desktop-ux-forever/67253"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are We Stuck with the Same Desktop UX Forever?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Scott Jenson&lt;/strong&gt; challenged us to think bigger about our interfaces. His talk was a masterclass on breaking free from old paradigms, and why open source is the perfect playground for the next generation of desktop UX.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="1600" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 2000px) 2000px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_2000/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fdfd4%2FUbuntu-Summit-25.10-talks-collage.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fdfd4%2FUbuntu-Summit-25.10-talks-collage.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fdfd4%2FUbuntu-Summit-25.10-talks-collage.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fdfd4%2FUbuntu-Summit-25.10-talks-collage.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fdfd4%2FUbuntu-Summit-25.10-talks-collage.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fdfd4%2FUbuntu-Summit-25.10-talks-collage.png 1920w" width="2000"/&gt;&lt;figcaption class="wp-element-caption"&gt;Ubuntu Summit 25.10 talks.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Thank you to our global circle of friends&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether you were &lt;a href="https://ubu.link/ubuntusummit-extended"&gt;organizing a watch party&lt;/a&gt; in Lisbon, debating the future of AI on Discourse, or just enjoying the stream with a cup of tea at home, &lt;strong&gt;thank you! &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You proved that the Ubuntu Summit is more than a venue; it is a community. By going remote, we didn’t step back, we reached out. And because of you, we empowered more voices and sparked more ideas than ever before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ubuntu Summit 25.10 is a wrap, but the clock is already ticking for the Ubuntu Summit 26.04 adventure. Until then, keep the conversation going on Discourse, enjoy the playlist, and if you are feeling innovative and ambitious, &lt;a href="https://ubu.link/ubuntusummit-cfp"&gt;submit a talk!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><author>ilvipero (ilvipero)</author><category>Ubuntu</category><category>Ubuntu Summit</category><category>ubuntu summit 25.10</category><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 14:46:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Canonical announces Ubuntu support for the NVIDIA Rubin platform</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/nvidia-vera-rubin-ubuntu-support</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Official Ubuntu support for the NVIDIA Rubin platform, including the NVIDIA Vera Rubin NVL72 rack-scale systems, announced at CES 2026 CES 2026, Las Vegas. – Canonical, the publisher of Ubuntu, is pleased to announce official support for the NVIDIA Rubin platform and the latest distributions of the new NVIDIA Nemotron 3 open models.&amp;nbsp; As AI [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Official Ubuntu support for the NVIDIA Rubin platform, including the NVIDIA Vera Rubin NVL72 rack-scale systems, announced at CES 2026&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;CES 2026, Las Vegas.&lt;/em&gt; – Canonical, the publisher of Ubuntu, is pleased to announce official support for the NVIDIA Rubin platform and the latest distributions of the new &lt;a href="https://www.nvidia.com/en-us/ai-data-science/foundation-models/nemotron/"&gt;NVIDIA Nemotron&lt;/a&gt; 3 open models. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As AI workloads transition from small-scale proof of concepts to massive-scale AI factories, the need for a stable, high-performance operating system substrate has never been greater. Ubuntu provides that foundation, unifying the NVIDIA Vera CPU, NVIDIA Rubin GPU, and &lt;a href="https://www.nvidia.com/en-us/networking/products/data-processing-unit/"&gt;NVIDIA BlueField-4 DPU&lt;/a&gt; into a cohesive execution environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;AI democratization requires more than powerful silicon; it needs a secure, frictionless environment from cloud to edge&lt;/em&gt;,” said Justin Boitano, Vice President, Enterprise AI Products, NVIDIA. “&lt;em&gt;Our work with Canonical ensures enterprises can deploy the NVIDIA Rubin platform, including the rack-scale Vera Rubin NVL72, on the Ubuntu foundation they already trust, streamlining the path from development to production with enterprise-grade security, and removing friction so organizations can innovate with confidence.&lt;/em&gt;“&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;Our collaboration with NVIDIA reinforces Canonical’s mission to democratize AI&lt;/em&gt;,” said Cindy Goldberg, VP Cloud and Silicon Partnerships at Canonical. “&lt;em&gt;By unifying the CPU, GPU, and DPU into a single, cohesive Ubuntu execution environment, we are making it easier to build private or sovereign clouds and the next generation of intelligent applications. Enterprises can build for the future on a secure foundation they trust.&lt;/em&gt;“&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First-class Arm support for Vera Rubin&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NVIDIA Vera Rubin NVL72 rack presents a scalable architecture for integrated AI compute, pairing the custom Arm-based Vera CPU with the Rubin GPU. In Ubuntu 26.04, Arm is a first-class citizen with x86 performance parity. Canonical is integrating critical upstream features including Nested Virtualization and MPAM (Memory System Resource Partitioning and Monitoring). These tools enable providers to partition memory bandwidth and cache at the hardware level, ensuring predictable performance for multi-tenant AI workloads. This infrastructure will be further reinforced with native Arm support in&lt;a href="https://canonical.com/maas/blog/openstack-with-sunbeam-for-medium-scale-cloud-infrastructure"&gt; OpenStack Sunbeam&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/data/spark"&gt;Apache Spark&lt;/a&gt;, allowing data engineers to run end-to-end pipelines on Arm-native silicon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, Ubuntu serves as the host OS for &lt;a href="https://www.nvidia.com/en-us/data-center/mission-control/"&gt;NVIDIA Mission Control&lt;/a&gt; software, which accelerates every aspect of infrastructure operations — from configuring deployments and integrating with facilities to managing clusters and workloads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Streamlined inference with Nemotron inference snaps&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deploying large language models (LLMs) often involves complex dependency management and version conflicts. To solve this, Canonical has introduced &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/blog/canonical-releases-inference-snaps"&gt;inference snaps&lt;/a&gt;. In a recent &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/live/rR3TpJvM150?si=MNWEIdBTXz_B6Eeu"&gt;livestream with the NVIDIA Developer community&lt;/a&gt;, Canonical’s team presented inference snaps for DGX Spark, showing how a single snap install command brings silicon-optimized AI models to every Ubuntu machine. To further this effort, Canonical will be collaborating with the NVIDIA team on packaging and distribution of the NVIDIA Nemotron-3 family of open models, starting with Nano models. Packaging these models using inference snaps provides a containerized, immutable environment that includes all necessary libraries and runtimes, ensuring that it is optimized for the new NVIDIA platforms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BlueField-4 and scalable storage&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Performance of the Rubin platform is further amplified by its data pipeline. Canonical is recommitting to the NVIDIA BlueField-4 DPU as an important networking and security component of NVIDIA platforms. With 64 NVIDIA Grace CPU cores and 800G/s throughput, BlueField-4 makes scaling AI Factories even more efficient. Ubuntu serves as a foundational environment for &lt;a href="https://developer.nvidia.com/networking/doca"&gt;NVIDIA DOCA&lt;/a&gt;  – allowing for seamless offloading of networking, storage, and security tasks from the Vera CPU to the DPU.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In collaboration with storage partners, Canonical is ensuring that Ubuntu’s storage subsystem is optimized for the GPUDirect Storage capabilities of BlueField-4. This enables high-speed data access between NVMe storage and Rubin GPU memory, eliminating bottlenecks. Whether deploying on-premises or in a sovereign cloud, the combination of Ubuntu and BlueField-4 provides the bare-metal isolation and hardware-root-of-trust necessary for secure, multi-tenant AI infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Learn more&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Visit us at CES booth #10562 in LVCC, North Hall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find out more about &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/nvidia"&gt;Canonical’s collaboration with NVIDIA.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Canonical (Canonical)</author><category>AI</category><category>AI/ML</category><category>nvidia</category><category>NVIDIA AI Enterprise</category><category>Ubuntu</category><pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 23:15:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Meet Canonical at CES 2026: A trusted foundation for your device lifecycle</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/canonical-at-ces-2026</link><description>&lt;p&gt;This year, the Canonical team will be at Booth #10562 in the North Hall, we will be demonstrating how Ubuntu Core, Ubuntu Pro for Devices, and our partner ecosystem help you accelerate development, ensure reliability, and simplify the lifecycle of your connected fleets.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;CES 2026 is here, bringing together the technologies defining the next generation of connected devices. With thousands of exhibitors showcasing everything from software-defined vehicles to industrial robotics, Canonical is focusing on a core challenge shared across these industries: how to scale deployments and maintain devices securely over the long term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, the Canonical team will be at Booth #10562 in the North Hall, we will be demonstrating how Ubuntu Core, Ubuntu Pro for Devices, and our partner ecosystem help you accelerate development, ensure reliability, and simplify the lifecycle of your connected fleets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sneak peek: What you can expect at the Canonical booth this year&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At our booth, we’re showcasing solutions that support the full device lifecycle, from secure production deployment and long-term maintenance to enabling AI workloads at the edge. Our experts will be on hand to walk through real-world use cases and architectures powering modern connected fleets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ubuntu Pro for Devices: Managing your device journey&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Security maintenance is a process, not a one-time fix. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’ve been keeping up with the EU Cyber Resilience Act (CRA)  and its long list of requirements for potentially expensive long-term maintenance, you’re likely already on the lookout for partners or solutions who can help simplify compliance. We’ll be on-hand to introduce Ubuntu Pro for Devices, a comprehensive subscription service which comfortably delivers long-term security maintenance across device lifecycles in line with the most stringent security standards. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through automated patching and IoT OTA updates, Ubuntu Pro for Devices can help you bridge the gap between development and operations. This helps keep your embedded Linux deployments security-maintained for up to 15 years, helping you address regulations like the Cyber Resilience Act.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ubuntu Core: Powering intelligent devices&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reliability is the priority for embedded systems. At the Canonical booth, we’ll demonstrate this with Ubuntu Core, Canonical’s immutable, fully containerised operating system built for embedded and edge devices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu Core uses strict application confinement and transactional updates to help ensure updates are applied safely, with a significantly reduced risk of failure. The operating system and applications are updated independently, helping devices remain stable and recoverable in production environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Designed for long-term reliability in the field, Ubuntu Core provides a secure foundation for deploying, updating, and maintaining intelligent devices at scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AI: Optimizing your workloads everywhere&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AI workloads place different demands on infrastructure as they move from data centers to edge devices. Teams often need to balance performance, power use, hardware constraints, and long-term maintenance once systems are in production.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At CES 2026, Canonical is showing how Inference Snaps and close work with silicon partners help address these challenges. The demo focuses on running AI inference efficiently across different hardware targets, while keeping deployments consistent and maintainable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether you are deploying computer vision pipelines or running large language models (LLMs) at the edge, Canonical helps you:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Package AI inference workloads in a consistent, repeatable way&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tune performance for specific hardware platforms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deploy and update models securely over the lifetime of a device fleet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This approach supports AI workloads that need to evolve over time, without rebuilding infrastructure for every hardware or model change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://canonical.com/solutions/ai" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"&gt;Learn more about Canonical’s approach to AI from cloud to edge&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Automotive: Driving the future&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The software-defined vehicle requires agility. &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/blog/future-of-infotainment-canonical-at-ces-2026"&gt;In our automotive showcase, we demonstrate how Anbox Cloud delivers Android infotainment with ultra-low latency using WebRTC streaming and support for 8K displays. &lt;/a&gt; Instead of relying on emulators or hardware-bound benches, you can deploy full Android IVI systems on any cloud and stream them to any screen in real time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By virtualizing Android Automotive OS in the cloud, we help OEMs and Tier 1 suppliers speed up infotainment development and testing on demand, without waiting for physical hardware. This brings the smartphone experience to the dashboard with greater efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;From high-performance robotics, to billions of AI quality control checks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our platform is only as strong as the ecosystem built upon it. This year, we are hosting demos with our partners who use Canonical solutions to solve real-world industry problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NVIDIA: Witness the power of physical AI&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are excited to participate in the NVIDIA Passport Program. Visit the Canonical booth to join in for a chance to win great prizes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will showcase the CES 2026 Innovation Honoree, &lt;a href="https://www.nvidia.com/en-us/autonomous-machines/embedded-systems/jetson-thor/"&gt;NVIDIA Jetson Thor,&lt;/a&gt; running physical AI workloads. &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/blog/nvidia-jetson-thor-ubuntu-support?_gl=1*1xbybtf*_gcl_au*MTEyODY5NjM3NS4xNzYxMzgzNTExLjUwNzY5ODI0NS4xNzYyNzg5NTA2LjE3NjI3ODk1MDU.*_ga*ODQ5NzU4MTQ3LjE3NjQ0MTc4MjI.*_ga_5LTL1CNEJM*czE3NjQ1MTkwOTgkbzUkZzEkdDE3NjQ1MjUwMTQkajU1JGwwJGgw"&gt;This demo highlights how NVIDIA’s hardware and Ubuntu’s real-time kernel capabilities drive high-performance inference in robotics&lt;/a&gt;. Our booth will also feature &lt;a href="https://www.nvidia.com/en-us/products/workstations/dgx-spark/"&gt;NVIDIA DGX Spark &lt;/a&gt;with local inference and fine tuning, proving that enterprise-grade AI is accessible and scalable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more information, please visit &lt;a href="https://www.nvidia.com/en-us/events/ces/"&gt;NVIDIA at CES 2026.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="658" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1600px) 1600px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1600/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F537c%2Fimage.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F537c%2Fimage.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F537c%2Fimage.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F537c%2Fimage.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F537c%2Fimage.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F537c%2Fimage.png 1920w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1600/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F537c%2Fimage.png 1600w" width="1600"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elementary: See industrial reliability in action&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://canonical.com/case-study/elementary-ai-machine-vision"&gt;See AI-powered visual inspection in action with Elementary. &lt;/a&gt;We will feature a live AI vision system performing visual inspections on real-world parts. The demo shows how operators configure inspections, review results, and gain actionable insights through an intuitive interface, all running on Ubuntu Core.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This all-in-one showcase demonstrates how Elementary uses the immutability and confinement of Ubuntu Core to deliver high-precision quality assurance on the factory floor. Visitors can also explore how inspection updates and new AI models are securely delivered over the air, enabling AI vision to move quickly from pilot to production.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At scale, Ubuntu Core enables Elementary to manage thousands of edge devices across eight Fortune 500 manufacturers, performing more than 1 billion AI-powered inspections per year. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="1518" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1600px) 1600px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1600/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F6ed4%2Fimage-1.jpeg" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F6ed4%2Fimage-1.jpeg 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F6ed4%2Fimage-1.jpeg 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F6ed4%2Fimage-1.jpeg 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F6ed4%2Fimage-1.jpeg 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F6ed4%2Fimage-1.jpeg 1920w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1600/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F6ed4%2Fimage-1.jpeg 1600w" width="1600"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The live system demonstrates how AI vision can quickly move from pilot to standard work&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rightware: Experience the future of infotainment development &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/blog/future-of-infotainment-canonical-at-ces-2026"&gt;In our automotive showcase, we are partnering with Rightware to demonstrate an integration between their Kanzi UI framework and Anbox Cloud.&lt;/a&gt; This demo illustrates how developers can visualize and test rich automotive user interfaces in the cloud, while streamlining the development cycle for next-generation cockpit experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Come see our high fidelity Kanzi-based UI cockpit rendered and streamed at 8K. This addresses the common pain point of infotainment developers: slow iteration caused by limited access to physical prototypes. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="900" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1600px) 1600px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1600/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2be4%2Fimage.jpeg" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2be4%2Fimage.jpeg 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2be4%2Fimage.jpeg 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2be4%2Fimage.jpeg 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2be4%2Fimage.jpeg 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2be4%2Fimage.jpeg 1920w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1600/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2be4%2Fimage.jpeg 1600w" width="1600"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Widescreen 8K infotainment CES demo&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bosch Rexroth: Bridging IT and OT with ctrlX AUTOMATION&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discover how Bosch Rexroth is removing the barriers between machine control, IT, and OT. We will showcase applications running on the ctrlX CORE, demonstrating the power of Ubuntu Core in an industrial setting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://canonical.com/blog/bosch-rexroth-adopts-ubuntu-core-and-snaps-for-app-based-ctrlx-automation-platform"&gt;With Ubuntu Core, ctrlX AUTOMATION apps run with strictly confined dependencies in snaps, ensuring isolation and stability.&lt;/a&gt; You will see how this architecture enables automated security updates and robust rollbacks, allowing machine builders to maintain reliability on the factory floor without needing manual engineering intervention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Grundium: Meeting stringent medical security standards &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://canonical.com/case-study/grundium-ubuntu-pro-for-devices"&gt;See Grundium’s Ocus® microscope slide scanner and learn how it meets the rigorous demands of the medical industry.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Medical devices require a continuously monitored security posture, which is why Grundium uses &lt;strong&gt;Ubuntu Pro for Devices&lt;/strong&gt; to ensure their Ocus® scanners meet stringent requirements throughout their lifecycle. Built on a foundation of 150 open source components requiring rigorous risk analysis, these devices rely on Ubuntu Pro to secure a supply chain of over &lt;strong&gt;25,000 packages&lt;/strong&gt; with a single subscription. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By using automated patching to enable up to &lt;strong&gt;10 years of support&lt;/strong&gt;, Grundium delivers a trustworthy platform for critical remote diagnostics, ensuring thousands of scanners remain operational worldwide without burdening their development teams&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Join us at CES 2026&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether you are a decision-maker solving the puzzle of device lifecycle management, or you are interested in the future of embedded operating systems, our team of engineers and industry experts will be happy to discuss your specific challenges at Booth #10562, North Hall throughout the event. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Date: January 6–9, 2026&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Venue: Las Vegas Convention Center (LVCC)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Booth: #10562, North Hall&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t leave your CES 2026 experience to chance. Secure time with our team to discuss how we can help you build, deploy, and maintain your connected devices. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://calendar.app.google/ao4AHxoZWGkx4wsBA"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Book a meeting with our team&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;More reading and resources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://canonical.com/solutions/iot-and-devices#get-in-touch"&gt;Contact Us&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://canonical.com/solutions/iot-and-devices"&gt;Check out our IoT webpage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://canonical.com/case-study/elementary-ai-machine-vision"&gt;Explore how Canonical helped Elementary deliver more than 1 billion inspections annually &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/blog/future-of-infotainment-canonical-at-ces-2026"&gt;Explore our Rightware CES 2026 showcase in the first blog of the series&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/nvidia"&gt;Check out the Enterprise-Ready AI solutions powered by Canonical and NVIDIA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Canonical (Canonical)</author><category>CES</category><category>events</category><pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 14:27:10 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A better way to provision NVIDIA BlueField DPUs at scale with MAAS</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/a-better-way-to-provision-nvidia-bluefield-dpus-at-scale-with-maas</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The recent release of MAAS 3.7 introduces a significant new capability: the ability to provision NVIDIA BlueField Data Processing Units (DPUs) directly through their Baseboard Management Controller (BMC),&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;MAAS 3.7 has been &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/maas/docs/release-notes-and-upgrade-instructions#p-9229-version-37-release-notes"&gt;officially released&lt;/a&gt; and it includes a bunch of cool new features. One of the capabilities that stands out most, without a doubt, is the support for NVIDIA Bluefield DPU provisioning directly through the Baseboard Management Controller (BMC).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, what are BlueField DPUs? This leads to a broader question: what are DPUs and SmartNICs, and why is the ability to provision them through the BMC a significant advancement?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s deep dive into all this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;DPUs and SmartNICs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today’s data centers face increasing demands: higher throughput, more tenants, rising security threats and the growing complexity of cloud-native environments. Traditional servers struggle when networking, storage, and security functions consume more and more CPU cycles intended for applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This trend has driven the industry toward &lt;strong&gt;infrastructure hardware acceleration&lt;/strong&gt;, where specialised processors handle tasks traditionally executed by the host CPU. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A SmartNIC was the logical solution, a Network Interface Card (NIC) enhanced with onboard compute and acceleration hardware. Unlike traditional NICs, which simply move packets, SmartNICs can process, filter, and &lt;strong&gt;accelerate data&lt;/strong&gt; directly on the card  before it ever reaches the host CPU.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Data Processing Unit (DPU) goes further. It is effectively a small, fully functional server on a PCIe card, with its own CPU cores, memory, operating system, security capabilities, and hardware offload engines. DPUs are designed to take over the entire &lt;strong&gt;infrastructure plane&lt;/strong&gt; (networking, storage, security and management) so that the host CPU can focus entirely on application workloads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="530" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_webp,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_720/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F4a37%2FDPU.webp" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_webp,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F4a37%2FDPU.webp 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_webp,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F4a37%2FDPU.webp 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_webp,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F4a37%2FDPU.webp 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_webp,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_720/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F4a37%2FDPU.webp 720w" width="720"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DPUs are increasingly common in cloud, telco, and high-performance environments such as AI training clouds. Typical use cases include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Network acceleration/offloading&lt;/strong&gt;: Implementing Software-Defined Networking (SDN) for OpenStack, LXD/MicroCloud, Kubernetes, and bare-metal, including distributed firewall functionality.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Storage acceleration/offloading&lt;/strong&gt;: running agents (like Ceph RBD) to present distributed storage as a standard device.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Secure root of trust&lt;/strong&gt;: providing authentication, attestation and isolation, and monitoring the host’s processes and network connections.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kubernetes on the DPU&lt;/strong&gt;: using the DPU as a worker node for packaging and orchestrating network, storage, and security functions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;NVIDIA Bluefield&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.nvidia.com/en-us/networking/products/data-processing-unit/"&gt;NVIDIA BlueField&lt;/a&gt; family is NVIDIA’s line of DPUs. This family showcases how NVIDIA has expanded from the original SmartNIC concept into a full platform that supports not only infrastructure offloads but also advanced telemetry, security analytics, and AI-centric workloads, all designed to free up host CPUs and accelerate core operations in modern and distributed data centers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BlueField-3 is particularly relevant here. It was the first DPU of the family that incorporated a Baseboard Management Controller (BMC), allowing remote monitoring and control of the DPU. A BMC is a dedicated, independent micro-controller embedded on a server’s motherboard (in this case embedded on the DPU) that provides out-of-band management capabilities. It enables administrators to remotely monitor hardware health (like temperature and power), control the server’s power state (turn it on/off or reboot), and access the console.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This independence is what makes clean, automated provisioning possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;How should you provision a DPU: through the BMC or through the host?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Historically, DPUs were provisioned &lt;strong&gt;through the host&lt;/strong&gt;. The host OS booted first, ran vendor tools, and then configured or imaged the DPU. While workable for early deployments, this approach tightly couples the DPU lifecycle to the host, makes recovery harder, and becomes operationally fragile at scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With a built-in BMC, a second option is available: provisioning the DPU directly &lt;strong&gt;through the BMC&lt;/strong&gt;. In this model, the DPU is treated like an independent server. The BMC can power it on, flash firmware, install an operating system, run configuration workflows, and make it operational, independently of the host.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Benefits of BMC-based provisioning include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consistent “day-0” initialization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Host-agnostic workflows (no dependency on a running OS)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easier recovery and re-provisioning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cleaner separation between host workloads and infrastructure functions, enabling a &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/blog/canonical-and-nvidia-bluefield-4-a-foundation-for-zero-trust-high-performance-infrastructure"&gt;zero-trust deployment model&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Better suitability for large-scale or zero-touch environments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the provisioning method &lt;strong&gt;MAAS now supports&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;MAAS now supports BlueField provisioning through the BMC&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://canonical.com/maas"&gt;MAAS (Metal as a Service)&lt;/a&gt; is Canonical’s open-source platform for managing physical servers with cloud-like automation. It provides a central place to discover, commission, deploy and repurpose machines. It offers repeatable workflows that make large-scale infrastructure easier to operate and an infrastructure-as-code approach to programmatically automate the whole data center.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the release of MAAS 3.7, BlueField DPUs can now be provisioned directly through their BMC. This allows MAAS to treat the DPU as an independent server, without relying on the host operating system to initialise or configure it. Behind the scenes, MAAS handles power control, device relationships, and the order of operations required to bring both the host and the DPU online correctly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prior to this release, MAAS supported BlueField provisioning only through-the-host, meaning that MAAS needed the host to be provisioned and operational first, before even being able to provision the DPU. While functional, this approach made DPU lifecycle management dependent on the host and limited automation in larger environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This new workflow gives operators a cleaner and more predictable way to manage DPUs. By integrating BlueField provisioning into standard MAAS processes, it becomes simpler to adopt DPUs across the data centre and maintain them consistently alongside the rest of the hardware fleet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Get started with MAAS 3.7&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can start experimenting with BlueField provisioning today by installing or upgrading to MAAS 3.7. The easiest way to get started with MAAS is to follow the &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/maas/docs/maas-in-thirty-minutes"&gt;comprehensive 30-min tutorial&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For DPU provisioning details and supported workflows, check out the &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/maas/docs"&gt;MAAS documentation&lt;/a&gt; and the dedicated &lt;a href="https://discourse.maas.io/t/how-to-deploy-dpus-in-maas/15418"&gt;BlueField provisioning guide.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Give it a try and &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/maas#get-in-touch"&gt;let us know&lt;/a&gt; how it works in your environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if you are interested in getting Canonical’s support and compliance for MAAS, you can explore &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com/pro"&gt;Ubuntu Pro&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/maas#get-in-touch"&gt;get in touch&lt;/a&gt; with our team. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Further reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://maas.io"&gt;Canonical MAAS (Metal as a Service)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://maas.io/tutorials/build-a-maas-and-lxd-environment-in-30-minutes-with-multipass-on-ubuntu"&gt;Build a MAAS and LXD environment in 30 minutes with Multipass on Ubuntu&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://maas.io/docs"&gt;MAAS documentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content:encoded><author>David Beamonte (David Beamonte)</author><category>bare metal</category><category>bluefield</category><category>data center</category><category>dpu</category><category>MAAS</category><pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 17:14:05 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>MicroCeph: why it’s the superior MinIO alternative (and how to use it)</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/microceph-why-its-the-superior-minio-alternative</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, the team at MinIO moved the open source project into maintenance mode and will no longer accept any changes. That means that no new features or enhancements will be added to MinIO, and existing issues &amp;#8212; according to the update &amp;#8212; will not be actively considered. Whilst MinIO brought a solid developer-friendly approach to [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;Recently, the team at MinIO moved the open source project into &lt;a href="https://github.com/minio/minio/commit/27742d469462e1561c776f88ca7a1f26816d69e2"&gt;maintenance mode&lt;/a&gt; and will no longer accept any changes. That means that no new features or enhancements will be added to MinIO, and existing issues — according to the update — will not be actively considered. Whilst MinIO brought a solid developer-friendly approach to object storage (S3) for many years, this update means that the project is unlikely to keep up with advancements in storage tech.  So, for developers hoping to stay at the cutting edge of object storage, and to take advantage of block and file storage, what’s the next step?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="2250" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 4000px) 4000px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_4000/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F752a%2FMicroCeph-minio-blog-1.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F752a%2FMicroCeph-minio-blog-1.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F752a%2FMicroCeph-minio-blog-1.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F752a%2FMicroCeph-minio-blog-1.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F752a%2FMicroCeph-minio-blog-1.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F752a%2FMicroCeph-minio-blog-1.png 1920w" width="4000"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ceph has set the standard as the trusted, production-worthy open source storage for over a decade. However, some users have found the upstream tooling complex to use; so, a couple of years ago we introduced MicroCeph as an opinionated and simple way to deploy Ceph.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the Micro name, there’s nothing missing. MicroCeph is fully-featured Ceph, with the same scale-out architecture, and block (RBD), file (CephFS, NFS), and object (S3, Swift) protocols. The positive difference is that MicroCeph offers simpler deployment, scaling, and day-2 operations. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since its release, adoption of MicroCeph has spread far and wide. Now, you’ll find it deployed in everything from single-node development environments and CI pipelines, to production-scale multi-PetaByte deployments, enabling organisations to manage ever increasing data storage needs. For developers looking for a MinIO alternative, MicroCeph could work for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Setting up your MinIO alternative: how to get started with MicroCeph&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this tutorial, we’ll walk through the steps to get a single node Ceph cluster up and running. We’ll also explain how to enable RGW (Rados Gateway), so that you can use the S3 API like you might have done with MinIO.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First you’ll need a single node or VM to try things out. And with MicroCeph being delivered as a Snap, you don’t have to be using Ubuntu OS – any Linux machine with snapd will work!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Begin by installing the latest stable version of MicroCeph:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo snap install microceph --channel=squid/stable&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the snap is downloaded and installed, we need to initialize the Ceph cluster:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo microceph cluster bootstrap&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can then check to see if the bootstrap was completed successfully: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo ceph status&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should see output similar to the example below. Don’t worry about HEALTH_WARN at this stage, that’s expected as we only have a single Monitor (MON) in the cluster and no Object Storage Daemons (OSDs).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="520" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 844px) 844px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_844/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fa80a%2Fimage-1.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fa80a%2Fimage-1.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fa80a%2Fimage-1.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fa80a%2Fimage-1.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fa80a%2Fimage-1.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_844/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fa80a%2Fimage-1.png 844w" width="844"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like any storage system, Ceph needs some disks to make it useful. In this scenario, we’ll add one file-based disk to get started. That’s perfect for testing and CI – but not ideal in production. For that you should use real disks, i.e. flash or spinning media. Find out more about which disks to use for MicroCeph in &lt;a href="http://microceph.com/"&gt;our documentation&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To add a file-based disk, input the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo microceph disk add loop,4G,1&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once again, we can check the status of the cluster. Here we can see that the OSD has been successfully added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="520" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 868px) 868px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_868/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F4e07%2Fimage.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F4e07%2Fimage.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F4e07%2Fimage.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F4e07%2Fimage.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F4e07%2Fimage.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_868/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F4e07%2Fimage.png 868w" width="868"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One more step that we need to carry out in this test, or demonstration configuration is to adjust the replication factor. This should &lt;strong&gt;never be done in production&lt;/strong&gt;, or with data that you care about: if the single disk fails, you will encounter data loss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To adjust the replication factor, input the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo microceph pool set-rf "" --size=1&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="658" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 1024px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1024/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F8bfc%2Fimage-1.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F8bfc%2Fimage-1.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F8bfc%2Fimage-1.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F8bfc%2Fimage-1.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F8bfc%2Fimage-1.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F8bfc%2Fimage-1.png 1920w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1024/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F8bfc%2Fimage-1.png 1024w" width="1024"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there is a warning, this can be ignored for now, as this is just a test environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Enabling RGW&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next step is to enable RGW so that we can use the S3 API.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo microceph enable rgw&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MicroCeph will take care of several things in this step: it’ll deploy the RGW daemon and create the pools needed for object meta-data and the objects themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can see those cluster changes by checking the cluster status again:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="642" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 974px) 974px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_974/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F6f35%2Fimage.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F6f35%2Fimage.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F6f35%2Fimage.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F6f35%2Fimage.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F6f35%2Fimage.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F6f35%2Fimage.png 1920w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_974/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F6f35%2Fimage.png 974w" width="974"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And also by listing the pools in the cluster:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo ceph osd pool ls&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="210" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 792px) 792px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_792/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F3ab3%2Fimage.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F3ab3%2Fimage.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F3ab3%2Fimage.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F3ab3%2Fimage.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_792/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F3ab3%2Fimage.png 792w" width="792"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, create a RGW user so that we can grant access to storage in the cluster:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo radosgw-admin user create --uid=user --display-name=user&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The command will provide output like the example below. Your application will need the access_key and secret_key to interact with the cluster – for example, to create buckets, as well as uploading and downloading objects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="506" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1338px) 1338px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1338/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fe1e8%2Fimage-1.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fe1e8%2Fimage-1.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fe1e8%2Fimage-1.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fe1e8%2Fimage-1.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fe1e8%2Fimage-1.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fe1e8%2Fimage-1.png 1920w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1338/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Fe1e8%2Fimage-1.png 1338w" width="1338"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can quickly find out the IP address of the RGW by checking MicroCeph’s status:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo microceph status&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="182" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 784px) 784px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_784/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2a03%2Fimage.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2a03%2Fimage.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2a03%2Fimage.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2a03%2Fimage.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_784/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2a03%2Fimage.png 784w" width="784"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then we can test the API endpoint using curl:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;curl http://&amp;lt;IP Address&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-full"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="118" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1600px) 1600px, 100vw" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1600/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Faf84%2Fimage.png" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_460/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Faf84%2Fimage.png 460w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_620/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Faf84%2Fimage.png 620w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1036/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Faf84%2Fimage.png 1036w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1681/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Faf84%2Fimage.png 1681w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1920/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Faf84%2Fimage.png 1920w, https://res.cloudinary.com/canonical/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto,fl_sanitize,c_fill,w_1600/https%3A%2F%2Fubuntu.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2Faf84%2Fimage.png 1600w" width="1600"/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here we can see that the API endpoint is responding – ready for you to create buckets, and start uploading and downloading files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many ways of interacting with object storage. Tools like &lt;a href="https://github.com/s3tools/s3cmd"&gt;s3cmd&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://github.com/boto/boto3"&gt;boto3&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://github.com/peak/s5cmd"&gt;s5cmd&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://cyberduck.io/s3/"&gt;cyberduck&lt;/a&gt; are all popular. Alternatively, your application may accept the access and secret keys to directly manage objects stored in an S3 compatible bucket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;MicroCeph beyond a MinIO alternative&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, this tutorial only provides a taster of what Ceph is capable of. Scaling up from one node is a very simple process, and ultimately, the cluster can be scaled to multiple petabytes if needed. And unlike MinIO, no other solution is needed if you require Block or File storage too! Find out how to perform a multi-node install in &lt;a href="https://canonical-microceph.readthedocs-hosted.com/v19.2.0-squid/how-to/multi-node/"&gt;our documentation&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The great thing about the MicroCeph snap is that, as part of Ubuntu and Canonical’s Long Term Support (LTS) commitment, it can be supported for up to 15 years from the release of the LTS. If you’re curious to find out how you can use MicroCeph in the long term, try our blog &lt;a href="https://canonical.com/blog/storage-for-kubernetes"&gt;explaining how to use MicroCeph as Kubernetes storage&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Philip Williams (Philip Williams)</author><category>ceph</category><category>Storage</category><pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 08:26:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Design and Documentation clinics at FOSDEM Fringe 2026</title><link>https://ubuntu.com//blog/design-and-documentation-clinics-at-fosdem-fringe-2026</link><description>&lt;p&gt;FOSDEM is one of the biggest and most exciting open source events of the year, held at the Solbosch campus of the Université Libre de Bruxelles (Brussels), Belgium. Thousands of open source contributors and enthusiasts attend, often with several folks from Canonical among them. The next one is coming quickly, with FOSDEM 2026 being held [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description><content:encoded>
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2026/"&gt;FOSDEM&lt;/a&gt; is one of the biggest and most exciting open source events of the year, held at the Solbosch campus of the Université Libre de Bruxelles (Brussels), Belgium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="has-medium-font-size"&gt;Thousands of open source contributors and enthusiasts attend, often with several folks from Canonical among them. The next one is coming quickly, with FOSDEM 2026 being held across the weekend of &lt;strong&gt;January 31st – February 1st&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the first time, a few of us from the Design and Documentation teams at Canonical are going to both attend and &lt;em&gt;organize&lt;/em&gt; a&lt;strong&gt; free&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2026/fringe/"&gt;FOSDEM Fringe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;event&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;on &lt;strong&gt;Monday February 2nd&lt;/strong&gt;, between 09:00 and 17:00.  Anyone who needs help with their open source work is invited, as are unaffiliated individuals who want to learn more about either Design or Documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;How we can help&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our fringe event includes both Design and Documentation clinics where attendees can ask questions and get the help they need to fix a problem, get a review, or create a solution. Items you might want to consider include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Design clinic:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UX/UI reviews:&lt;/strong&gt; Professional feedback on your CLI or GUI.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Workflow optimization:&lt;/strong&gt; Streamline how users interact with your tool.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Visualization:&lt;/strong&gt; Learn how to create and share your ideas.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Documentation&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;clinic:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Structure and strategy:&lt;/strong&gt; Organize and plan your content for better navigability.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tooling setup:&lt;/strong&gt; Pick and configure the right documentation tools.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Onboarding:&lt;/strong&gt; Make it easier for new contributors to join.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But these are just a guide. We’re up for any challenge!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 class="wp-block-heading"&gt;Register now&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When: &lt;/strong&gt;Monday 2nd February, between 09:00 and 17:00. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href="https://www.workatfirma.be/"&gt;Firma&lt;/a&gt;, Brussels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To give us some idea of numbers, we’re asking anyone who may want to attend to register their interest first. Please fill in the following form and we’ll be in touch:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSfJLEIb5zZ3gggdIWQiB6X2asTIEJ_07CPV077blzf9YJ0HCQ/viewform"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Documentation and Design Clinic @FOSDEM Fringe Attendance Form&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Questions? Find us on Matrix at &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://matrix.to/#/#design:ubuntu.com"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;#design:ubuntu.com&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt; and &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://matrix.to/#/#documentation:ubuntu.com"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;#documentation:ubuntu.com&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><author>Graham Morrison (Graham Morrison)</author><category>Design</category><category>documentation</category><category>Event</category><pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 09:24:45 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>